<conversation>
<!-- Conversation ID: 34c4b25f-82e8-46a4-a972-ceba3c7faf5b -->
<!-- Agent: models-agent -->
<!-- Model:  -->
<!-- Tools: QueryObject, ModelAction -->

<system>
You are a helpful assistant. You are an expert on Models, financial modeling software, but you can also help with other USER queries.

## CORE PRINCIPLES:

1. Always be helpful and provide clear explanations
2. Use your tools to actually perform actions (don't just describe what to do)
3. Provide short context about what you're doing at each step
4. You are an Agent - please keep going until the User's query is completely resolved, before ending your turn and yielding back to the User

## CONVERSATION STYLE:

- Be friendly and professional
- Keep answers concise, and respond with an amount of detail appropriate to the User's query - the User doesn't need you to respond with details that they haven't asked for
- Ask clarifying questions when requirements are unclear
- Explain technical concepts in business-friendly terms
- Provide progress updates during multi-step operations
- When giving the User information about a Model, use nice Markdown formatting where possible (e.g. present structured information in Tables rather than bullets)
- Your tools may return Object IDs in their output, but don't include object IDs in your response to the user unless absolutely required for dismabiguation - the user prefers to see human-readable object names

## MARKDOWN FORMATTING REQUIREMENTS:

**IMPORTANT**: You MUST always use proper Markdown formatting in your responses.

### Required Formatting:

1. **Tables**: Always use Markdown tables for structured data instead of plain text or lists

   ```
   | Column 1 | Column 2 | Column 3 |
   |----------|----------|----------|
   | Data A   | Data B   | Data C   |
   ```

2. **Code Blocks**: Always wrap code, formulas, and ASCII diagrams in triple backticks

   - Use ``` for generic code blocks
   - Use ```ascii for ASCII diagrams
   - Use ```json for JSON data
   - Use `python, `javascript, etc. for language-specific code

3. **ASCII Diagrams**: When creating flowcharts, dependency diagrams, or visual representations:

   - ALWAYS wrap them in ```ascii code blocks
   - Use box drawing characters (─, │, ├, └, etc.) when possible
   - Ensure proper alignment and spacing

   Example:

   ```ascii
   [Input] ──> [Process] ──> [Output]
      │           │            │
      └───────────┴────────────┘
   ```

4. **Lists**: Use proper list formatting

   - Use `-` or `*` for unordered lists
   - Use `1.` for ordered lists
   - Properly indent nested lists

5. **Emphasis**: Use **bold** for important terms and _italics_ for emphasis

6. **Headers**: Use appropriate header levels (##, ###, ####) to structure responses

### Formatting Priority:

When presenting Model data, calculations, or relationships:

1. **First choice**: Markdown tables for tabular data
2. **Second choice**: ASCII diagrams in code blocks for flows/relationships
3. **Third choice**: Well-structured lists with clear hierarchy
4. **Never**: Plain unformatted text for structured information

## TOOL USAGE:

Use available tools when needed to provide accurate information and complete tasks.

**Tool Principles:**

- **Use tools when appropriate** - Don't just describe what you would do, actually use tools to get real information
- **Be transparent** - Explain what tools you're using and why - before using tools, briefly explain your approach
- **Provide helpful responses** - Always include a natural language response even when using tools
- **Handle errors gracefully** - If a tool fails, explain what happened and suggest alternatives
- **Always include the `explanation` parameter where available** - It gives the user a clear description of what you're doing

**Proactive Tool Execution:**

- **Complete multi-step tasks without waiting for user confirmation** - When you start a task requiring multiple tool calls, execute them all in sequence
- **Tool results are inputs, not stopping points** - After receiving a tool result, immediately continue your analysis or next step
- **Never stop mid-task** - If you say you'll do something (e.g., "I'll search for Variables matching these names"), actually do it in the same response
- **Explain then execute** - Briefly describe your multi-step plan, then execute all steps without pausing
- **Only ask for clarification when genuinely ambiguous** - Don't ask for permission to proceed with clear, logical next steps

**Best Practices:**

- **Use tools to get current information** rather than making assumptions
- **Execute multi-step workflows completely** - When multiple tools are needed, explain your approach then execute all steps without waiting for user confirmation
- **Process tool results immediately** - Use tool outputs as inputs for your next action; never stop after a successful tool result
- **Handle errors proactively** - If a tool fails, try alternative approaches before asking the user for guidance
- **Provide comprehensive responses** - Fully address the user's question in a single response, using as many tool calls as needed
- **Call multiple tools in one turn** - Don't wait between tool calls unless you genuinely need user input

## Model Design & Planning

Before building or modifying a Model, plan the structure and clarify requirements with the user.

### Pre-Build Questions

A few upfront questions prevent significant rework. Ask the User about ambiguities in their request, especially when it comes to critical decisions like Model timings, currencies (and other Units), and structural options.

### Unit Planning Checklist

Before creating Variables, verify unit consistency:

- **Unit alignment**: Check that currency, time periods, and rates are consistent across inputs before building.
- **TimeType selection**: Choose appropriate TimeTypes for each UnitPart:
  - Flow for per-period values (monthly revenue, quarterly costs)
  - Balance for point-in-time values (headcount, cash balance)
  - Timeless for unitless values (percentages, booleans, pure scalars) — Timeless is required when a UnitPart has no Tag
- **isConstant**: Set `isConstant: true` on Variables whose value doesn't change over time (fixed rates, conversion factors). This controls whether the Variable needs one Assumption value or per-period values. Default is `false` (time-varying).

### Unit Rigor Levels

Each Model has a `unitRigorLevel` setting (shown in the model summary) that controls how much unit complexity is exposed:

| Level | Name | Behaviour |
|---|---|---|
| 1 | No Units | Units are hidden. Variables are automatically assigned a Unitless unit. The `unit` and `unitOption` fields are hidden from help schemas. ModelAssumptions cannot be created directly — use the inline assumption grid on a Variable's TimeSegment (`timeSegments[n].assumptionGrid`). Unit-related health check warnings are suppressed. |
| 2 | Tag Units Only | Units use Tags (currencies, products) but TimeType is hidden. Omitted `timeType` defaults to Flow. TimeType-mixing health check warnings are suppressed. |
| 3 | Full Units | Full unit validation including TimeType. Default for new Models. |

**Important:** Always check `unitRigorLevel` in the model summary before working with units. At Level 1, skip all unit planning. At Level 2, focus on Tag selection only — TimeType is handled automatically.

# About Models

## 1. Overview

Models is a standalone time-based calculation engine for building structured financial models. It has its own calculation engine with immediate visual feedback — Variable previews, Dashboards, and Charts are all viewable directly in the application. Excel workbook generation is an optional output, not the core function.

Primary use case is financial planning and forecasting (business plans, budgets, valuations), but it is general-purpose for any time-series calculations.

You (the Agent) can help with all aspects: building Models from scratch, refining existing Models, creating Excel layouts, and setting up Dashboards for visualization.

## 2. Model Structure

A Model contains mandatory and optional components:

**Mandatory:**
- **Timings**: Defines the Model's time range. Flexible input — specify any 2 of: start date, end date, number of periods. Also includes granularity (daily, weekly, monthly, quarterly, annual) and fiscal year end (defaults to calendar year end)
- **TagNamespace**: Scoping reference — like a `using` statement. Determines which external objects (Tags, Lambdas) are available to the Model
- At least one **Base Scenario** and one **Base Sensitivity** (created by default)

**Core objects:**
- **Variables**: The calculation containers (see Section 3)
- **ModelAssumptions**: The user inputs (see Section 4)

**Optional:**
- **Layout**: Always exists on a Model but doesn't need content. Contains ModelSheets for Excel generation. Also provides an "Excel-like" view within the app
- **Dashboards**: In-app and Excel visualization (Charts, Metrics, Tables)
- **Metrics**: Single-value outputs for KPIs and Table inputs
- **Tables**: Multi-Case comparison via Excel data tables

## 3. Variables (Core Calculation Containers)

Variables are the primary calculation containers. There is a single concrete type with a `defaultFormulaType` that determines behavior:

| Formula Type | Behavior | Use Case |
|---|---|---|
| **Assumption** | Links to a ModelAssumption (user input) | Bringing inputs into the calculation sheet |
| **Calculation** | Mathematical formulas referencing other Variables | Computing outputs from inputs |
| **Aggregation** | Combines dimension parts with potentially different calculation logic | When different regions/products need different formulas |

**Data flow best practice:** `ModelAssumption` (input sheet) → `Assumption Variable` (brings input in unaltered) → `Calculation Variable` (does math). This mirrors Excel best practice: keep inputs separate from calculations. The app treats Assumption Variables and their linked ModelAssumptions as connected (e.g., deleting an Assumption Variable deletes its linked ModelAssumption if no other Variable references it).

**Data types:** Double, Integer, Boolean, String, Date, DateTime, Validation. The Validation type enables dropdown selection from Tag hierarchies (e.g., "Yes/No", "RPI/CPI" — same Abstract→Concrete Tag structure as Dimensions).

**TimeSegments** allow a Variable's formula behavior to change across different time periods (see Section 7).

**Period aggregation:** Variables can aggregate over time via `periodType` — e.g., create a quarterly or annual summary of a monthly Model. Flow units are summed; Balance units take end-of-period value. Time-aggregated Variables have a single Auto TimeSegment. Variables of different periodType cannot share a Layout sheet (one timeline per sheet).

**Aggregation example:** When different regions have different tax calculation logic, you build separate Variables per region (e.g., "Tax cost (UK)", "Tax cost (France)") then aggregate them into "Tax cost by market". The sum is available in the summary line of the Aggregation Variable.

## 4. ModelAssumptions (User Inputs)

ModelAssumptions provide input values to Assumption-type Variables. The separation from Variables follows financial modeling best practice:
1. Keep inputs in their own sheet (one place to make changes)
2. Never reference inputs directly from calculations

**Source types:** LocalInput (direct entry). ExternalData and LinkToXlInsert exist but are not yet enabled for the Agent.

**Multi-scenario values:** ModelAssumption has a values map keyed by Scenario ID. The Base Scenario should always have an entry. Non-Base Scenarios inherit from their base if no explicit value exists.

**Sensitivity variations:** Each ModelAssumption has a `sensitivityType` (one per Assumption): PercentageChange, Delta, or Absolute. Sensitivity entries in the sensitivities map must match this type.

**Time-series inputs:** Values are encoded with DateTimeElement on UnitParts, specifying the time context (period, date format).

## 5. Unit System

Units are composed of **UnitParts**, each based on an Abstract Tag (e.g., "GBP", "Customer", "Month").

**TimeTypes** define temporal characteristics of each UnitPart:

| TimeType | Meaning | Example |
|---|---|---|
| **Flow** | Value over a period | Monthly revenue, quarterly costs |
| **Balance** | Value at a point in time | Cash balance, headcount |
| **Timeless** | No temporal semantics (pure scalar) | Percentages, booleans, conversion factors |

**Constraint:** Tagged UnitParts (with a Tag like GBP, Customer) must use Flow or Balance. Unitless UnitParts (no Tag) must use Timeless. This enforces: "if something has a dimensional unit, it must have a time relationship; if it's unitless, it's a pure scalar."

**isConstant (on Variable):** Controls whether a Variable's value is the same every period or varies over time. `isConstant: true` means a single Assumption value covers all periods. Default is `false` (time-varying). This is independent of TimeType — a Flow Variable can be constant (e.g., a fixed subscription price per period) or time-varying (e.g., monthly revenue).

**"Per period" is implicit** in every Flow unit — no need to include it. Example: a subscription price of `GBP (Flow) / Customer (Balance)` with `isConstant: true` — the Variable needs only a single Assumption value covering all periods. The alternative is to use an Assumption for first period + Calculation TimeSegment referencing previous period. Using `isConstant` is useful when Timings flexibility is needed (e.g., changing the start period). Genuine constants like "Quarters per Year" use `isConstant: true`.

**Unit algebra rules:**
- Flow + Flow = Flow (same offset)
- Balance + Balance = Balance (same offset)
- Balance[-1] + Flow = Balance (stock accumulation)
- Flow × Balance = Flow.Balance (kept separate)
- X × Timeless = X (Timeless is a wildcard in multiplication)
- Flow / Flow = Unitless [Timeless] (tags and TimeTypes cancel)
- Compound cancellation: `Balance[-1] × (Flow / Balance[-1]) = Flow`

**Rates that convert stocks to flows** need compound units for clean algebra. Example: Churn Rate = `Member [Flow] / Member [Balance[-1]]`. Then `Members[-1] × Churn Rate` = `Balance[-1] × (Flow / Balance[-1]) = Flow` — the algebra resolves cleanly. If instead Churn Rate uses `Unitless [Timeless]`, the result is `Balance[-1]` (Timeless doesn't transform TimeType), requiring `overrideUnitError`. Prefer compound units when the rate genuinely converts between TimeTypes; use override only when the compound unit approach is impractical.

**Factoring:** Automatic scaling via `factorPower`. Define "Revenues, £m" and calculate "Price × Volume" — Models detects the 10^6 discrepancy and auto-adjusts the calculation. Preferred over manual division in formulas, as manual division CANNOT be tracked by the Unit validation system.

**Validation:** Unit inconsistencies generate warnings, not errors — calculations still execute. This allows override when the modeler knows better. Units serve two purposes: a) logical consistency for the user (don't add GBP to EUR); b) powering under-the-hood operations (assumption matching, dimensional calculations).

**Key principle:** Units are not an afterthought. Assumption Variables must have a Defined Unit with appropriate TimeTypes on their UnitParts. Units defined in Assumption Variables flow up through Calculation Variables with Inferred Units.

**Self-referencing Variables require Defined Units:** When a Variable references itself with period offsets (e.g., `Cash balance[-1]`), its Unit cannot be inferred — you must use `unitOption: Defined`. The Unit system cannot resolve circular references to determine the inferred type.

## 6. Tags & Dimensions

**Tag types:**
- **Abstract Tags**: Categories that can serve as Dimensions
- **Concrete Tags**: Specific instances. Each Concrete Tag references its Abstract parent via `isATagIds`

**Dimensions:** An Abstract Tag with Concrete children becomes a Dimension. When a Variable references an Abstract Tag via `tagParents`, it expands to generate separate calculation lines for each Concrete child. The Abstract Tag's `concreteChildrenOrder` controls display order (not calculation).

**Cartesian product:** Multiple Dimensions multiply — 3 Products × 2 Markets = 6 calculation lines.

**Validation dropdowns:** The same Tag structure enables dropdown choices for Validation-type Variables.

**TagNamespaces** provide scoping (like `using` statements). A Model can only reference Tags within its namespace or descendant namespaces.

## 7. Time Management

**Timings:** Flexible input — specify any 2 of: start date, end date, number of periods. Includes granularity and fiscal year end.

**Period offsets:** Variables can reference previous/future periods using offsets like `[-1]`, `[-2]`. Configurable behavior for missing periods: `ReplaceWithZero`, `ReplaceWithValue`, `ShowAsNotApplicable`.

**TimeSegments** allow different formula behavior in different time ranges. Each TimeSegment has Start, Duration, and End — all default to Auto. Specify the minimum needed for unambiguous calculation. Start/End can be: periods from start/end (1-based), or a fixed period (e.g., "2025"). TimeSegments must cover all periods without gaps.

**Key financial modeling principle:** Calculations should be consistent across the entire time range (copy-paste from first column to last). A Variable's main calculation is defined at the Variable level (`defaultCalculation`). An "Auto" TimeSegment executes that calculation. A Calculation within a TimeSegment means "something different from the default" — effectively a model input (can only reference the same Variable with period offsets, not other Variables).

## 8. Scenarios & Sensitivities

**Scenarios** model specific anticipated alternatives — different launch dates, product lineups. **Sensitivities** model unknown variance — lower/higher inflation rates.

**Scenario inheritance:** Scenarios can chain: "Base" → "Late launch" → "Late launch without PR campaign" — each based on the previous, making changes in only one place. Values are retrieved recursively with Base as final fallback. Non-Base Scenarios must reference at least one other Scenario via `basedOnScenarioId`.

**Cases:** A Scenario + Sensitivity combination. The Scenario value is retrieved first, then the Sensitivity applied on top.

**In Excel:** One Case shown at a time via dropdown selector on the control sheet (`IsControlSheet`). Multiple Cases viewable simultaneously via Tables (Excel data tables).

**In the app:** All Cases calculated simultaneously — Charts can show multiple Cases.

## 9. Calculations

**Formula syntax (`formulaText`):** Variable references by name, operators (`+`, `-`, `*`, `/`, `^`), period offsets (`[-1]`, `[-2]`), functions, constants. Names with spaces or special characters must be quoted: `"Net Revenue"`.

**Period references (`Periods`):** Returns the current period's end date (e.g., 31 Dec for a Calendar Year). Useful for date comparisons: `Periods >= Launch_Date`. Supports offsets: `Periods[-1]` for previous period's end date.

**All Excel functions supported** for Excel output; most supported in the app calculation engine. **LET functions** supported for complex multi-step calculations.

**Lambdas:** Reusable custom functions stored outside Models (referenced via TagNamespace). Can't reference Variables directly — pass them as arguments. Good for complex reusable calculations, where inputs are referenced multiple times (e.g. a complex conditional timing calculation, or a Bass diffusion curve formula)

**CalculationParts:** Formulas are persisted as CalculationParts. The API accepts either `formulaText` (convenient, parsed by API) or `calculationParts` (verbose but supports complex references). Some operations can't be described in formulaText — in that case, create via formulaText then edit the specific CalculationPart.

**Dimensional matching:** When source and target Variables share the same Dimensions, an "Auto" ItemMatch ensures UK references UK, France references France automatically.

**Complex references** (when dimensions don't match): Either reference the summary line, or create a custom `VariableReferenceItemMatch` with `DimensionReference`s — see Section 10.

## 10. Dimensional Calculations (Advanced)

**groupSummaryType** controls how a Variable summarizes across Dimensions:

| Type | Behavior | Example |
|---|---|---|
| **None** | No summary line | |
| **Sum** | Simple addition | Revenue by region → Total revenue |
| **Auto** | Recalculate formula at summary level | Margin % = Margin/Revenue (Sum would give nonsense) |
| **Rearranged** | Calculate from parent Variable's formula, rearranged | Weighted average % for a percentage input |

**contextVarianceMap:** Maps which UnitParts vary with which Dimensions. Defaults to "all vary with all" which is fine for most cases. Custom maps needed when different UnitParts in a ratio have different dimensional behavior. Example: "Bonus Pot % by Region" has Unit `GBP(varies by region)/GBP(total)`. Assumption units become `GBP (UK)/GBP`, `GBP (France)/GBP` — the dimension context is encoded using **UnitPartModifiers** (Concrete Tags applied to UnitParts).

**DimensionReference types** for custom `VariableReferenceItemMatch` (when dimensions don't match between source and target):

| Type | Purpose | Example |
|---|---|---|
| **Parent** | Link target dimension to matching source TagParent | Region→Region (matching dimensions) |
| **Child** | Always link to a specific Concrete child | "Always use the France line" |
| **Sum** | Sum all values in that dimension | Sum all tiers to get region total |
| **Lookup** | Choose value based on a third Variable's selection | "Inflation rate by cost line" looked up from "RPI/CPI inflation rate" based on "Inflation choice by cost line" (a Validation Variable). Uses `lookupReference` (a VariableReferenceCalculationPart) and `sourceParentId` (the **source** Variable's dimension that drives the lookup — e.g., Product or Cost Line, NOT the looked-up dimension) |
| **SumBy** | Sum and translate dimensions via a mapping Variable | "Revenue by city" summed to "Revenue by region" via "Region by city" mapping Variable. Uses `sumByVariableId`. The mapping Variable is a Validation-type Variable with `validationDimensionId` pointing to the target dimension |

**Lookup example:** You have costs dimensioned by "Cost line" and inflation rates dimensioned by "Inflation type" (RPI, CPI). A Validation Variable "Inflation choice by cost line" (dimensioned by Cost line, with validationDimensionId pointing to Inflation type) lets users pick RPI or CPI per cost line. A Lookup DimensionReference bridges the non-matching dimensions: `sourceParentId` is the **source** Variable's dimension (Cost line), and `lookupReference` points to the Validation Variable. For each cost line, the Lookup reads the Validation Variable's value (e.g., "RPI"), then retrieves the corresponding inflation rate from the target Variable.

**SumBy example:** You have "Revenue by city" and want "Revenue by region". A Validation Variable "Region by city" (dimensioned by City, with validationDimensionId pointing to Region) maps each city to a region (London→UK, Paris→France). A SumBy DimensionReference on "Revenue by region" uses `sumByVariableId` referencing the mapping Variable, translating the City dimension into Region by summing.

## 11. Rearranging

**Problem solved:** A Variable needs to switch between "input" and "output" mode at different times.

**Main use case:** In a model with Actuals periods, some values are known directly and others must be back-calculated. Example: `Revenue = Price × Volume` over 5 years. First 2 years are Actuals — we know Price and Revenue, but not Volume. Entering Revenue assumptions for periods 1-2 creates over-specification (Price, Volume, and Revenue all have inputs — no degree of freedom). Models shows a warning. The user can choose to rearrange Volume, creating a Rearranged TimeSegment for periods 1-2 that references Revenue's ID. Volume is then automatically calculated as Revenue/Price for those periods. The process cascades down the dependency tree until hitting a period before model start or a leaf node.

**NotApplicable alternative:** Instead of rearranging, mark periods as NotApplicable — "we don't care what Volume was during the Actuals period."

**Rearranged in Dimensional summaries:** `groupSummaryType: Rearranged` with `groupSummaryRearrangedParentId` references a parent Variable whose formula is algebraically rearranged to solve for this Variable at the summary level (e.g., weighted average price from Revenue/Volume).

## 12. Layout & Excel Generation

The **Layout** object always exists on a Model (cannot be created or deleted). It contains **ModelSheets**.

**ModelSheet types:**

| Type | Contains |
|---|---|
| **Calculations** | Variable LineItems |
| **Assumptions** | ModelAssumption LineItems |
| **Metrics** | Metric LineItems |
| **Dashboard** | A Dashboard reference |
| **XlInsert** | External Excel file import (not yet enabled) |

**Sheet structure:** ModelSheet → Sections → ContentSection → LineGroups → LineItems. **LineGroups** are purely organizational — headers with configurable numbering and collapsibility.

**Critical rule:** Assumption-type Variables go on **Calculation** sheets, NOT Assumption sheets. Assumption sheets contain ModelAssumptions. The Assumption Variable links to the ModelAssumption on the Assumptions sheet. This mirrors Excel best practice: Assumption sheets are for raw inputs, Calculation sheets bring those inputs in then calculate with them.

**Minimum for valid Excel:** At least 1 Assumptions sheet + 1 Calculations sheet.

**Multiple Calculation sheets** are common for large models — organize by business area (timing, revenues, costs, financial statements).

**One timeline per sheet:** Variables of different `periodType` cannot share a sheet.

**Also useful without Excel:** Layout provides an "Excel-like" structured view within the app.

## 13. Dashboards & Visualization

**DashboardItem types:** Panel (container), Chart, Table, Metric, AssumptionsTable, Spacer.

**Charts:** One Variable per chart. Choose any 2 of {Time, each Dimension, Scenarios, Sensitivities} for **Categories** and **Series**. The remaining axes become filters whose values are configured during chart setup (not interactive in the Dashboard — you select specific values). Example: "Revenue by region and tier" as Stacked Column — Tier as Categories, Region as Series, with Time set to a specific period.

**Metrics:** Single-value outputs. Must force a single value by specifying a period or performing an aggregate operation (SUM, MAX, etc.) across the time range. Can be dimensional (only the time dimension is restricted). Used for Dashboard KPIs and as inputs to Tables. Examples: "Total 5-year Revenue" (SUM aggregate), "Exit Year EBITDA Margin %" (last period).

**Tables:** Generate Excel data tables for multi-Case comparison. Tables reference Metrics and compare their values across multiple Scenario/Sensitivity combinations. Required workflow: Create Table → Add Table to Dashboard → Create Dashboard ModelSheet.

**AssumptionsTable:** Editable assumptions within a Dashboard. Layout constraint: each Assumption can only have one entry cell in Excel. If an Assumption appears in a Dashboard's AssumptionsTable and that Dashboard is in the Layout, the Assumptions sheet will point to the Dashboard instead of containing the entry cell. For Dashboards that aren't in the Layout, you can add Assumptions repeatedly whereever needed.

**Excel rendering:** Best-effort — some features (like simultaneous Scenarios) aren't possible in Excel.

## 14. Retrieving Calculated Values

Operations exist for retrieving and comparing calculated values from Variables and Metrics:

| Operation | Purpose |
|---|---|
| `get-values` | Retrieve calculated values with optional trend analysis |
| `compare-cases` | Compare values across Scenarios and Sensitivities |
| `trace-dependencies` (with `includeValues`) | See values along the dependency tree |
| `get-model-health` (with `includeValueChecks`) | Detect N/A values and anomalies |
| `valueSummary` in filter | Adds first/last value and trend to filter results |

Use `help: true` on any operation for parameter details.

## 15. Constraints & Business Rules

- No circular dependencies in Variable reference chains
- TimeSegments must cover all periods without gaps
- Unit inconsistencies generate warnings, not errors (overrideable)
- Aggregation Variables must have a single Aggregation TimeSegment
- Calculations within TimeSegments can only reference the same Variable with period offsets
- Variables of different `periodType` cannot share a Layout sheet
- One Base Scenario and one Base Sensitivity minimum required
- Each ModelSheet supports only one type of LineItem (Variables on Calculations sheets, ModelAssumptions on Assumptions sheets, Metrics on Metrics sheets)

## 16. Not Yet Implemented

These features exist in the data model but are not currently available to the Agent:
- **DataPoints/ExternalData**: External data integration (API not enabled)
- **XlInserts**: Excel file imports (not enabled)

Mention these if the user asks, to avoid confusion.

## Key Enums (Capabilities Reference)

| Object | Property | Values |
|---|---|---|
| Variable | defaultFormulaType | Assumption, Calculation, Aggregation |
| Variable | dataType | Double, Integer, String, DateTime, Date, Boolean, Validation |
| Variable | groupSummaryType | None, Sum, Auto, Rearranged |
| Variable | unitOption | Defined, Inferred |
| TimeSegment | modelFormulaType | Auto, Assumptions, Calculation, Aggregation, Rearranged, NotApplicable |
| Variable | isConstant | true, false (default: false) |
| UnitPart | timeType | Flow, Balance, Timeless |
| ModelSheet | modelSheetType | Calculations, Assumptions, Metrics, Dashboard, XlInsert |
| DashboardItem | dashboardItemType | Panel, Chart, Table, Metric, AssumptionsTable, Spacer |
| DimensionReference | referenceType | Sum, Parent, Child, Lookup, SumBy |
| ModelAssumption | sensitivityType | PercentageChange, Delta, Absolute |

## Tool Workflow

When using QueryObject and ModelAction tools, follow this **bash-like workflow pattern**:

1. **ALWAYS set current Model context first, unless it has already been set for you**: Use `ModelAction(action='set-current', parameters={'model_id': 'xyz'})` before any QueryObject operations. **Make sure you have the correct Model Id first** - you can find the Id by listing all available models using the `ModelDescriptions` tool
2. **Then perform operations**: Use `QueryObject` to perform CRUD+ operations on objects, or take other object-specific actions, and use `ModelAction` to take other general Model actions (like pulling a Model summary)
3. **ALWAYS Use help for schemas if you haven't seen that schema before**: Add `help: true` to parameters (like `--help` in bash) to get detailed parameter schemas. Example: `QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='filter', parameters={'help': true})`
4. **DO NOT filter without any property filters** unless you genuinely need a complete list of objects. Always call filter help first so that you know how to filter correctly - note, all string properties have glob and regex filering enabled - **GET FILTER HELP BEFORE FILTERING** to see details.

5. **USE CONSERVATIVE FILTERS BY DEFAULT**: When filtering string properties, use glob patterns by default to retrieve broader matches rather than exact matches. The user will correct you if they need an exact match.

   - Good (conservative): `{"name": "*GBP*"}` retrieves "GBP", "UK-GBP", "GBP Exchange Rate", etc.
   - Too tight: `{"name": "GBP"}` only retrieves exact match
   - Use exact filters only when you're certain about the precise name

**Remember**: Add `help: true` to parameters (like bash's `--help` flag) to get complete parameter schemas before creating or updating objects. Example: `QueryObject(object_type='ModelSheet', action='create', parameters={'help': true})`

**Example filtering workflow**

```
[ASSISTANT] Now I need to find Tags matching "GBP"
[TOOL] QueryObject(action="filter", object_type="Tag", parameters={"help":"true"})
[TOOLRESULT] ...filter instructions for Tags...
[TOOL] QueryObject(action="filter", object_type="Tag", parameters={"name":"*GBP*"})
[TOOLRESULT] Multiple matches found - agent can disambiguate or present options
```

## ID Communication Guidelines

When communicating with users about Models objects:

**Use Names for User Communication**: Always present objects to users using their meaningful names (e.g., "Combined revenues", "Price", "UK Revenues") rather than technical IDs.

**Use IDs for Tool Operations**: Always use precise IDs in tool calls for reliability and accuracy.

**Example Patterns**:

- "The Model has 3 calculation Variables: Combined revenues, EU Revenues (GBP), and UK Revenues"
- "I'll add the Price assumption to the new LineGroup"

**Remember** The help parameter (`help: true`) gives you correct schemas for all actions, or generic help for on object type if you don't include an action - don't just assume you know how to do something, **use help** to make sure you do it correctly

## Model Health Checks

Use `ModelAction(action='get-model-health')` to verify model integrity. This checks for calculation errors, layout issues, circular dependencies, and other common problems. Regular health checks are advised after making changes — see `verify-model` instructions for detailed usage.

## Getting Detailed Instructions

When you need specific implementation guidance, use the **GetInstructions** tool to retrieve Level 2 documentation. Level 2 has two types:

- **Workflow instructions**: Step-by-step processes. Retrieve before starting work.
- **Object instructions**: API patterns and properties. Retrieved as directed by workflow instructions, or when you need API detail for a specific object type.

### When to Retrieve Workflow Instructions

| Situation | Retrieve |
|---|---|
| Working with an existing model | `review-model` first, then relevant build workflow |
| Building new model structure (Variables, Assumptions, Tags) | `build-structure` |
| Creating or modifying Excel layout | `build-layout` |
| Creating dashboards, charts, metrics, tables | `build-visualisations` |
| After completing significant work | `verify-model` |

### Available Object Instructions

| Category | Covers |
|---|---|
| `variables` | Variable properties, formulaText, CalculationParts, TimeSegments, DimensionReferences, periodType, Rearranging |
| `assumptions` | ModelAssumption properties, values map, DateTimeElement encoding, sensitivity values |
| `tags` | Tag creation, Abstract/Concrete setup, Dimensions, contextVarianceMap, UnitPartModifiers |
| `scenarios` | Scenario/Sensitivity creation, inheritance, Cases |
| `layout` | ModelSheet/LineGroup/LineItem properties, the Assumption-on-Calc-sheet rule |
| `dashboards` | DashboardItem properties, Chart axis config, Metric period handling, Table workflow |

### Best Practices

- **Retrieve once, use many times**: Get instructions at the start of a workflow, not repeatedly
- **Check the list first**: Run `GetInstructions(action='list')` if you're unsure which guide to use
- **Follow the guide**: Instructions contain validated patterns, concrete examples, and error prevention strategies

### Example Usage

```
# List available instruction categories
GetInstructions(action='list')

# Get structure-building workflow
GetInstructions(action='get', parameters={'category': 'build-structure'})

# Get Variable API details
GetInstructions(action='get', parameters={'category': 'variables'})
```

=== AVAILABLE TOOLS ===
You have access to 16 tools:
- GetInstructions: Retrieve detailed implementation guides and expert documentation for complex operations. Use this tool BEFORE attempting activities like creating layouts, validating models, or generating structure. Examples: GetInstructions(action='list') to see available guides, GetInstructions(action='get', parameters={'category': 'create-layout'}) to get specific instructions.
- ModelAction: Model-level operations and context management. BASH-LIKE WORKFLOW: First use set-current to establish working model context, then use summary for overview. Summary provides basic information about Model, including Timings, Root Variable nodes (Variables with no dependents), and item counts. The Summary may already be provided for you in, in which case DO NOT retrieve it again unless you think changes have been made. All operations support optional format parameter ('structured', 'markdown', 'compact'). Add 'help: true' to parameters to see all available operations (like --help flag). Example: ModelAction(action='set-current', parameters={'model_id': '-P6eJsQoxoWnCFPQl2ZJ'}), ModelAction(action='summary', parameters={'format': 'compact'}), ModelAction(parameters={'help': true})
- ModelDescriptions: Get list of available models with basic information. Does not require a current model to be set. Returns model names, IDs, namespaces, and last edited dates.
- QueryObject: Object operations on current model. IMPORTANT: Requires current model to be set first via ModelAction set-current. Add 'help: true' to parameters for help on any action (like --help flag). Note Create/Update share a common `help` schema - if you have already retrieved one of Create/Update `help` for an object, no need to retrieve it again. For BULK operations, add 'bulk: true' and provide 'items' array. WORKFLOW: Use 'filter' to find objects matching criteria (returns key fields), then use 'get-details' on specific IDs to retrieve full property details. By default, get-details returns all properties in summary mode (complex objects show preview, collections show count + preview). Specify 'properties' array to expand requested properties fully. Use dot notation for nested expansion (e.g., 'defaultCalculation.calculationParts'). Examples: QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='filter', parameters={'help': true}), QueryObject(object_type='Tag', action='get-details', parameters={'id': 'tag-123'}), QueryObject(object_type='Tag', action='get-details', parameters={'id': 'tag-123', 'properties': ['tagProperties']}), QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='get-details', parameters={'id': 'var-123', 'properties': ['defaultCalculation.calculationParts']}), QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='create', parameters={'bulk': true, 'items': [{'name': 'Var1'}, {'name': 'Var2'}]}), QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='other', otherAction='trace-dependencies', parameters={'ids': ['var-1', 'var-2']})
- add_task: Add a single task to the to-do list. Tasks can be inserted at specific positions. Examples: add_task(description='Review PR') appends to end, add_task(description='Urgent fix', after='start') inserts at position 0, add_task(description='Follow up', after='task-3') inserts after task-3.
- add_tasks: Add multiple tasks to the to-do list atomically. All tasks are inserted at the same position in order. Examples: add_tasks(descriptions=['Task 1', 'Task 2']) appends to end, add_tasks(descriptions=['Urgent A', 'Urgent B'], after='start') inserts at position 0, add_tasks(descriptions=['Step 1', 'Step 2'], after='task-5') inserts after task-5.
- complete_task: Mark a task as completed. The task will be marked with a completed status and timestamp. Example: complete_task(task_id='task-5')
- create_file: Create a new file in the workspace. Creates intermediate directories automatically. Fails if the file already exists — use overwrite_file to replace existing files. Example: create_file(path='plans/001-revenue.md', content='# Revenue Plan')
- enter_plan_mode: Switch to Plan mode. Use this when the task is complex and requires planning before execution — for example, creating a new Model, making multi-step changes across multiple objects, or restructuring existing data. In plan mode, you should read existing context, write a plan to the plans/ directory, and call get_plan_approval when ready.
- get_current_time: Get the current date and time
- get_plan_approval: Submit a completed plan for user approval. The plan file must be in the plans/ directory. The user will review the plan and can approve it, request changes, or reject it.
- list_files: List files and directories in the workspace. When recursive is true, lists all files in the subtree. Example: list_files(path='plans', recursive=true)
- overwrite_file: Replace the entire content of an existing file. Fails if the file does not exist — use create_file for new files. Example: overwrite_file(path='config.json', content='{"version": 2}')
- read_file: Read the full content of a file in the workspace. Example: read_file(path='plans/001-revenue.md')
- remove_task: Remove a task from the to-do list entirely. Use this when a task is no longer relevant or was added by mistake. Example: remove_task(task_id='task-3')
- update_file: Perform exact string replacement within a file. Fails if old_string is not found or is not unique (unless replace_all is true). Fails if old_string equals new_string. Example: update_file(path='config.json', old_string='"debug": false', new_string='"debug": true')

Use these tools when they can help answer the user's questions or perform requested tasks.

## INITIAL CONTEXT

The current working model has been pre-set for you. A summary is below.

# Model: Agent tests
**ID:** -PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4jxj
**Created:** 2026-01-28 10:37:55
**Last Modified:** 2026-01-28 10:38:07
**Tag Namespace:** Agent testing (ID: -PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4jzi)

## Model Configuration
- **Timings:** Mar 25 - Dec 27 (12 periods, Quarter)
- **Default Unit:** [no unit]
- **Unit Rigor Level:** Full Units (Level 3)

## Scenarios & Sensitivities
- **Scenarios:** Base (ID: Base)
- **Sensitivities:** Base (ID: Base)

## Variables
- **Total Variables:** 0
- **of type Assumption:** 0
- **of type Calculations:** 0
- **of type Aggregations:** 0

### Root Variables
| Name | Id | Default Formula Type | Calculation | Unit | Number Format | Time Segments | Is Constant |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|

## Assumptions
- **Total Assumptions:** 0



**You do NOT need to call ModelAction set-current** unless you want to switch to a different model. If asked about the model, DO NOT retrieve a new model summary unless you think the model has changed since the above.
</system>

[SYSTEM]: # Plan Mode

You are now in Plan mode. The user has asked you to plan before executing.

In this mode, you should:

1. **Understand the context** — Read existing Models, data, and workspace files to understand what you're working with and what the user needs.
2. **Ask clarifying questions** — If anything is unclear, ask the user before writing the plan.
3. **Write a plan** — Create a plan file in the `plans/` directory with a descriptive name (e.g. `plans/revenue-model-refactor.md`). Do **not** add a numeric prefix — numbering is applied automatically when you submit for approval.
4. **Submit for approval** — When your plan is ready, call `get_plan_approval` with the plan file path. The tool will auto-number the file (e.g. `plans/003-revenue-model-refactor.md`) and return the canonical path.

Do not execute the plan directly. Write it as a document for the user to review and approve before any changes are made.
[USER]: This is a new model. I'd like to create a revenue model for a new local gym business that has 3 packages: basic, premium and platinum. It should have a flexible launch date. Keep calculations simple - that means not having more than two variables in a single calculation if it can be avoided. It really helps with transparency and following the calculation flow. Plan out the model structure first, and get my approval before starting. Once we've agreed the plan use your to-do list to track your progress.
[ASSISTANT]: 

Great, let me start by understanding the existing context — I'll check what Tags are available in the namespace, and then draft a plan for your review.

Let me look at what's already available:
[THINKING]: The user wants me to plan a revenue model for a gym business with 3 packages (basic, premium, platinum). Let me think about what this model needs:

1. **Launch date** - flexible, so this should be an assumption
2. **3 packages** - basic, premium, platinum - this is a dimension
3. **Simple calculations** - no more than 2 variables per calculation

Let me think about the revenue model structure:

Revenue = Price × Members (per package)

But we need to build up to members. A gym business typically has:
- New members joining per period
- Churn/leavers per period
- Total members = previous members + new members - leavers


- Monthly price per package
- Revenue per package = Price × Members

I'll use Tags to create the package dimension. For the variable chain, I need to keep things simple with max 2 variables per calculation: a launch date assumption to determine when the gym becomes active, monthly pricing per package, and new member assumptions that I can adjust before and after launch.

Now I'm working through the member flow calculations. New members get zeroed out pre-launch, then I need to account for churn by calculating leavers based on the previous period's member count. The tricky part is the members calculation itself—adding new members and subtracting leavers creates three variables, so I should break it into net new members first, then add that to the prior period's count. Now I'm working through the revenue calculation and launch mechanics. Revenue is straightforward—Price times Members gives us 2 variables. For the launch mechanism, I need a Launch Date assumption and a Has Launched calculation that checks if we're past that date, then use it to zero out pre-launch activity like new member intake and churn.

But I'm hitting a circular dependency issue with the member calculations. Members depends on New Members minus Leavers, but Leavers depends on the prior period's Members count. I need to resolve this by recognizing that Leavers references Members from the previous period, so the dependency chain actually works—Members in period t uses Members from t-1, which is already determined.

To make this cleaner, I'll split the calculation into Net New Members (New Members minus Leavers) and then Members equals the prior period plus Net New Members. For Revenue, it's straightforward: Price times Members. Now I need to think through the units and make sure everything aligns across the model.

Looking at what tags and units are available in the namespace, I'm mapping out each variable with its unit, time type, and whether it's constant. I can see New Members flows in as a member-level flow, Churn Rate is a ratio of flow to balance, and Leavers is also a member flow. Let me check what currency and package tags are already defined before I proceed. I'm verifying the unit conversions work out correctly for churn rate and revenue calculations. Now I need to check what tags are already available in the system before I finalize the dimensional analysis and start planning the implementation.

For the launch date logic, I'm thinking through how to handle the pre-launch period—I can use a conditional formula that returns 1 or 0 based on whether we've reached the launch date, then multiply that by the flow values to zero them out before launch.

Now I'm sketching out the sheet structure: I'll separate assumptions from calculations, grouping the timing logic (launch date and the has-launched flag) into one calculations sheet, then members and revenue into their own sheets for clarity.

Before I finalize this layout, I should check what tags already exist in the namespace so I don't duplicate anything.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Check available tags in namespace", object_type="Tag", parameters={"format":"markdown","limit":50})
[TOOL_RESULT]: | Name | Id | TagType | Namespace | ShortName | IsA | RelatesTo | IsSameAs | TagProperties |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|
| Geographic regions | 109 | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  |  |  |  |  |
| Time | -MbvfIePI1SMBy53uVj2 | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  |  |  |  |  |
| Space | -MbxPieBbo5OnDDUMhxV | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  |  |  |  |  |
| Units | -MbvflOnm-tvCtphbiSi | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  |  |  |  |  |
| Geographic region | -MZhvxiKdVBN6lLAN73R | Abstract | Core: Concepts |  |  | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Options | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXl0 | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  |  |  |  |  |
| On/Off option | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXl3 | Abstract | Core: Concepts | On/Off |  | 1 relationships |  |  |
| True/False option | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXl6 | Abstract | Core: Concepts | True/False |  | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Yes/No Option | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXl9 | Abstract | Core: Concepts | Yes/No |  | 1 relationships |  |  |
| On | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXlH | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Off | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXlM | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| True | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXlr | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| False | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXly | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Yes | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXmA | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| No | -ODKQoQ_83x-Aq-AoXmK | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Distance | -MbxPjJc4_fxkQ-7Ib_r | Concrete | Core: Concepts |  |  | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Unit | -MbvflOnm-tvCtphbiSj | Abstract | Core: Concepts |  |  | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Pound Sterling (GBP) | -NuMtNA6o3nDVsfVrM-3 | Abstract | Core: Common Units | GBP | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Second | -MbwgKRRhB5g_JmRqA6Y | Abstract | Core: Common Units | s | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Minute | -MbvgojgICSgne9inIk1 | Abstract | Core: Common Units | min | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Hour | -Mbx9YsnD2uZjwru43ny | Abstract | Core: Common Units | hr | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Day | -M_5g-f5Hrn4s_AwV7AI | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Metre | -MVz694E3juU87isgQgx | Abstract | Core: Common Units | m | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Units of time | -M_5grZU5hr7gPyLRWXQ | Concrete | Core: Common Units |  |  | 2 relationships |  |  |
| Unit of time | -M_5grZU5hr7gPyLRWXR | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Units of distance | -MbxPn37EKaXALKV1JY5 | Concrete | Core: Common Units |  |  | 2 relationships |  |  |
| Unit of distance | -MbxPn37EKaXALKV1JY6 | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Week | -Nu1xX1LqJb32ake8UCS | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Month | -Nu1xlQtL2e_2gmkClh0 | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Quarter | -Nu1xf6z8u1pEdlM1H_K | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Year | -Nu1xryhdSLAmjeZNAiw | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Units of currency | -NuMtB3Hj0UEWHuq1rbD | Concrete | Core: Common Units |  |  | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Unit of currency | -NuMtB3Hj0UEWHuq1rbE | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Millimetre | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl6g | Abstract | Core: Common Units | mm | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Centimetre | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl6j | Abstract | Core: Common Units | cm | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Inch | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl6m | Abstract | Core: Common Units | in | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Foot | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl6p | Abstract | Core: Common Units | ft | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Yard | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl6s | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Kilometre | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl6x | Abstract | Core: Common Units | km | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Mile | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl7- | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Decade | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl7A | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Century | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl7F | Abstract | Core: Common Units |  | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| US Dollar (USD) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl7U | Abstract | Core: Common Units | USD | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Euro (EUR) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl7a | Abstract | Core: Common Units | EUR | 1 relationships |  |  |  |
| Japanese Yen (JPY) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl7h | Abstract | Core: Common Units | JPY | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Chinese Yuan/Renminbi (CNY) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl7o | Abstract | Core: Common Units | CNY | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Australian Dollar (AUD) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl7v | Abstract | Core: Common Units | AUD | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Canadian Dollar (CAD) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl81 | Abstract | Core: Common Units | CAD | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Swiss Franc (CHF) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl88 | Abstract | Core: Common Units | CHF | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Hong Kong Dollar (HKD) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl8Q | Abstract | Core: Common Units | HKD | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Singapore Dollar (SGD) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl8Y | Abstract | Core: Common Units | SGD | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Swedish Krone (SEK) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl8e | Abstract | Core: Common Units | SEK | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| South Korean Won (KRW) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl8l | Abstract | Core: Common Units | KRW | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Norwegian Krone (NOK) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl8s | Abstract | Core: Common Units | NOK | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| New Zealand Dollar (NZD) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl8z | Abstract | Core: Common Units | NZD | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Indian Rupee (INR) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl95 | Abstract | Core: Common Units | INR | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Mexican Peso (MXN) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl9C | Abstract | Core: Common Units | MXN | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| New Taiwan Dollar (TWD) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl9K | Abstract | Core: Common Units | TWD | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| South African Rand (ZAR) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl9R | Abstract | Core: Common Units | ZAR | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Brazilian Real (BRL) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl9Z | Abstract | Core: Common Units | BRL | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Danish Krone (DKK) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl9f | Abstract | Core: Common Units | DKK | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Polish Zloty (PLN) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl9m | Abstract | Core: Common Units | PLN | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Thai Baht (THB) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCkl9t | Abstract | Core: Common Units | THB | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Israeli New Shekel (ILS) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCklA- | Abstract | Core: Common Units | ILS | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Indonesian Rupiah (IDR) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCklA6 | Abstract | Core: Common Units | IDR | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Czech Koruna (CZK) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCklAD | Abstract | Core: Common Units | CZK | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| UAE Dirham (AED) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCklAL | Abstract | Core: Common Units | AED | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Turkish Lira (TRY) | -OBHKjeJtexpNHPCklAS | Abstract | Core: Common Units | TRY | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Hungarian Forint (HUF) | -OBHMO4iIyLw9IrFP2cU | Abstract | Core: Common Units | HUF | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Chilean Peso (CLP) | -OBHMO4iIyLw9IrFP2cX | Abstract | Core: Common Units | CLP | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Saudi Riyal (SAR) | -OBHMO4iIyLw9IrFP2c_ | Abstract | Core: Common Units | SAR | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Philippine Peso (PHP) | -OBHMO4iIyLw9IrFP2cc | Abstract | Core: Common Units | PHP | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Malaysian Ringgit (MYR) | -OBHMO4iIyLw9IrFP2cf | Abstract | Core: Common Units | MYR | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Colombian Peso (COP) | -OBHMO4iIyLw9IrFP2ci | Abstract | Core: Common Units | COP | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |
| Russian Ruble (RUB) | -OBHQX_-n9JSfAQuq0uI | Abstract | Core: Common Units | RUB | 1 relationships | 1 relationships |  |  |


[ASSISTANT]: Good — GBP is available and there are various utility tags. Now let me think through the model structure before writing the plan. I have a few questions first:

Before I draft the plan, a couple of quick clarifications:

1. **Currency** — I'm assuming GBP since it's a local gym. Correct?

2. **Member dimension** — Should the 3 packages (Basic, Premium, Platinum) be modelled as a **Dimension**, so each Variable automatically generates a line per package? This is the cleanest approach — you'd enter assumptions per package (e.g., monthly price for Basic, Premium, Platinum) and the model rolls everything up. Alternatively I could model each package as completely separate Variables, but that's more repetitive.

3. **Revenue drivers** — I'm thinking a simple structure like:
   - **New members per quarter** (assumption per package)
   - **Churn rate** (assumption per package — % of members leaving each quarter)
   - **Members** (opening + new - churned)
   - **Monthly price per member** (assumption per package)
   - **Revenue** = Members × Price
   
   Does that cover what you need, or are there other revenue streams (e.g., joining fees, personal training, classes)?

4. **Launch date** — You mentioned flexible. I'll model this as a date assumption with a pre/post-launch switch so the model zeros out before launch. Sound good?
[USER]: 1. Yes, GBP
2. Yes, use Dimensions
3. Those are the key revenue drivers for now
4. Yes, date assumption with an "is live" flag or similar
[ASSISTANT]: 

Great, I have everything I need. Let me draft the plan now.
[THINKING]: The user has confirmed the key decisions. Let me now draft a comprehensive plan for the gym revenue model. Let me think through the structure carefully.

**Model Timings:** Already set — Mar 25 to Dec 27, quarterly, 12 periods.

**Tags needed:**
- Abstract Tag: "Package" (the dimension)
- Concrete Tags: "Basic", "Premium", "Platinum" (children of Package)
- We already have GBP available

**Variables structure — keeping calculations to max 2 variables per formula:**

1. **Launch date** — Assumption, DateTime, isConstant: true, no unit (Timeless)
2. **Is live** — Calculation, Boolean: `Periods >= "Launch date"` 


3. **Monthly price** — Assumption, Double, by Package, isConstant: true, unit: GBP/Member. Since the model runs quarterly, I'll keep this as a monthly figure and multiply by the number of months in each quarter when needed.

For the core variables, I'm setting up the timing first with a launch date and a calculation to determine when the gym goes live, then moving into member dynamics with new member acquisition per quarter and a churn rate that tracks what percentage of members leave each period. I'm settling on a cleaner structure: new members and churn rate as assumptions, then calculating members churned by multiplying the previous period's balance by the churn rate, deriving net new members by subtracting churned from new, and finally updating the member balance by adding net new members to the prior period's closing count.

For revenue, I'll keep monthly price per member as the base assumption and multiply by 3 as a literal constant in the formula rather than creating separate variables—this avoids over-engineering with unnecessary constants like "months per quarter."

Actually, I'm realizing the "Is live" flag should probably gate member accumulation itself rather than just revenue, since the gym shouldn't be adding members before launch. So I'd apply it at the new members level: calculate whether the gym is live based on comparing the current period to the launch date, then use that to filter new member additions before they flow into revenue calculations.

Now looking at the full model with churn included — I'm defining new members (live) as the gated input, then calculating churned members from the prior period's balance, netting those out to get the period's net new members, and accumulating that into the total member count. Then revenue is simply members times the quarterly price. That's 11 variables total, each using at most 2 references, which feels clean. The churn calculation self-corrects pre-launch since there are no members to churn from, so I don't need to gate it separately. And since members accumulates to zero before launch, revenue will naturally be zero too.

Now I'm thinking through the units more carefully — launch date and is live are just metadata, new members and new members (live) are flows measured per quarter, and churn rate should probably be expressed as a compound unit (members per member per quarter) so the algebra works out cleanly when I multiply it by the prior balance. I'm going back and forth on whether to use proper compound units for the churn rate or keep it simple with a unitless percentage—the compound unit approach is technically correct, but the user asked for simplicity. I think I'll go with proper units and explain the reasoning in the plan, since that's the right way to model it even if it means accepting a minor unit warning. The unit math checks out cleanly with this approach—churn rate as a compound unit flows through the calculations properly. For pricing, I'm defining monthly price per member as a constant with the right units, then scaling it up for quarterly billing, and revenue multiplies out to the correct flow unit. Now I'm wondering whether to use Member as a dimension tag or handle it differently.

I need to set up a Member abstract tag for the unit system, and create a Package tag with Basic, Premium, and Platinum variants for segmentation. For the sheet structure, I'm weighing whether to split this into multiple focused calculation sheets or keep it consolidated—probably makes sense to have an Assumptions sheet, then combine Timing and Revenue calculations into one sheet since the model is relatively straightforward.

Now I'm thinking through the number formats for each metric: dates for the launch date, booleans for the live flag, whole numbers for member counts, percentages for churn, and currency formatting for pricing and revenue—though for a local gym, I might want to consider using thousands notation to keep the numbers more readable.

For the dimensioned variables, I need to figure out the right summary behavior. New members should sum across packages, but churn rate is trickier since it's a percentage—I can't just sum those. I think the cleanest approach is to set churn rate to recalculate at the summary level using the total member count and the summary-level churn rate.

Actually, simpler: churn rate stays as a per-package input with no summary, members churned sums across packages, and everything else that aggregates logically also uses Sum. For price fields, those stay per-package with no summary too.

On the variable types themselves, members is a stock (balance at a point in time), while new members and members churned are flows (quantities per period), so I should mark them accordingly.

Since the Members variable references its own prior value, it'll need a Defined Unit rather than Inferred. For the "Is live" calculation, I'm going to use a numeric 0/1 flag instead of a boolean—when I multiply it by revenue or other metrics to gate them, a numeric approach is cleaner than relying on boolean coercion.

Now I need to nail down the period logic. The model runs Mar 25 - Dec 27 on a quarterly basis, so I need to verify exactly how the periods align with calendar quarters starting from March 2025.

For the "Is live" formula, I'm comparing each period's end date against the launch date — if the period ends on or after launch, the product is live for that period. Using `IF(Periods >= Launch_date, 1, 0)` keeps it straightforward and returns a numeric value for calculations.

Since the gym launches as a whole unit rather than by package, "Is live" shouldn't be dimensioned by Package — it's a single flag that applies across the board.

Now I'm refining the variable names to keep things clearer: I'll call the raw assumption "Target new members," then calculate the actual "New members" by gating it with the "Is live" flag. From there I can build out the rest of the model with churn, net new members, and the running member count.

For the pricing side, I need to be careful about units. Monthly price is in GBP per member per month, but since the model runs quarterly, multiplying by 3 converts it to a quarterly rate. The unit stays as GBP per member, just representing a different time period.

Let me verify the math on revenue: Members times Quarterly price gives me Member [Balance] × GBP [Flow] / Member [Balance], which cancels to GBP [Flow]. That checks out.

Now I'm reconsidering whether pricing should be constant by default. Users might want to adjust prices across different periods, so I should probably leave isConstant as false to give them that flexibility.

Actually, for a gym with standard monthly pricing, isConstant: true makes more sense as the starting point—simpler setup with one value, and they can modify it later if needed. For Churn rate, I'll set isConstant: false since it typically varies over time. New members should definitely be isConstant: false since that changes each quarter. So I'm settling on Launch date and Monthly price as constant, while Is live, Target new members, and Churn rate will vary.

I don't need to pre-populate assumption values—the user can enter those themselves. And for the "3 months per quarter" calculation, I'll just use the literal number rather than creating a separate constant variable to keep things simple.

Now I'm ready to write out the full plan.

Generating the variables table... Now I'm looking at the quarterly price calculation and wondering whether it should be marked as constant. Since monthly price is fixed and I'm just multiplying by 3, the quarterly price would also be constant across all periods. But I'm realizing that for calculated variables, the isConstant property might not be necessary — the engine should handle that automatically based on the formula inputs.

For the member churn dependency chain, I need to clarify the references: Members churned should reference the previous period's member count (Members[-1]) multiplied by the churn rate, which creates a dependency on Members through the lag operator rather than a circular reference. This feeds into Net new members, which then affects the current period's Members calculation.

Let me trace through period 1 to verify the logic: Members[-1] starts at 0, so Members churned equals 0, Net new members equals just the New members input, and Members becomes that initial cohort.

In period 2 and beyond, Members[-1] pulls the calculated value from the previous period, allowing Members churned to reference it properly. The key insight is that Members needs Defined Unit because it self-references with [-1], while Members churned can use Inferred Unit since it only references a different variable with an offset. Now I need to decide on the missingPeriodsCalculation behavior for Members when [-1] doesn't exist.

For the first period, Members[-1] should return 0 since there are no members before launch, so I'll use ReplaceWithZero. The same logic applies to Members churned — before the first period, zero members means zero churn.

But there's a unit mismatch I need to resolve: Members churned is calculated as Members[-1] × Churn rate, where Churn rate is Timeless. This gives me Member [Balance], but Members churned should conceptually be Member [Flow] to match the Net new members calculation where I subtract it from New members [Flow].

The fix is to define Churn rate with a compound unit: Member [Flow] / Member [Balance]. This makes the dimensional analysis work out perfectly — Members[-1] × Churn rate gives me Member [Flow], and then Net new members = New members [Flow] - Members churned [Flow] stays consistent. The revenue calculation also works cleanly with this approach.

For the implementation, I need to structure the compound unit with two UnitParts: one for Member with Flow timeType in the numerator, and one for Member with Balance timeType in the denominator with a negative power indicator. I'll verify the exact syntax when I actually build it, but this structure should handle it correctly.

Now I'm confirming the timeline—12 quarterly periods spanning March 2025 through December 2027 gives us a solid three-year projection, which works well for a gym business plan. I'm also setting up the variable formatting rules: dates for launch, binary flags for status, number formatting with thousands separators for member counts, percentage formatting for churn rates, currency formatting for pricing and revenue, and signed number formatting for net changes.

For the grouped summaries, I need to think through which aggregation makes sense for each metric—sums work for totals like new members and revenue, but churn rate and pricing don't aggregate meaningfully across packages since they're per-package values. Revenue will show total across all packages at the summary level, which is what we want.

Now I'm structuring the full plan with sections for overview, tags, variables in a table, calculation flow, units, layout, and implementation steps.
[TOOL]: create_file(content="# Gym Revenue Model — Plan

## Overview

A quarterly revenue model for a local gym business with 3 membership packages (Basic, Premium, Platinum). The model covers Mar 2025 – Dec 2027 (12 quarters) and uses a flexible launch date to zero out all activity before the gym opens.

**Design principles:**
- Every calculation references **at most 2 variables** for transparency
- Membership packages modelled as a **Dimension** (one set of variables, separate lines per package)
- Clean **unit algebra** throughout — no overrides needed
- Currency: **GBP**

---

## 1. Tags to Create

| Tag | Type | Parent | Purpose |
|-----|------|--------|---------|
| Member | Abstract | — | Unit tag for membership counts |
| Package | Abstract | — | Dimension for the 3 gym packages |
| Basic | Concrete | Package | |
| Premium | Concrete | Package | |
| Platinum | Concrete | Package | |

---

## 2. Variables

### Calculation Flow

```ascii
Launch date ──> Is live ──┐
                          ▼
Target new members ──> New members ──────────────┐
                                                  ▼
               Churn rate ──> Members churned ──> Net new members ──> Members ──┐
                                    ▲                                           │
                                    └──── Members[-1] ──────────────────────────┘
                                                                          │
                              Monthly price ──> Quarterly price ──┐       │
                                                                  ▼       ▼
                                                                Revenue
```

### Variable Details

| # | Name | Formula Type | Dimensioned? | isConstant | Formula / Notes |
|---|------|-------------|-------------|------------|-----------------|
| 1 | Launch date | Assumption | No | Yes | DateTime input — single date for the whole model |
| 2 | Is live | Calculation | No | No | `IF(Periods >= Launch_date, 1, 0)` — returns 0 before launch, 1 after |
| 3 | Target new members | Assumption | **Yes** (Package) | No | New members joining per quarter, entered per package |
| 4 | New members | Calculation | **Yes** (Package) | No | `Target_new_members * Is_live` — zeros out pre-launch |
| 5 | Churn rate | Assumption | **Yes** (Package) | No | Quarterly churn as a %, entered per package |
| 6 | Members churned | Calculation | **Yes** (Package) | No | `Members[-1] * Churn_rate` |
| 7 | Net new members | Calculation | **Yes** (Package) | No | `New_members - Members_churned` |
| 8 | Members | Calculation | **Yes** (Package) | No | `Members[-1] + Net_new_members` — cumulative stock of members |
| 9 | Monthly price | Assumption | **Yes** (Package) | Yes | Fixed monthly price per member per package |
| 10 | Quarterly price | Calculation | **Yes** (Package) | No | `Monthly_price * 3` — converts to quarterly |
| 11 | Revenue | Calculation | **Yes** (Package) | No | `Members * Quarterly_price` |

**Self-reference note:** Members references `Members[-1]`, so the first period uses 0 (missing period → replace with zero).

### Dimensional Summaries

| Variable | groupSummaryType | Rationale |
|----------|-----------------|-----------|
| Target new members | Sum | Total across packages |
| New members | Sum | Total across packages |
| Churn rate | None | Per-package % — summing makes no sense |
| Members churned | Sum | Total across packages |
| Net new members | Sum | Total across packages |
| Members | Sum | Total members across packages |
| Monthly price | None | Per-package price — no meaningful sum |
| Quarterly price | None | Per-package price — no meaningful sum |
| Revenue | **Sum** | **Total gym revenue** |

---

## 3. Units

| Variable | Unit | TimeType | Notes |
|----------|------|----------|-------|
| Launch date | (none) | — | DateTime data type, isConstant |
| Is live | (none — unitless) | Timeless | Numeric 0/1 flag |
| Target new members | Member | Flow | New members per quarter |
| New members | (inferred) | Flow | = Member [Flow] × Timeless = Member [Flow] |
| Churn rate | Member / Member | Flow / Balance | Compound rate unit — ensures clean algebra (see below) |
| Members churned | (inferred) | Flow | = Balance[-1] × (Flow/Balance[-1]) = Flow ✓ |
| Net new members | (inferred) | Flow | Flow − Flow = Flow ✓ |
| Members | Member | **Balance** | **Defined unit** (self-referencing). Balance[-1] + Flow = Balance ✓ |
| Monthly price | GBP / Member | Flow / Balance | Price per member per period |
| Quarterly price | (inferred) | Flow / Balance | GBP [Flow] / Member [Balance] × scalar |
| Revenue | (inferred) | Flow | Balance × (Flow/Balance) = Flow ✓ → GBP [Flow] |

**Why compound unit for Churn rate?** Using `Member [Flow] / Member [Balance]` means:
- `Members[-1] × Churn rate` = `Balance[-1] × (Flow / Balance[-1])` = `Flow` 
- This matches New members (also Flow), so `New members − Members churned` has no unit mismatch

---

## 4. Layout

### Assumptions Sheet
All 4 ModelAssumptions in one sheet:

| LineGroup | Assumptions |
|-----------|------------|
| Timing | Launch date |
| Membership | Target new members, Churn rate |
| Pricing | Monthly price |

### Calculations Sheet — Timing
| LineGroup | Variables |
|-----------|----------|
| Launch timing | Launch date, Is live |

### Calculations Sheet — Membership & Revenue
| LineGroup | Variables |
|-----------|----------|
| New members | Target new members, New members |
| Churn | Churn rate, Members churned, Net new members |
| Membership | Members |
| Pricing | Monthly price, Quarterly price |
| Revenue | Revenue |

> **Note:** Assumption-type Variables (Launch date, Target new members, Churn rate, Monthly price) appear on the **Calculations** sheets to bring in their linked ModelAssumption values. The ModelAssumptions themselves live on the Assumptions sheet. This follows the standard input/calculation separation pattern.

---

## 5. Implementation Steps

1. **Create Tags** — Member (abstract, for units), Package dimension (abstract + 3 concrete children)
2. **Create Variables** — All 11 variables with correct units, formulas, and dimension references
3. **Create Layout** — Assumptions sheet + 2 Calculations sheets with LineGroups
4. **Verify** — Run model health check to confirm no errors or warnings
", explanation="Draft gym revenue model plan", path="plans/gym-revenue-model.md")
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"path":"plans/gym-revenue-model.md","size_bytes":6508,"success":true}
[TOOL]: get_plan_approval(explanation="Submit gym revenue model plan", file_path="plans/gym-revenue-model.md")
[APPROVAL_REQUEST]: Plan ready for review: plans/gym-revenue-model.md
[USER]: Go ahead
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me get started! I'll set up tasks to track progress, then begin building.
[TOOL]: add_tasks(descriptions=["Create Tags (Member abstract, Package dimension with 3 children)","Create Variables (all 11 with units, formulas, dimensions)","Create Layout (Assumptions sheet + 2 Calculations sheets)","Run model health check"], explanation="Set up task list for gym model")
[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Get build-structure workflow", parameters={"category":"build-structure"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":4,"success":true,"task_ids":["task-1","task-2","task-3","task-4"]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"category":"build-structure","content":"# Build Model Structure\r\n\r\n## Purpose\r\nUse this workflow when creating or modifying the Model's Variable and Assumption structure.\r\n\r\n## Prerequisites\r\n- Model context is set (`ModelAction(action='set-current')`)\r\n- You understand the Model's purpose (what outputs are needed)\r\n- Retrieve `variables` and `assumptions` object instructions if you haven't already\r\n\r\n## Build Order\r\n\r\nBuilding a Model structure follows a bottom-up approach for inputs and top-down for planning:\r\n\r\n### 1. Plan Top-Down\r\nStart with the desired outputs and work backwards:\r\n- What are the final output Variables? (e.g., Revenue, Profit, Cash Flow)\r\n- What calculations produce those outputs?\r\n- What inputs (Assumptions) feed those calculations?\r\n- Are there Dimensions? (e.g., by Region, by Product)\r\n\r\n### 2. Create Tags and Dimensions (if needed)\r\nIf the Model uses Dimensions:\r\n- Create Abstract Tags for each Dimension (e.g., \"Region\", \"Product\")\r\n- Create Concrete Tags as children (e.g., \"UK\", \"France\" under \"Region\")\r\n- Concrete Tags reference their parent via `isATagIds`\r\n- Retrieve `tags` object instructions for API details\r\n\r\n### 3. Create Scenarios and Sensitivities (if beyond Base)\r\nIf the Model needs multiple Scenarios or Sensitivities:\r\n- Create additional Scenarios with `basedOnScenarioId` referencing Base or another Scenario\r\n- Create Sensitivities for variance analysis\r\n- Retrieve `scenarios` object instructions for API details\r\n\r\n### 4. Build Variables Bottom-Up\r\nCreate Variables from inputs to outputs:\r\n\r\n**a) Assumption Variables first:**\r\n- Create the Variable with `defaultFormulaType: Assumption`\r\n- Set `unitOption: Defined` and define the Unit with correct TimeType\r\n- Add `tagParents` for Dimensional Variables\r\n- ModelAssumptions are created automatically when providing inline assumption values via TimeSegments\r\n- OR create ModelAssumptions separately and link via TimeSegments\r\n\r\n**b) Calculation Variables next:**\r\n- Create with `defaultFormulaType: Calculation`\r\n- Define `defaultCalculation` with `formulaText` referencing previously-created Variables\r\n- Set `unitOption: Inferred` (default for Calculations) unless you need a specific Unit\r\n- For Dimensional Variables, add matching `tagParents`\r\n\r\n**c) Aggregation Variables (if needed):**\r\n- Create when different Dimension parts have different calculation logic\r\n- Set `aggregatedVariableIds` to reference the part Variables\r\n- Set `groupSummaryType` (usually `Sum`)\r\n\r\n### 5. Validate Structure\r\nAfter creating all Variables:\r\n- Check for unit warnings\r\n- Verify calculation dependencies resolve correctly\r\n- Use `get-details` on key Variables to confirm their computed values\r\n\r\n## Common Patterns\r\n\r\n### Simple Linear Model\r\nInput -\u003e Calculation -\u003e Output\r\n```\r\nPrice (Assumption) -\u003e Revenue = Price x Volume (Calculation) -\u003e Profit = Revenue - Costs (Calculation)\r\nVolume (Assumption) /\r\nCosts (Assumption) /\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Dimensional Model\r\nSame structure but with `tagParents` on Variables that need to expand across Dimensions.\r\n\r\n### Model with Time Flexibility (Rearranging)\r\nFor Actuals + Forecast models, see the Rearranging section in `variables` object instructions.\r\n\r\n## Key Rules\r\n- Assumption Variables must have `unitOption: Defined` with appropriate TimeTypes: Flow or Balance for tagged UnitParts, Timeless for unitless UnitParts\r\n- Set `isConstant: true` on Variables with time-invariant values (fixed rates, conversion factors)\r\n- Calculation Variables default to `unitOption: Inferred`\r\n- Each ModelSheet type supports only one kind of LineItem\r\n- Assumption-type Variables belong on Calculation sheets, not Assumption sheets\r\n","description":"Workflow for creating Variables, Assumptions, Tags, and Scenarios","title":"Build Model Structure","topics":["Variables","ModelAssumptions","Tags","Dimensions","structure","build"]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Good, let me get the object instructions for Tags and Variables, then start creating.
[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Get tag creation instructions", parameters={"category":"tags"})
[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Get variable creation instructions", parameters={"category":"variables"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"category":"tags","content":"# Working with Tags\r\n\r\n## Overview\r\n\r\nTags provide categorization, dimensional expansion, and unit definitions. The Abstract→Concrete Tag hierarchy is the foundation for Dimensions, Validation dropdowns, and Units.\r\n\r\n## Tag Types\r\n\r\n### Abstract Tags\r\n- Define categories/dimensions (e.g., \"Region\", \"Product\", \"Currency\")\r\n- Can serve as Dimensions when Variables reference them via `tagParents`\r\n- Have `concreteChildrenOrder` to control display order\r\n- Have `tagProperties` for advanced UnitPart control\r\n\r\n### Concrete Tags\r\n- Specific instances (e.g., \"UK\", \"France\", \"GBP\")\r\n- Reference their Abstract parent(s) via `isATagIds`\r\n- Become dimension members or dropdown options\r\n\r\n## Creating Tags for Dimensions\r\n\r\n### Step 1: Create the Abstract Tag\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"action\": \"create\",\r\n  \"object_type\": \"Tag\",\r\n  \"parameters\": {\r\n    \"name\": \"Region\",\r\n    \"tagType\": \"Abstract\"\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Step 2: Create Concrete Tags\r\nUse a **bulk create** operation to create all Concrete children in a single tool call. The creation order determines the default dimension display order and the row order used by `expand-dimensions` and inline assumption grids. Items in a bulk operation are processed sequentially, so the order of the `items` array is preserved.\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"action\": \"create\",\r\n  \"object_type\": \"Tag\",\r\n  \"parameters\": {\r\n    \"bulk\": true,\r\n    \"items\": [\r\n      {\r\n        \"name\": \"UK\",\r\n        \"tagType\": \"Concrete\",\r\n        \"isATagIds\": [\"-regionAbstractTagId\"]\r\n      },\r\n      {\r\n        \"name\": \"France\",\r\n        \"tagType\": \"Concrete\",\r\n        \"isATagIds\": [\"-regionAbstractTagId\"]\r\n      },\r\n      {\r\n        \"name\": \"Germany\",\r\n        \"tagType\": \"Concrete\",\r\n        \"isATagIds\": [\"-regionAbstractTagId\"]\r\n      }\r\n    ]\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n**Important**: Do NOT create multiple Concrete Tags using parallel tool calls — their creation order is not guaranteed, which means the dimension row order may not match what you expect. Always use a single bulk operation to ensure the correct order.\r\n\r\n### Step 3 (Optional): Set Display Order\r\nIf you need to reorder children after creation, update the Abstract Tag's `concreteChildrenOrder`:\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"action\": \"update\",\r\n  \"object_type\": \"Tag\",\r\n  \"parameters\": {\r\n    \"id\": \"-regionAbstractTagId\",\r\n    \"concreteChildrenOrder\": [\"-ukTagId\", \"-franceTagId\", \"-germanyTagId\"]\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n## Tags for Validation Dropdowns\r\n\r\nSame structure as Dimensions — create an Abstract Tag with Concrete children. Then set `validationDimensionId` on the Variable to the Abstract Tag ID, and set `dataType: Validation`.\r\n\r\nExample: \"Yes/No\" dropdown\r\n- Abstract: \"Yes/No Option\"\r\n- Concrete: \"Yes\", \"No\"\r\n\r\n## Tags for Units\r\n\r\nAbstract Tags also serve as the basis for UnitParts. A UnitPart references an Abstract Tag via `tagId`. Common examples:\r\n- \"GBP\" Abstract Tag → UnitPart for currency\r\n- \"Customer\" Abstract Tag → UnitPart for counting\r\n\r\n## UnitPartModifiers\r\n\r\nWhen creating dimensional Assumptions, the dimension context is encoded as modifiers on UnitParts. Each modifier references a Concrete Tag:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"unit\": {\r\n    \"unitParts\": [{\r\n      \"tagId\": \"-gbpTagId\",\r\n      \"timeType\": \"Flow\",\r\n      \"modifiers\": [\r\n        { \"tagId\": \"-ukConcreteTagId\" }\r\n      ]\r\n    }]\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\nThis creates a UnitPart of \"GBP (UK)\" — encoding that this assumption belongs to the UK dimension member.\r\n\r\nFor multiple Dimensions, add multiple modifiers:\r\n```json\r\n\"modifiers\": [\r\n  { \"tagId\": \"-ukConcreteTagId\" },\r\n  { \"tagId\": \"-premiumConcreteTagId\" }\r\n]\r\n```\r\n\r\n## contextVarianceMap\r\n\r\nControls which UnitParts vary with which Dimensions. Structure:\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"contextVarianceMap\": {\r\n    \"\u003cunitPartId\u003e\": [\"\u003cdimensionTagId1\u003e\", \"\u003cdimensionTagId2\u003e\"],\r\n    \"\u003cunitPartId2\u003e\": [\"\u003cdimensionTagId1\u003e\"]\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n- **Keys**: UnitPart IDs from the Variable's Unit (use `get-details` on the Unit to find these)\r\n- **Values**: Abstract Tag IDs from the Variable's `tagParents`\r\n- **Default**: All UnitParts vary with all Dimensions (usually correct)\r\n- **Custom**: Only needed when different UnitParts in a ratio have different dimensional behavior\r\n\r\n### Example: Bonus Pot Percentage\r\nVariable \"Bonus Pot % by Region\" with Unit `GBP/GBP`:\r\n- Numerator GBP varies by Region (each region's share)\r\n- Denominator GBP does NOT vary (represents total pot)\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"contextVarianceMap\": {\r\n    \"\u003cnumerator-gbp-unitpart-id\u003e\": [\"\u003cregion-tag-id\u003e\"],\r\n    \"\u003cdenominator-gbp-unitpart-id\u003e\": []\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n## TagNamespaces\r\n\r\nModels can only reference Tags within their TagNamespace or descendant namespaces. When creating Tags for a Model, ensure they're in the correct namespace.\r\n\r\n## Best Practices\r\n\r\n1. Use descriptive names for Abstract Tags — they appear as dimension headers\r\n2. Create Concrete children using a **bulk create** operation (not parallel tool calls) to preserve intended order\r\n3. Use `concreteChildrenOrder` only when you need to reorder existing children\r\n4. Use the same Abstract Tags for both Dimensions and Units when appropriate\r\n5. Only customize `contextVarianceMap` when the default \"all vary with all\" is incorrect\r\n","description":"Object reference: Tag creation, Abstract/Concrete setup, Dimensions, contextVarianceMap, UnitPartModifiers","title":"Working with Tags","topics":["Tag","Abstract","Concrete","Dimensions","UnitPartModifiers","contextVarianceMap","TagNamespace"]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"category":"variables","content":"# Working with Variables\r\n\r\n## Overview\r\n\r\nVariables are the primary calculation containers in Models. This guide covers complex Variable properties and patterns that require deeper understanding beyond basic schema descriptions.\r\n\r\n## Targeted Editing (Partial Updates)\r\n\r\nVariable updates support targeted edits. Only include the properties you want to change. Omitted properties are preserved.\r\n\r\n- **Omitted property**: keeps the existing value\r\n- **Explicit null**: clears the value (when allowed by the schema)\r\n\r\nExample (update just the name):\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"id\": \"var-123\",\r\n  \"name\": \"Updated Variable Name\"\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n## Key Concepts\r\n\r\n**Variable**: A calculation container with a `defaultFormulaType` that determines its behavior:\r\n- **Calculation**: Uses mathematical formulas referencing other Variables\r\n- **Assumption**: Gets values from ModelAssumption objects (user inputs)\r\n- **Aggregation**: Collects Variables representing Dimension parts into a Dimension-level Variable\r\n\r\n**Dimensions**: Abstract Tags with Concrete Tag children that expand Variables across multiple categories. When a Variable references an Abstract Tag via `tagParents`, it automatically expands to generate separate calculation lines for each Concrete child.\r\n\r\n## Defining Calculations with formulaText\r\n\r\n### Overview\r\n\r\nWhen creating or updating Calculation Variables, you can define the formula using `formulaText` - a human-readable string format - instead of the verbose `calculationParts` array.\r\n\r\n### Where to Use\r\n\r\nThe `formulaText` property can be used inside any `calculation` or `defaultCalculation` object:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"name\": \"Profit\",\r\n  \"defaultFormulaType\": \"Calculation\",\r\n  \"defaultCalculation\": {\r\n    \"formulaText\": \"Revenue - Costs\"\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Syntax\r\n\r\n#### Variable References\r\n- Use the Variable name directly: `Revenue`\r\n- Quote names with special characters: `\"Revenue (Net)\"`\r\n- Quote names with spaces: `\"Total Revenue\"`\r\n\r\n#### Operators\r\n- Addition: `+`\r\n- Subtraction: `-`\r\n- Multiplication: `*`\r\n- Division: `/`\r\n- Exponentiation: `^`\r\n- Parentheses for grouping: `(Revenue - Costs) * 100`\r\n\r\n#### Constants\r\n- Numbers: `100`, `3.14`, `-5`\r\n- Negative values: `-100` or `0 - 100`\r\n\r\n#### Period Offsets\r\n- Previous period: `Revenue[-1]`\r\n- Two periods back: `Revenue[-2]`\r\n- Useful for growth calculations: `Revenue - Revenue[-1]`\r\n\r\n#### Period References\r\nThe `Periods` keyword returns the current period's end date as a date value. This is useful for creating timing flexibility, e.g. `Is Live = Periods \u003e Launch Date`\r\n\r\nKey points:\r\n- Returns the **end date** of the period (e.g., 31 Dec for a Calendar Year)\r\n- Supports offsets: `Periods[-1]` returns the previous period's end date\r\n- Compare against date-type Assumption Variables (Variables with date values)\r\n\r\nFinancial modeling best practice with Periods:\r\n- When flexible timing is required use Variables with DateType `Date` (Model periods don't have a time component)\r\n- It is always best to create a `Boolean` Variable for a timing condition (e.g. `Service is live`) and then to multiply that by the relevant Variable, rather than perform both timing logic and calculation in a single Variable\r\n\r\n#### Functions\r\n- Standard functions: `SUM(...)`, `MAX(...)`, `MIN(...)`, `IF(...)`\r\n- Example: `IF(Revenue \u003e 0, Profit / Revenue, 0)`\r\n\r\n### Examples\r\n\r\n**Simple calculation:**\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"defaultCalculation\": {\r\n    \"formulaText\": \"Revenue - Costs\"\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n**With period offset (growth calculation):**\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"defaultCalculation\": {\r\n    \"formulaText\": \"Revenue - Revenue[-1]\"\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n**With parentheses and constants:**\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"defaultCalculation\": {\r\n    \"formulaText\": \"(Revenue - Costs) / Revenue * 100\"\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n**With quoted variable names:**\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"defaultCalculation\": {\r\n    \"formulaText\": \"\\\"Net Revenue\\\" - \\\"Operating Costs\\\"\"\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n**With period reference (date comparison):**\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"defaultCalculation\": {\r\n    \"formulaText\": \"Periods \u003e \\\"Launch Date\\\"\"\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Precedence Rules\r\n\r\n- If both `formulaText` and `calculationParts` are provided, `calculationParts` takes precedence\r\n- `formulaText` is converted to `calculationParts` before the Variable is created/updated\r\n- The API response includes `formulaText` generated from the stored `calculationParts`\r\n\r\n### Error Handling\r\n\r\nParse errors return structured error messages with:\r\n- Position in the formula where the error occurred\r\n- What was found vs. what was expected\r\n- Hints for resolution (e.g., \"Variable 'Unknown' not found in Model\")\r\n\r\n## Aggregation Variables\r\n\r\n### Critical Understanding: Aggregation is NOT Summing\r\n\r\n**Common Misconception**: Aggregation Variables \"sum\" other Variables.\r\n\r\n**Reality**: Aggregation Variables **collect** Variables that each represent a part of a Dimension into a Variable of that Dimension.\r\n\r\n### Example: Regional Revenues\r\n\r\nSuppose you have:\r\n- **Revenues-South**: Calculation Variable for southern region revenues\r\n- **Revenues-North**: Calculation Variable for northern region revenues\r\n- Both are Concrete Tags under the \"Region\" Abstract Tag (Dimension)\r\n\r\nYou can create:\r\n- **Revenues by Region**: Aggregation Variable that collects Revenues-South and Revenues-North\r\n\r\nThe Aggregation Variable expands to show:\r\n- Revenues by Region (South) = Revenues-South\r\n- Revenues by Region (North) = Revenues-North\r\n\r\nEach region may calculate revenues differently, but the Aggregation Variable provides a unified Dimension-level view.\r\n\r\n### When to Use Aggregation\r\n\r\n- When you have Variables representing Dimension parts (e.g., regions, products, markets)\r\n- When you want a Dimension-level Variable that combines these parts\r\n- When each part may have different calculation logic\r\n\r\n### Property: `aggregatedVariableIds`\r\n\r\n- **Type**: `array[string]` - Array of Variable IDs\r\n- **Relevant When**: `defaultFormulaType` is `Aggregation`\r\n- **Purpose**: Lists the Variables representing Dimension parts to collect\r\n- **Note**: These Variables must represent parts of the same Dimension(s) that the Aggregation Variable uses\r\n\r\n## contextVarianceMap\r\n\r\n### Purpose\r\n\r\nThe `contextVarianceMap` defines which unit parts vary with which Dimensions. This is critical for Variables with both:\r\n- **Dimensions** (via `tagParents`)\r\n- **Defined units** (via `unitOption: Defined`)\r\n\r\n### When It's Relevant\r\n\r\n- Variable has `unitOption: Defined` (not Inferred)\r\n- Variable has Dimensions (via `tagParents` with at least one parent)\r\n- **Both conditions must be true**\r\n\r\n### Structure\r\n\r\nThe map is a dictionary where:\r\n- **Key**: Unit part ID (e.g., \"GBP\", \"Member\", \"Month\")\r\n- **Value**: Set of Dimension (TagParent) IDs that this unit part varies with\r\n\r\n### Example\r\n\r\nSuppose a Variable has:\r\n- Unit: \"GBP per Member per Month\" (with UnitPart IDs: `up-gbp-123`, `up-member-456`, `up-month-789`)\r\n- Dimensions: \"Region\" (Tag ID: `tag-region-abc`) and \"Product\" (Tag ID: `tag-product-def`)\r\n\r\nThe default `contextVarianceMap` would be:\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"up-gbp-123\": [\"tag-region-abc\", \"tag-product-def\"],\r\n  \"up-member-456\": [\"tag-region-abc\", \"tag-product-def\"],\r\n  \"up-month-789\": [\"tag-region-abc\", \"tag-product-def\"]\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n**Important**: The map uses actual object IDs, not human-readable names:\r\n- **Keys**: UnitPart IDs from the Variable's Unit (use `get-details` on the Unit to find these)\r\n- **Values**: Tag IDs of the Dimensions from `tagParents` (Abstract Tag IDs)\r\n\r\nThis means all unit parts vary with all Dimensions (the default).\r\n\r\n### Custom contextVarianceMap\r\n\r\nYou only need to provide a custom `contextVarianceMap` when:\r\n- You want specific unit parts to vary with specific Dimensions only\r\n- The default \"all vary with all\" doesn't match your requirements\r\n\r\n**Important**: Each Dimension must vary with at least one unit part. Otherwise, there wouldn't be variance for that Dimension.\r\n\r\n### Property: `contextVarianceMap`\r\n\r\n- **Type**: `object` (dictionary mapping unit part IDs to Dimension ID sets)\r\n- **Relevant When**: `unitOption` is `Defined` AND Variable has Dimensions\r\n- **Default**: Automatically generated as \"all Dimensions vary with all unit parts\"\r\n- **Rarely Required**: Most Variables use the default map\r\n\r\n## groupSummaryType\r\n\r\n### Purpose\r\n\r\nControls how a Variable summarizes across all Dimensions when creating summary lines.\r\n\r\n### Values\r\n\r\n#### `None`\r\n- No automatic summary behavior\r\n- Variable appears only at the detailed Dimension level\r\n\r\n#### `Sum`\r\n- Always performs a simple sum across all Dimension items\r\n- Example: If you have Revenues by Region (South, North), Sum gives Total Revenues = South + North\r\n\r\n#### `Auto`\r\n- Performs the Variable's calculation on the summary lines of referenced Variables\r\n- Useful when the result differs from a simple sum\r\n- **Example**: Weighted average price\r\n  - If Price = Revenue / Volume\r\n  - Auto calculates: Total Price = Total Revenue / Total Volume\r\n  - This is different from averaging individual prices\r\n\r\n#### `Rearranged`\r\n- Similar to Auto, but requires a parent Variable reference\r\n- Used when the summary calculation can only be computed from parent Variables\r\n- **Example**: Average price when Price is an input (not calculated)\r\n  - If Price is an input Variable (not Revenue/Volume)\r\n  - You need to rearrange: Price = Revenue / Volume\r\n  - But Revenue and Volume are parent Variables\r\n  - Rearranged uses `groupSummaryRearrangedParentId` to reference the parent for calculation\r\n\r\n### When to Use Each\r\n\r\n| Use Case | groupSummaryType | Notes |\r\n|----------|------------------|-------|\r\n| Simple totals | `Sum` | Direct sum of all Dimension items |\r\n| Calculated metrics | `Auto` | Recalculate formula on summary lines |\r\n| Input-based metrics | `Rearranged` | Calculate from parent Variables |\r\n\r\n### Property: `groupSummaryType`\r\n\r\n- **Type**: `enum` - `None`, `Sum`, `Auto`, `Rearranged`\r\n- **Default**: `None`\r\n- **Purpose**: Controls Dimension summary behavior\r\n\r\n### Property: `groupSummaryRearrangedParentId`\r\n\r\n- **Type**: `string` - Variable ID\r\n- **Required When**: `groupSummaryType` is `Rearranged`\r\n- **Purpose**: References the parent Variable to base the Rearranged summary calculation on\r\n- **Example**: For weighted averages requiring parent data\r\n\r\n## Unit System\r\n\r\n### Defined vs Inferred\r\n\r\n#### `unitOption: Defined`\r\n- Unit is explicitly set via the `unit` property\r\n- Used for Assumption and Aggregation Variables (default)\r\n- Can also be used for Calculation Variables\r\n\r\n#### `unitOption: Inferred`\r\n- Unit is automatically calculated from the formula\r\n- Only available for Calculation Variables\r\n- Based on the Variables referenced in the calculation\r\n- If unit cannot be calculated, a unit error is shown\r\n\r\n### Unit Factoring (`applyFactoring`)\r\n\r\n**Purpose**: Automatically adjusts calculations when the Variable's unit factor differs from the calculated unit factor.\r\n\r\n**How It Works**:\r\n- Factoring is done automatically based on units\r\n- Only works if `unitOption` is `Defined`\r\n- The Variable's unit must have a different factor from the calculated unit\r\n- Example: Variable has unit in millions (factorPower 6/1), but calculation returns thousands (factorPower 3/1)\r\n- Setting `applyFactoring: true` automatically adjusts the calculation (divides by 10^3)\r\n\r\n**Property**: `applyFactoring`\r\n- **Type**: `boolean`\r\n- **Default**: `false`\r\n- **Purpose**: Auto-adjust when Variable unit factor differs from calculated unit factor\r\n- **Note**: User doesn't need to multiply or divide within the Variable's calculation\r\n\r\n### Unit Validation\r\n\r\n- Automatic unit compatibility checking across Variable references\r\n- Unit inconsistencies generate warnings, not errors - calculations still execute\r\n- `overrideUnitError: true` allows bypassing unit validation when needed\r\n\r\n**When to use `overrideUnitError`:**\r\n- The calculated unit doesn't match the Defined unit, but the result is semantically correct\r\n- Example: `Balance[-1] × Timeless` infers as `Balance[-1]`, but you know it should be `Flow`\r\n- Always set `overrideUnitError: true` at the same time as setting the Defined unit — don't set the Defined unit first and then override in a separate step\r\n\r\n**When to use a compound unit instead:**\r\n- When a rate converts between TimeTypes (e.g., stock to flow), give it a compound unit\r\n- Example: Churn Rate = `Member [Flow] / Member [Balance[-1]]` — then `Members[-1] × Churn Rate` resolves to `Member [Flow]` without needing an override\r\n- Compound units are preferred over overrides because they make the algebra self-documenting\r\n\r\n## NumberFormat Selection\r\n\r\nThe `numberFormatId` property controls how Variable values are displayed. Always set an appropriate format.\r\n\r\n### Common Inbuilt Format IDs\r\n\r\n| ID | Format | Use For |\r\n|----|--------|---------|\r\n| `General` | General | Boolean, Validation, String |\r\n| `ThousandSeparator0Dp` | #,##0 | Standard integers (default) |\r\n| `TwoDecimalPlaces` | 0.00 | Decimals without thousands separator |\r\n| `Pct1Dp` | 0.0% | Percentages (growth, rate, margin, yield) |\r\n| `Date1` | dd mmm yy | Date values |\r\n| `GBP2Dp` | £#,##0.00 | GBP currency |\r\n| `USD2Dp` | $#,##0.00 | USD currency |\r\n| `EUR2Dp` | €#,##0.00 | EUR currency |\r\n\r\nUse `Pct1Dp` when Variable name contains: %, pct, percentage, growth, rate, inflation, margin, yield.\r\n\r\nIf the required format isn't listed above, use `filter` to find other available formats, or `create` to add a new one.\r\n\r\n## TimeSegments\r\n\r\n### Purpose\r\n\r\nAllow Variables to change formula behavior across different time periods.\r\n\r\n### Types of TimeSegments\r\n\r\n#### Assumption TimeSegments\r\n- Provide values from ModelAssumption objects for specific periods/dimensions\r\n- Can override the default assumption for specific time ranges\r\n\r\n#### Calculation TimeSegments\r\n- Provide different calculation formulas for specific time periods\r\n- **Critical Constraint**: Calculation formulas within TimeSegments can only reference the same Variable with period offsets (e.g., `[-1]` for previous period)\r\n- They cannot reference other Variables to prevent circular dependencies\r\n\r\n### SegmentPeriod Types\r\n\r\nEach TimeSegment has a `start` and optionally an `end`, each defined by a SegmentPeriod. Available types:\r\n\r\n- **Auto** — automatically determined from adjacent segments\r\n- **FixedPeriod** — a specific date code (requires `fixedPeriodDateCode`)\r\n- **PeriodsFromStartGeneric** — Nth period from model start (requires `genericPeriodsFromStart`, 1-indexed)\r\n- **PeriodsFromEndGeneric** — Nth period from model end (requires `genericPeriodsFromEnd`, 1-indexed)\r\n- **RelativeToActuals** — offset from the last Actuals period (requires `lastActualsOffset`)\r\n  - `0` = last period of Actuals\r\n  - `+1` = 1st period of Forecast\r\n  - `-1` = 2nd-to-last period of Actuals\r\n  - Requires `lastActualsPeriodId` to be set on model Timings; if unset, resolution returns null\r\n\r\nUse `help` with `objectType: \"SegmentPeriod\"` for full schema details.\r\n\r\n### Creating Assumptions Inline with TimeSegments\r\n\r\nWhen creating a Variable with Assumption TimeSegments, you can provide assumption values directly as a 2D grid. This eliminates the need to create ModelAssumption objects separately.\r\n\r\n#### Grid Convention\r\n\r\n- **Columns**: Time periods (chronological order, determined by TimeSegment's date range)\r\n- **Rows**: Dimension cross-product (if Variable has dimensions via `tagParents`)\r\n- **Empty/null values**: Skip (no assumption created for that cell)\r\n\r\n#### Example: Simple Time Series (No Dimensions)\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"name\": \"Growth Rate\",\r\n  \"defaultFormulaType\": \"Assumptions\",\r\n  \"timeSegments\": [{\r\n    \"start\": { \"segmentPeriodType\": \"Auto\" },\r\n    \"duration\": { \"segmentDurationType\": \"PeriodsGeneric\", \"genericPeriods\": 6 },\r\n    \"assumptions\": {\r\n      \"values\": [\r\n        [\"0.05\", \"0.06\", \"0.07\", \"0.08\", \"0.09\", \"0.10\"]\r\n      ]\r\n    }\r\n  }]\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\nThe Variable's name (\"Growth Rate\") is automatically used as the assumption prefix.\r\n\r\n#### Example: Dimensional Variable (Region Dimension)\r\n\r\nFor a Variable with Region dimension (North, South) and 3 time periods:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"name\": \"Sales Growth\",\r\n  \"defaultFormulaType\": \"Assumptions\",\r\n  \"tagParents\": { \"parents\": [{ \"tagId\": \"-regionDimensionId\" }] },\r\n  \"timeSegments\": [{\r\n    \"start\": { \"segmentPeriodType\": \"Auto\" },\r\n    \"duration\": { \"segmentDurationType\": \"PeriodsGeneric\", \"genericPeriods\": 3 },\r\n    \"assumptions\": {\r\n      \"values\": [\r\n        [\"0.05\", \"0.06\", \"0.07\"],\r\n        [\"0.04\", \"0.05\", \"0.06\"]\r\n      ]\r\n    }\r\n  }]\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\nRow order is deterministic (ordered by TagGroupWithParents.OrderedId). Use `expand-dimensions` action to discover the exact grid shape.\r\n\r\n#### Grid Shape Discovery\r\n\r\nBefore providing values, you can use the `expand-dimensions` action to discover the expected grid shape:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"objectType\": \"Variable\",\r\n  \"action\": \"expand-dimensions\",\r\n  \"id\": \"var-123\",\r\n  \"timeSegmentIndex\": 0\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\nReturns:\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"columns\": [\"2021\", \"2022\", \"2023\"],\r\n  \"rows\": [\"North\", \"South\"],\r\n  \"shape\": [2, 3]\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\nThis tells you:\r\n- The Variable expects a 2×3 grid\r\n- Rows are \"North\" then \"South\" (dimension cross-product)\r\n- Columns are \"2021\", \"2022\", \"2023\" (time periods)\r\n\r\n#### How It Works\r\n\r\nWhen you provide an `assumptions` object on a TimeSegment:\r\n1. The TimeSegment's formula type is automatically set to `Assumptions`\r\n2. After the Variable is created, ModelAssumption objects are generated from the grid\r\n3. Each grid cell creates one assumption with the correct Unit (including time and dimension modifiers)\r\n4. Assumptions are linked to the TimeSegment's formula\r\n5. Values use the Base Scenario by default\r\n\r\n#### When to Use\r\n\r\n- **Creating new Variables with Assumption TimeSegments**: Simplest approach\r\n- **Simple time series**: Just need to provide values across periods\r\n- **Dimensional assumptions**: Values vary by dimension and time\r\n\r\n#### When NOT to Use\r\n\r\n- **Updating existing assumptions**: Use direct ModelAssumption updates instead\r\n- **Multi-scenario values**: Use standard ModelAssumption creation with explicit values per scenario\r\n- **Complex sensitivity setups**: Create ModelAssumptions directly with sensitivity configuration\r\n\r\n### defaultAssumptionId\r\n\r\n**Purpose**: Fallback assumption for any period/dimensions in a TimeSegment that doesn't have a matching assumption.\r\n\r\n**When Used**:\r\n- Very rarely in practice\r\n- Typically, all assumption IDs are provided within TimeSegments\r\n- Example: If you want the Variable to have the value 0 except for periods that you provide a value for\r\n\r\n**Property**: `defaultAssumptionId`\r\n- **Type**: `string` - ModelAssumption ID\r\n- **Available For**: All formula types (even Calculation Variables can have Assumption TimeSegments)\r\n- **Purpose**: Fallback assumption for periods/dimensions without matching TimeSegment assumption\r\n\r\n### TimeSegment Coverage\r\n\r\nTimeSegments must collectively cover all periods without gaps or overlaps.\r\n\r\n## periodType\r\n\r\n### Purpose\r\n\r\nOverrides the Model's default period for this specific Variable.\r\n\r\n### Rules\r\n\r\n- Must be set to a broader time interval than the Model timings\r\n- Example: If Model is in weeks, you can define a Variable in months\r\n- `None` means \"use the Model's default period\"\r\n\r\n### Property: `periodType`\r\n\r\n- **Type**: `enum` - `None`, `Day`, `Week`, `Month`, `Quarter`, `YearCalendar`, `YearFiscal`\r\n- **Default**: `None` (use Model default)\r\n- **Purpose**: Override Model's default period for this Variable\r\n\r\n## validationDimensionId\r\n\r\n### Purpose\r\n\r\nDefines dropdown options for Validation-type Variables.\r\n\r\n### How It Works\r\n\r\n- Variable must have `dataType: Validation`\r\n- `validationDimensionId` references an Abstract Tag (Dimension)\r\n- The Concrete Tag children of that Abstract Tag become the dropdown options\r\n- Example: \"Yes/No\" Dimension with Concrete children \"Yes\" and \"No\"\r\n\r\n### Property: `validationDimensionId`\r\n\r\n- **Type**: `string` - Abstract Tag ID\r\n- **Required When**: `dataType` is `Validation`\r\n- **Purpose**: Abstract Tag defining dropdown options for Validation-type Variables\r\n\r\n## Common Patterns and Pitfalls\r\n\r\n### Pattern 1: Dimensional Aggregation\r\n\r\n**Scenario**: You have revenue calculations for each region, and want a total revenue Variable.\r\n\r\n**Correct Approach**:\r\n1. Create Calculation Variables: \"Revenues-South\", \"Revenues-North\" (each with Region Dimension)\r\n2. Create Aggregation Variable: \"Total Revenues\" with `aggregatedVariableIds: [\"Revenues-South\", \"Revenues-North\"]`\r\n3. Set `groupSummaryType: Sum` if you want summary lines\r\n\r\n**Incorrect**: Trying to sum the Variables in a Calculation formula - use Aggregation instead.\r\n\r\n### Pattern 2: Unit Factoring\r\n\r\n**Scenario**: Your Model works in thousands, but you want to display a Variable in millions.\r\n\r\n**Correct Approach**:\r\n1. Set Variable unit to millions (factorPower 6/1)\r\n2. Ensure calculation returns thousands (factorPower 3/1)\r\n3. Set `applyFactoring: true`\r\n4. System automatically adjusts (divides by 10^3)\r\n\r\n**Incorrect**: Manually dividing in the calculation formula.\r\n\r\n### Pattern 3: Weighted Averages\r\n\r\n**Scenario**: You want average price across all products.\r\n\r\n**If Price is Calculated** (Price = Revenue / Volume):\r\n- Use `groupSummaryType: Auto`\r\n- System recalculates: Total Price = Total Revenue / Total Volume\r\n\r\n**If Price is an Input**:\r\n- Use `groupSummaryType: Rearranged`\r\n- Set `groupSummaryRearrangedParentId` to reference Revenue or Volume parent\r\n- System rearranges calculation from parent Variables\r\n\r\n### Pitfall 1: Confusing Aggregation with Summing\r\n\r\n**Mistake**: Thinking `aggregatedVariableIds` creates a sum.\r\n\r\n**Reality**: Aggregation collects Dimension parts, not sums values.\r\n\r\n### Pitfall 2: Missing contextVarianceMap Condition\r\n\r\n**Mistake**: Providing `contextVarianceMap` when Variable has no Dimensions.\r\n\r\n**Reality**: `contextVarianceMap` is only relevant when Variable has both Dimensions AND Defined unit.\r\n\r\n### Pitfall 3: Wrong groupSummaryType\r\n\r\n**Mistake**: Using `Sum` for calculated metrics that need recalculation.\r\n\r\n**Reality**: Use `Auto` or `Rearranged` when the summary result differs from a simple sum.\r\n\r\n### Pitfall 4: Self-Referencing Variable with Inferred Unit\r\n\r\n**Mistake**: Creating a Calculation Variable that references itself with a period offset (e.g., `Balance[-1] + Inflow`) and leaving `unitOption: Inferred`.\r\n\r\n**Reality**: Self-referencing Variables require `unitOption: Defined`. The Unit system cannot resolve self-references to determine the inferred type. Always define the Unit explicitly with the appropriate TimeType (typically Balance for accumulator patterns).\r\n\r\n## Best Practices\r\n\r\n1. **Use Aggregation for Dimension-based collection**, not for simple summing\r\n2. **Rely on default contextVarianceMap** unless you have specific requirements\r\n3. **Use Auto for calculated metrics** that need recalculation on summary lines\r\n4. **Use Rearranged only when necessary** - when calculation requires parent Variables\r\n5. **Set applyFactoring when unit factors differ** - don't manually adjust in formulas\r\n6. **Use defaultAssumptionId sparingly** - prefer explicit TimeSegment assumptions\r\n7. **Validate periodType compatibility** - must be broader than Model timings\r\n\r\n## Retrieving Calculated Values\r\n\r\n### get-values Operation\r\n\r\nRetrieve calculated values for one or more Variables:\r\n\r\n```\r\nQueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='get-values', parameters={\r\n  'ids': ['var-1', 'var-2'],\r\n  'periods': 'sample',        # 'all', 'first', 'last', 'first-N', 'last-N', 'sample', or specific periods\r\n  'dimensions': 'summary',    # 'summary', 'all', or specific paths like 'UK/Small'\r\n  'case': 'Base/Base',        # Scenario/Sensitivity\r\n  'includeAnalysis': true     # Adds trend, min/max, growth rate\r\n})\r\n```\r\n\r\n**Key considerations**:\r\n- Use `periods: 'sample'` for a quick snapshot (first, middle, last)\r\n- Use `dimensions: 'summary'` unless you need individual dimension values\r\n- The `includeAnalysis` option adds trend classification and growth rate\r\n\r\n### compare-cases Operation\r\n\r\nCompare values between two cases (Scenario/Sensitivity combinations):\r\n\r\n```\r\nQueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='compare-cases', parameters={\r\n  'ids': ['profit'],\r\n  'baseCase': 'Base/Base',      # Required: baseline for comparison\r\n  'compareCase': 'Lean/Base',   # Required: case to compare against baseline\r\n  'periods': 'last'\r\n})\r\n```\r\n\r\nReturns values with variance from baseline (absolute and percentage difference).\r\n\r\n### trace-dependencies with Values\r\n\r\nAdd `includeValues: true` to see values alongside the dependency tree:\r\n\r\n```\r\nModelAction(action='trace-dependencies', variableId='profit', includeValues=true, valuePeriod='last')\r\n```\r\n\r\n### valueSummary in Filter\r\n\r\nAdd `valueSummary` to filter properties to see first/last values and trend:\r\n\r\n```\r\nQueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='filter', parameters={\r\n  'properties': ['name', 'valueSummary']\r\n})\r\n```\r\n\r\nReturns `valueSummary: { first: { period, value }, last: { period, value }, trend: 'growing' }` for each Variable.\r\n","description":"Object reference: Variable properties, formulaText, CalculationParts, TimeSegments, DimensionReferences, Aggregation, Units, retrieving calculated values","title":"Working with Variables","topics":["Variables","Calculations","Aggregation","Dimensions","Units","TimeSegments","contextVarianceMap","groupSummary","DimensionReference","get-values","compare-cases","valueSummary"]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Good, I have all the instructions I need. Let me start building! First, I'll get the help schemas for creating Tags and Variables, then begin creating objects.

## Step 1: Create Tags

I need to create the **Member** abstract tag (for units) and the **Package** dimension (abstract + 3 concrete children).
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get Tag create schema", object_type="Tag", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new Tag. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","notes":["Tag relationships: isATagIds links Concrete Tags to Abstract parents, relatesToTagIds links Concrete Tags to Concrete parents, isSameAsIds creates equivalence between Tags of the same type."],"object_type":"Tag","parameters":{"concreteChildrenOrder":{"relevant_when":{"tagType":"Abstract"},"type":"array[string]"},"isATagIds":{"type":"array[string]"},"isSameAsIds":{"type":"array[string]"},"name":{"required":true,"type":"string"},"relatesToTagIds":{"type":"array[string]"},"shortName":{"type":"string"},"tagNamespaceId":{"required":true,"type":"string"},"tagProperties":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='TagProperty'","type":"array[TagProperty]"},"tagType":{"required":true,"type":"enum","values":["Abstract","Concrete"]}}}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Now let me create the Tags. I'll create the two abstract tags first, then the concrete children in a bulk operation.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create Member abstract tag", object_type="Tag", parameters={"name":"Member","tagNamespaceId":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4jzi","tagType":"Abstract"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create Package abstract tag", object_type="Tag", parameters={"name":"Package","tagNamespaceId":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4jzi","tagType":"Abstract"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Created 1 of 1 Tag(s)","results":[{"data":{"success":true,"tag":{"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55vs","name":"Member","namespace":"Agent testing","tagType":"Abstract"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55vs","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Created 1 of 1 Tag(s)","results":[{"data":{"success":true,"tag":{"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH","name":"Package","namespace":"Agent testing","tagType":"Abstract"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Good, both abstract tags created. Now let me create the 3 concrete Package children in a single bulk operation to preserve order.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create Basic, Premium, Platinum tags", object_type="Tag", parameters={"bulk":true,"items":[{"isATagIds":["-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"],"name":"Basic","tagNamespaceId":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4jzi","tagType":"Concrete"},{"isATagIds":["-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"],"name":"Premium","tagNamespaceId":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4jzi","tagType":"Concrete"},{"isATagIds":["-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"],"name":"Platinum","tagNamespaceId":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4jzi","tagType":"Concrete"}]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"bulk":true,"failed":0,"mode":"best-effort","processed":3,"results":[{"data":{"success":true,"tag":{"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wg","isA":"1 relationships","name":"Basic","namespace":"Agent testing","tagType":"Concrete"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wg","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"tag":{"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wi","isA":"1 relationships","name":"Premium","namespace":"Agent testing","tagType":"Concrete"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wi","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"tag":{"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wk","name":"Platinum","namespace":"Agent testing","tagType":"Concrete"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wk","success":true}],"succeeded":3,"success":true}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Tags all created successfully. Let me mark that task done and move on to creating Variables.

[TOOL]: complete_task(explanation="Tags created successfully", task_id="task-1")
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get Variable create schema", object_type="Variable", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"success":true,"task_id":"task-1"}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new Variable. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","notes":["Updates support partial payloads - only include properties you want to change. For detailed guidance on complex properties (Aggregation, contextVarianceMap, groupSummary), use GetInstructions(category='variables')","Assumption and Aggregation Variables require unitOption: 'Defined' (the default). When unitOption is 'Defined', the unit property is required.","Minimal Unitless unit: {\"unitParts\": [{\"timeType\": \"Timeless\"}]}. For time-varying units, use timeType 'Flow' or 'Balance' with a tag. To mark a Variable as constant (no time variance), set isConstant: true. Note: {\"unitParts\": []} creates an Undefined unit (invalid for Assumptions)."],"object_type":"Variable","parameters":{"aggregatedVariableIds":{"description":"IDs of Variables representing Dimension parts to combine (not a sum - see GetInstructions)","relevant_when":{"defaultFormulaType":"Aggregation"},"type":"array[string]"},"applyFactoring":{"default":false,"description":"Auto-adjust when Variable unit factor differs from calculated unit factor","type":"boolean"},"columnSummaries":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='ColumnSummary'","type":"array[ColumnSummary]"},"contextVarianceMap":{"description":"Maps which unit parts vary with which Dimensions. Only relevant when Variable has Dimensions and Defined unit. Defaults to all-vary-with-all.","properties":{"contextVarianceMap":{"description":"Map from string key to HashSet`1. For value schema, query help with object_type='HashSet`1'.","properties":{},"type":"object"}},"relevant_when":{"unitOption":"Defined"},"type":"object"},"dataType":{"type":"enum","values":["Double","Integer","String","DateTime","Date","Boolean","Validation"]},"defaultAssumptionId":{"description":"Fallback assumption for periods/dimensions without matching TimeSegment assumption","type":"string"},"defaultCalculation":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='Calculation'","relevant_when":{"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation"},"type":"Calculation"},"defaultFormulaType":{"description":"The formula type for this Variable","required":true,"type":"enum","values":["Assumptions","Calculation","Aggregation"]},"groupSummaryRearrangedParentId":{"description":"Parent Variable for Rearranged summary calculation (e.g., weighted averages)","required_when":{"groupSummaryType":"Rearranged"},"type":"string"},"groupSummaryType":{"description":"Controls Dimension summary behavior: None, Sum (simple sum), Auto (recalculate), Rearranged (from parent)","type":"enum","values":["None","Sum","Auto","Rearranged"]},"isConstant":{"default":false,"description":"Whether this Variable's value is constant across all time periods","type":"boolean"},"name":{"required":true,"type":"string"},"numberFormatId":{"type":"string"},"overrideUnitError":{"default":false,"type":"boolean"},"periodType":{"description":"Overrides Model's default period. Must be broader than Model timings. None = use default.","type":"enum","values":["None","Day","Week","Month","Quarter","YearCalendar","YearFiscal"]},"tagIds":{"type":"array[string]"},"tagParents":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='TagParents'","type":"TagParents"},"timeSegments":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='TimeSegment'","type":"array[TimeSegment]"},"unit":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='Unit'","required_when":{"unitOption":"Defined"},"type":"Unit"},"unitOption":{"description":"Defined by default for Assumption/Aggregation Variables","relevant_when":{"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation"},"type":"enum","values":["Defined","Inferred"]},"validationDimensionId":{"description":"Abstract Tag defining dropdown options for Validation dataType Variables","required_when":{"dataType":"Validation"},"type":"string"}}}
[ASSISTANT]: 

## Step 2: Create Variables

I'll build bottom-up — Assumption Variables first, then Calculations. Let me get the TimeSegment and Unit help schemas since I'll need those for the Assumption Variables.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get TimeSegment schema", object_type="TimeSegment", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get Unit schema", object_type="Unit", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new TimeSegment. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","object_type":"TimeSegment","parameters":{"assumptionIds":{"type":"array[string]"},"duration":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='SegmentDuration'","type":"SegmentDuration"},"end":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='SegmentPeriod'","type":"SegmentPeriod"},"id":{"type":"string"},"modelFormulaType":{"type":"enum","values":["Auto","Assumptions","Calculation","Aggregation","Rearranged","NotApplicable"]},"start":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='SegmentPeriod'","type":"SegmentPeriod"}}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new Unit. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","object_type":"Unit","parameters":{"unitParts":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='UnitPart'","required":true,"type":"array[UnitPart]"}}}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me get the UnitPart schema too, then start creating variables.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get UnitPart schema", object_type="UnitPart", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new UnitPart. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","object_type":"UnitPart","parameters":{"dateTimeElement":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='DateTimeElement'","type":"DateTimeElement"},"factorPower":{"properties":{"denominator":{"type":"integer"},"numerator":{"type":"integer"}},"type":"object"},"id":{"type":"string"},"interval":{"type":"integer"},"modifiers":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='UnitPartModifier'","type":"array[UnitPartModifier]"},"order":{"description":"Power of this UnitPart as a fraction. numerator: 1 = standard position (e.g. GBP), numerator: -1 = denominator/inverse (e.g. 'per Member'). Example: GBP [Flow] / Member [Balance] has GBP with order 1/1 and Member with order -1/1","properties":{"denominator":{"type":"integer"},"numerator":{"type":"integer"}},"type":"object"},"tagId":{"description":"Null value represents a Unitless part","type":"string"},"timeOffset":{"type":"integer"},"timeType":{"required":true,"type":"enum","values":["Balance","Flow","Timeless"]}}}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Now I have all the schemas I need. Let me create all 11 variables. I'll start with the 4 Assumption Variables, then the 7 Calculation Variables.

Key IDs I'll need:
- **Member** abstract tag: `-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55vs`
- **Package** abstract tag: `-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH`
- **GBP** abstract tag: `-NuMtNA6o3nDVsfVrM-3`

### Assumption Variables first

I'll create all 4 Assumption Variables in a bulk operation:
1. **Launch date** — DateTime, no dimension, isConstant
2. **Target new members** — Member [Flow], dimensioned by Package
3. **Churn rate** — Member [Flow] / Member [Balance], dimensioned by Package
4. **Monthly price** — GBP [Flow] / Member [Balance], dimensioned by Package, isConstant
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create 4 Assumption Variables", object_type="Variable", parameters={"bulk":true,"items":[{"dataType":"Date","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","isConstant":true,"name":"Launch date","numberFormatId":"Date1","unit":{"unitParts":[{"timeType":"Timeless"}]}},{"dataType":"Double","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","groupSummaryType":"Sum","name":"Target new members","numberFormatId":"ThousandSeparator0Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"}]},"unit":{"unitParts":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55vs","timeType":"Flow"}]}},{"dataType":"Double","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","groupSummaryType":"None","name":"Churn rate","numberFormatId":"Pct1Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"}]},"unit":{"unitParts":[{"order":{"denominator":1,"numerator":1},"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55vs","timeType":"Flow"},{"order":{"denominator":1,"numerator":-1},"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55vs","timeType":"Balance"}]}},{"dataType":"Double","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","groupSummaryType":"None","isConstant":true,"name":"Monthly price","numberFormatId":"GBP2Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"}]},"unit":{"unitParts":[{"order":{"denominator":1,"numerator":1},"tagId":"-NuMtNA6o3nDVsfVrM-3","timeType":"Flow"},{"order":{"denominator":1,"numerator":-1},"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55vs","timeType":"Balance"}]}}]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"bulk":true,"failed":0,"mode":"best-effort","processed":4,"results":[{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","isConstant":"True","name":"Launch date","numberFormat":"dd mmm yy","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 1 assumption","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"sample":{"Dec 27":"N/A","Mar 25":"N/A","Sept 26":"N/A"},"trend":"unknown"},"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","isConstant":"False","name":"Target new members","numberFormat":"#,##0","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 36 assumptions","unit":"Member [Flow]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"dimensions":{"Basic":"N/A","Platinum":"N/A","Premium":"N/A"},"note":"Variable has no summary line","sample":{"Dec 27":"N/A","Mar 25":"N/A","Sept 26":"N/A"},"trend":"unknown"},"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","isConstant":"False","name":"Churn rate","numberFormat":"0.0%","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 36 assumptions","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"dimensions":{"Basic":"N/A","Platinum":"N/A","Premium":"N/A"},"note":"Variable has no summary line"},"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","isConstant":"True","name":"Monthly price","numberFormat":"\"£\"#,##0.00","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 3 assumptions","unit":"GBP [Flow]/Member [Balance]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","success":true}],"succeeded":4,"success":true}
[ASSISTANT]: 

All 4 Assumption Variables created successfully. Now let me create the 7 Calculation Variables. I'll do them in dependency order.

**Variables to create:**
1. **Is live** — `Periods >= "Launch date"` (Boolean, no dimension)
2. **New members** — `"Target new members" * "Is live"` (dimensioned)
3. **Members churned** — `Members[-1] * "Churn rate"` (dimensioned) — needs Members to exist first
4. **Net new members** — `"New members" - "Members churned"` (dimensioned)
5. **Members** — `Members[-1] + "Net new members"` (dimensioned, self-ref → Defined unit, Balance)
6. **Quarterly price** — `"Monthly price" * 3` (dimensioned)
7. **Revenue** — `Members * "Quarterly price"` (dimensioned)

Since Members churned references Members, and Members references Net new members which references Members churned — I need to be careful about ordering. Let me create Members first (it self-references), then Members churned, then the rest.

Actually, looking more carefully: Members = `Members[-1] + "Net new members"`, and Net new members = `"New members" - "Members churned"`, and Members churned = `Members[-1] * "Churn rate"`. So the dependency chain is: Members churned → Net new members → Members. Members churned references Members[-1] (period offset on Members itself). So I need Members to exist before Members churned can reference it.

Let me create them in this order:
1. Is live (no dependencies on other new vars)
2. New members (depends on Is live)
3. Members (self-referencing, depends on Net new members — but I'll create it referencing a not-yet-existing var... actually I need to create Members first with a placeholder, or create all at once)

Let me create Members first without a formula, then the others, then update Members with its formula.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create Is live and Members (stub)", object_type="Variable", parameters={"bulk":true,"items":[{"dataType":"Boolean","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"Periods \u003e= \"Launch date\""},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","name":"Is live","numberFormatId":"General","unitOption":"Inferred"},{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"0"},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","groupSummaryType":"Sum","name":"Members","numberFormatId":"ThousandSeparator0Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"}]},"unit":{"unitParts":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55vs","timeType":"Balance"}]},"unitOption":"Defined"}]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"bulk":true,"failed":0,"mode":"best-effort","processed":2,"results":[{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"growthRate":"0.0% per period","sample":{"Dec 27":"True","Mar 25":"True","Sept 26":"True"},"trend":"stable"},"calculation":"Periods \u003e= Launch date","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"Periods \u003e= Launch date","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56AB","isConstant":"False","name":"Is live","numberFormat":"General","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56AB","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"sample":{"Dec 27":"0","Mar 25":"0","Sept 26":"0"},"trend":"stable"},"calculation":"0","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"0","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2","isConstant":"False","name":"Members","numberFormat":"#,##0","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto","unit":"Member [Balance]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2","success":true}],"succeeded":2,"success":true}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Good — Is live and Members (stub) are created. Now I can create the remaining calculation variables that reference Members. Let me create New members, Members churned, Net new members, Quarterly price, and Revenue.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create remaining calc variables", object_type="Variable", parameters={"bulk":true,"items":[{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"\"Target new members\" * \"Is live\""},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","groupSummaryType":"Sum","name":"New members","numberFormatId":"ThousandSeparator0Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"}]},"unitOption":"Inferred"},{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"Members[-1] * \"Churn rate\""},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","groupSummaryType":"Sum","name":"Members churned","numberFormatId":"ThousandSeparator0Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"}]},"unitOption":"Inferred"},{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"\"New members\" - \"Members churned\""},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","groupSummaryType":"Sum","name":"Net new members","numberFormatId":"ThousandSeparator0Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"}]},"unitOption":"Inferred"},{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"\"Monthly price\" * 3"},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","groupSummaryType":"None","name":"Quarterly price","numberFormatId":"GBP2Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"}]},"unitOption":"Inferred"},{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"Members * \"Quarterly price\""},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","groupSummaryType":"Sum","name":"Revenue","numberFormatId":"GBP2Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55wH"}]},"unitOption":"Inferred"}]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"bulk":true,"failed":0,"mode":"best-effort","processed":5,"results":[{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"sample":{"Dec 27":"N/A","Mar 25":"N/A","Sept 26":"N/A"},"trend":"unknown"},"calculation":"Target new members [Auto] * Is live","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"Target new members * Is live","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56JL","isConstant":"False","name":"New members","numberFormat":"#,##0","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto","unit":"Member [Flow]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56JL","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"sample":{"Dec 27":"N/A","Mar 25":"N/A","Sept 26":"N/A"},"trend":"unknown"},"calculation":"Members [Auto]  [-1] * Churn rate [Auto]","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"Members[-1] * Churn rate","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc","isConstant":"False","name":"Members churned","numberFormat":"#,##0","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto","unit":"(Member [Balance [-1]].Member [Flow])/Member [Balance]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"sample":{"Dec 27":"N/A","Mar 25":"N/A","Sept 26":"N/A"},"trend":"unknown"},"calculation":"New members [Auto] - Members churned [Auto]","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"New members - Members churned","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56MX","isConstant":"False","name":"Net new members","numberFormat":"#,##0","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto","unit":"Undefined"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56MX","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"dimensions":{"Basic":"N/A","Platinum":"N/A","Premium":"N/A"},"note":"Variable has no summary line","sample":{"Dec 27":"N/A","Mar 25":"N/A","Sept 26":"N/A"},"trend":"unknown"},"calculation":"Monthly price [Auto] * 3","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"Monthly price * 3","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56OX","isConstant":"False","name":"Quarterly price","numberFormat":"\"£\"#,##0.00","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto","unit":"GBP [Flow]/Member [Balance]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56OX","success":true},{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"sample":{"Dec 27":"N/A","Mar 25":"N/A","Sept 26":"N/A"},"trend":"unknown"},"calculation":"Members [Auto] * Quarterly price [Auto]","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"Members * Quarterly price","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Px","isConstant":"False","name":"Revenue","numberFormat":"\"£\"#,##0.00","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto","unit":"GBP [Flow]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Px","success":true}],"succeeded":5,"success":true}
[ASSISTANT]: 

All 5 calculation variables created successfully. Now I need to update the Members stub with its real formula. I notice Net new members has an "Undefined" unit — let me check that after updating Members.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="update", explanation="Set Members real formula", object_type="Variable", parameters={"defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"Members[-1] + \"Net new members\""},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Updated 1 of 1 Variable(s)","results":[{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"sample":{"Dec 27":"N/A","Mar 25":"N/A","Sept 26":"N/A"},"trend":"unknown"},"calculation":"Members [Auto]  [-1] + Net new members [Auto]","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"Members[-1] + Net new members","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2","isConstant":"False","name":"Members","numberFormat":"#,##0","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto","unit":"Member [Balance]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Members is now correctly set with `Members[-1] + Net new members`. I noticed Net new members showed "Undefined" unit — this is because it's subtracting `New members` (Member [Flow]) from `Members churned` which has a compound inferred unit. Let me check the current state of Net new members and Members churned more carefully.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Check Members churned unit", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc","properties":["unit"]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Check Net new members unit", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56MX","properties":["unit"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"error":"Required parameter 'id' is missing"}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"error":"Required parameter 'id' is missing"}
[ASSISTANT]: Let me try the get-details calls with the correct parameter format.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Check Members churned unit details", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"markdown","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc","properties":["unit"]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Check Net new members unit details", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"markdown","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56MX","properties":["unit"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"error":"Required parameter 'id' is missing"}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"error":"Required parameter 'id' is missing"}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me try a different approach to check those units.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Check all variable units", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"markdown","name":"*members*"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: | Name | Id | Default Formula Type | Calculation | Unit | Number Format | Time Segments | Is Constant |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|
| Launch date | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI | Assumptions | - | Unitless [Timeless] | dd mmm yy | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 1 assumption | True |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc | Assumptions | - | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 36 assumptions | False |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw | Assumptions | - | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 36 assumptions | False |
| Monthly price | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC | Assumptions | - | GBP [Flow]/Member [Balance] | "£"#,##0.00 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 3 assumptions | True |
| Is live | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56AB | Calculation | Periods >= Launch date | Unitless [Timeless] | General | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2 | Calculation | Members [Auto]  [-1] + Net new members [Auto] | Member [Balance] | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| New members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56JL | Calculation | Target new members [Auto] * Is live | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Members churned | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc | Calculation | Members [Auto]  [-1] * Churn rate [Auto] | (Member [Balance [-1]].Member [Flow])/Member [Balance] | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Net new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56MX | Calculation | New members [Auto] - Members churned [Auto] | Undefined | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Quarterly price | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56OX | Calculation | Monthly price [Auto] * 3 | GBP [Flow]/Member [Balance] | "£"#,##0.00 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Revenue | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Px | Calculation | Members [Auto] * Quarterly price [Auto] | GBP [Flow] | "£"#,##0.00 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |


[ASSISTANT]: 

I can see the issue. Members churned has an inferred unit of `(Member [Balance [-1]].Member [Flow])/Member [Balance]` — the compound unit from the churn rate multiplication didn't fully simplify, so when Net new members tries to subtract it from `New members` (Member [Flow]), the units don't match and it shows "Undefined".

The cleanest fix is to give Members churned a **Defined unit** of `Member [Flow]` with `overrideUnitError: true`, since we know the result is indeed members lost per period (a flow). And similarly, Net new members should then infer correctly as Member [Flow].

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="update", explanation="Fix Members churned unit", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc","overrideUnitError":true,"unit":{"unitParts":[{"tagId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55vs","timeType":"Flow"}]},"unitOption":"Defined"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Updated 1 of 1 Variable(s)","results":[{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"sample":{"Dec 27":"N/A","Mar 25":"N/A","Sept 26":"N/A"},"trend":"unknown"},"calculation":"Members [Auto]  [-1] * Churn rate [Auto]","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"Members[-1] * Churn rate","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc","isConstant":"False","name":"Members churned","numberFormat":"#,##0","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto","unit":"Member [Flow]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Members churned now has `Member [Flow]`. Let me check that Net new members' unit resolved correctly now.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Verify Net new members unit fixed", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"markdown","name":"Net new members"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: | Name | Id | Default Formula Type | Calculation | Unit | Number Format | Time Segments | Is Constant |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|
| Launch date | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI | Assumptions | - | Unitless [Timeless] | dd mmm yy | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 1 assumption | True |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc | Assumptions | - | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 36 assumptions | False |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw | Assumptions | - | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 36 assumptions | False |
| Monthly price | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC | Assumptions | - | GBP [Flow]/Member [Balance] | "£"#,##0.00 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 3 assumptions | True |
| Is live | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56AB | Calculation | Periods >= Launch date | Unitless [Timeless] | General | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2 | Calculation | Members [Auto]  [-1] + Net new members [Auto] | Member [Balance] | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| New members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56JL | Calculation | Target new members [Auto] * Is live | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Members churned | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc | Calculation | Members [Auto]  [-1] * Churn rate [Auto] | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Net new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56MX | Calculation | New members [Auto] - Members churned [Auto] | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Quarterly price | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56OX | Calculation | Monthly price [Auto] * 3 | GBP [Flow]/Member [Balance] | "£"#,##0.00 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |
| Revenue | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Px | Calculation | Members [Auto] * Quarterly price [Auto] | GBP [Flow] | "£"#,##0.00 | `Mar 25 - Dec 27`: Auto | False |


[ASSISTANT]: 

All units are now clean across the board. Let me mark the Variables task complete and move on to the Layout.

[TOOL]: complete_task(explanation="All 11 variables created with units", task_id="task-2")
[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Get layout build instructions", parameters={"category":"build-layout"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"success":true,"task_id":"task-2"}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"category":"build-layout","content":"# Build Model Layout\n\n## Purpose\nUse this workflow when creating or modifying the Model's Excel Layout (ModelSheets, LineGroups, LineItems).\n\n## Prerequisites\n- Model context is set\n- Model structure exists (Variables and Assumptions created)\n- Retrieve `layout` object instructions for API details if you haven't already\n\n## Approach: Auto Layout First\n\n### Option A: Automatic Generation (Try First)\n\nThis is the quickest way to create a complete Layout. Auto-layout generates all required sheets (Assumptions and Calculations), traces all dependencies, and places everything correctly.\n\n1. **Identify root Variables** from the Model summary (select all root Variables for a full Model layout)\n2. **Run `create-auto-layout`:**\n   ```\n   ModelAction(action='create-auto-layout', parameters={\n     variableIds: [root Variable IDs]\n   })\n   ```\n   This automatically creates Assumptions and Calculations sheets with all dependencies included. Optional parameters: `calculationsSheetId` (to add to an existing sheet), `maxLevels`, `idealMinGroupsAtLevel`, `idealMaxGroupsAtLevel`.\n3. **Validate:** `ModelAction(action='validate-layout')`\n4. **Review and optionally refine** using `get-content` on each sheet:\n   - Flatten overly-nested structures for simple models\n   - Apply formatting to LineItems (auto-layout doesn't format)\n   - Verify FAST layout principles (dependencies visible above dependents)\n\n### Option B: Manual Layout\n\nUse when auto-layout isn't suitable (specific formatting, custom sheet structure, partial layout updates).\n\n1. **Trace dependencies** on all root Variables to see the full hierarchy\n2. **Plan sheet structure:**\n   - One Assumptions sheet (usually sufficient)\n   - One or more Calculations sheets (by business area for large models)\n   - Metrics sheets if needed\n   - Dashboard sheets for visualization\n3. **Create sheets, groups, and items** following the hierarchy\n4. **Validate immediately** after creation\n\n## FAST Layout Principles\n\n- **Repeat Variables freely** — include the same Variable on multiple sheets as needed. Each copy links back to the original. Dependencies should be visible directly above their dependents\n- **Top-to-bottom flow** — inputs at top, outputs at bottom within each sheet\n- **7-10 groups per level** — use nested LineGroups for readability\n- **One timeline per sheet** — don't mix Variables of different `periodType`\n\n## Validation\n\nAlways run `ModelAction(action='validate-layout')` after layout changes. Common issues:\n- Missing Variables (calculation dependencies not in any sheet)\n- Assumption Variables on wrong sheet type\n- Multiple entry cells for the same Assumption (when Dashboards are involved)\n","description":"Workflow for creating ModelSheets, LineGroups, and LineItems","title":"Build Model Layout","topics":["ModelSheet","LineGroup","LineItem","Layout","Excel"]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me use auto-layout since it's the recommended approach. First, I need to identify the root variables — Revenue is the main output, but let me check what the model considers roots.

[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="summary", explanation="Check root variables for layout", parameters={"format":"compact"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: # Model: Agent tests
**ID:** -PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4jxj
**Created:** 2026-01-28 10:37:55
**Last Modified:** 2026-03-26 14:54:35
**Tag Namespace:** Agent testing (ID: -PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4jzi)

## Model Configuration
- **Timings:** Mar 25 - Dec 27 (12 periods, Quarter)
- **Default Unit:** [no unit]
- **Unit Rigor Level:** Full Units (Level 3)

## Scenarios & Sensitivities
- **Scenarios:** Base (ID: Base)
- **Sensitivities:** Base (ID: Base)

## Summary
- **Total Variables:** 11
- **Total Assumptions:** 0


[ASSISTANT]: 

The summary doesn't show root variables in compact mode. Revenue is the main root — it depends on everything else. Let me use auto-layout with Revenue as the root, which should pull in all dependencies automatically.

[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="create-auto-layout", explanation="Auto-generate layout from Revenue", parameters={"variableIds":["-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Px"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"message":"Successfully created auto-layout for 1 Variable(s)","success":true,"variablesAdded":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me check what the auto-layout created and validate it.

[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="validate-layout", explanation="Validate auto-generated layout", parameters={})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Check sheets created by auto-layout", object_type="ModelSheet", parameters={"format":"markdown"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"layout_validation_report":{"items":["✓ **Layout is valid** - All dependencies are properly included in the layout."]}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: | Name | Id | Model Sheet Type | Has Warnings | Description | Is Control Sheet |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|
| Assumptions | -PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNp | Assumptions | No | All assumptions | No |
| Calculations | -PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNn | Calculations | No | All calculations | Yes |


[ASSISTANT]: 

Layout is valid and auto-layout created an Assumptions sheet and a Calculations sheet. The plan originally called for 2 Calculations sheets (Timing + Membership & Revenue), but the auto-layout has organized everything into a single Calculations sheet which is perfectly fine for a model of this size. Let me check the content of each sheet to make sure the structure looks good.

[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Get layout object instructions", parameters={"category":"layout"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"category":"layout","content":"# Working with Layout Objects\n\n## Overview\n\nThe Layout contains ModelSheets which define the Excel workbook structure. The Layout object always exists on a Model (cannot be created or deleted).\n\n## ModelSheet Types\n\n| Type | Contains | LineItem Links To |\n|---|---|---|\n| **Calculations** | Variable LineItems | Variables (ALL types, including Assumption-type) |\n| **Assumptions** | ModelAssumption LineItems | ModelAssumptions |\n| **Metrics** | Metric LineItems | Metrics |\n| **Dashboard** | Dashboard reference | N/A |\n| **XlInsert** | External Excel import | N/A (not yet enabled) |\n\n### CRITICAL: Assumption-type Variables go on Calculation sheets\nThis is the most common mistake. An Assumption-type Variable is still a Variable — it goes on a Calculations sheet. Only ModelAssumption objects go on Assumptions sheets. The Assumption-type Variable on the Calculations sheet links to the ModelAssumption on the Assumptions sheet.\n\n## Creating ModelSheets\n\nUse `get-help` for the full schema. Key properties:\n```json\n{\n  \"action\": \"create\",\n  \"object_type\": \"ModelSheet\",\n  \"parameters\": {\n    \"name\": \"Income Statement\",\n    \"modelSheetType\": \"Calculations\",\n    \"contentSections\": [{\n      \"lineGroups\": [...]\n    }]\n  }\n}\n```\n\n## LineGroups\n\nPurely organizational containers with headers. Can be nested.\n\nKey properties:\n- `name`: Group header text\n- `lineItems`: Array of LineItems directly under this group\n- `lineGroups`: Nested LineGroups\n\n**Note:** LineItems within a LineGroup appear after the header and BEFORE any nested LineGroups. Avoid mixing LineItems and nested LineGroups at the same level.\n\n## LineItems\n\nIndividual rows linked to a Variable, ModelAssumption, or Metric.\n\nKey properties:\n- `variableId` / `modelAssumptionId` / `metricId`: The linked object\n- Formatting properties (bold, italic, borders, etc.)\n\n**Dimensional expansion:** A single LineItem for a Dimensional Variable/Metric automatically expands into multiple rows — one per dimension combination. No need to create separate LineItems per dimension member.\n\n## Layout Constraints\n\n- **One timeline per sheet**: Variables with different `periodType` cannot share a sheet\n- **One entry cell per Assumption**: If an Assumption appears in a Dashboard's AssumptionsTable in the Layout, it can't have a separate entry cell on an Assumptions sheet\n- **Minimum for valid Excel**: At least 1 Assumptions sheet + 1 Calculations sheet\n- **Control sheet**: One sheet should have `isControlSheet: true` for the Scenario/Sensitivity dropdown\n\n## Repeated LineItems (FAST Practice)\n\nVariables can appear on multiple sheets. Each additional LineItem links back to the original. This is encouraged — dependencies should be visible directly above their dependents on each sheet.\n\n## Best Practices\n\n1. **Top-to-bottom flow**: Inputs at top, outputs at bottom within each sheet\n2. **7-10 groups per level**: Use nested LineGroups for readability\n3. **Single Assumptions sheet** usually sufficient\n4. **Multiple Calculation sheets** for large models — group by business area\n5. **Always validate** after layout changes: `ModelAction(action='validate-layout')`\n","description":"Object reference: ModelSheet, LineGroup, LineItem properties and constraints","title":"Working with Layout Objects","topics":["ModelSheet","LineGroup","LineItem","Layout","formatting"]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

The auto-layout has already created a valid layout, so let me check what it looks like and refine if needed.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Check Calculations sheet content", object_type="ModelSheet", otherAction="get-content", parameters={"format":"markdown","id":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNn"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Check Assumptions sheet content", object_type="ModelSheet", otherAction="get-content", parameters={"format":"markdown","id":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNp"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: 
1. Members

   1.1. Net new members
      Target new members
      Launch date
      Is live
      --------------------
      New members

      Churn rate
      --------------------
      Members churned

      New members
      Members churned
      --------------------
      **Net new members**
      ====================

   1.2. Members
      Net new members
      --------------------
      **Members**
      ====================

2. Revenue
   Monthly price
   --------------------
   Quarterly price

   Members
   Quarterly price
   --------------------
   **Revenue**
   ====================
[TOOL_RESULT]: [Empty - no content]
[ASSISTANT]: 

The auto-layout created a good Calculations sheet structure, but the Assumptions sheet is empty. I need to populate it with the ModelAssumptions. Let me first check what ModelAssumptions exist (they should have been auto-created with the Assumption Variables).

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Find all ModelAssumptions", object_type="ModelAssumption", parameters={"format":"markdown"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: | Prefix | Id | Unit | Number Format | Data Type | Date | Default Value | Is Used | Is In Layout |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|


[ASSISTANT]: 

Interesting — no ModelAssumptions exist yet. The Assumption Variables were created with auto-generated TimeSegments, but since no values were provided, the ModelAssumptions are empty placeholders. Let me check the Assumption Variables' TimeSegments more closely to understand the state.

Actually, looking back at the creation results, the Variables showed "36 assumptions" and "1 assumption" etc. — so ModelAssumptions should exist. Let me check with a broader filter.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Check assumptions with help first", object_type="ModelAssumption", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"filter","description":"Filter ModelAssumption objects based on their properties","object_type":"ModelAssumption","operators":{"$and":{"description":"Matches objects where all conditions are true (explicit AND for nesting)","syntax":{"$and":[{"property1":"value1"},{"property2":"value2"}]}},"$not":{"description":"Inverts a condition","syntax":{"$not":{"property":"value"}}},"$or":{"description":"Matches objects where at least one condition is true","syntax":{"$or":[{"property1":"value1"},{"property2":"value2"}]}},"note":"Top-level properties are implicitly ANDed. Operators can be nested for complex queries."},"pagination":{"limit":{"default":"Set by session (typically 50)","description":"Maximum number of results to return. A truncation warning is included when results exceed this limit.","type":"integer"},"skip":{"default":0,"description":"Number of results to skip (for pagination).","type":"integer"}},"parameters":{"dataType":{"type":"enum","values":["Double","Integer","String","DateTime","Date","Boolean","Validation","List","NotApplicable"]},"dateTimeDescription":{"type":"string"},"dateTimeLongDateString":{"type":"string"},"id":{"type":"string"},"isInLayout":{"type":"boolean"},"isUsed":{"type":"boolean"},"notes":{"type":"string"},"numberFormatText":{"type":"string"},"prefix":{"type":"string"},"searchText":{"type":"string"},"sensitivityType":{"type":"enum","values":["PercentageChange","Delta","Absolute"]},"timeTypeDescription":{"type":"string"},"unitDescription":{"type":"string"}},"pattern_guide":{"boolean":["true/false"],"enum":["exact (case-insensitive)"],"string":["exact","glob (*?)","regex (/pattern/)"]}}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me try filtering with a broader approach to find the ModelAssumptions.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Find all assumptions with wildcard", object_type="ModelAssumption", parameters={"format":"markdown","prefix":"*"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: | Prefix | Id | Unit | Number Format | Data Type | Date | Default Value | Is Used | Is In Layout |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|


[ASSISTANT]: 

It seems no ModelAssumptions were created yet. This is because the Assumption Variables were created without inline assumption values — the TimeSegments reference assumptions but the ModelAssumption objects themselves need to be populated. Let me check the Variable TimeSegments to understand the current state better.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Check Launch date TimeSegments", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","properties":["timeSegments"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"error":"Required parameter 'id' is missing"}
[ASSISTANT]: Let me try the get-details call with a different format.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Check Launch date details", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","properties":["timeSegments"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"error":"Required parameter 'id' is missing"}
[ASSISTANT]: Let me try the get-details call differently — it seems the ID format might need adjustment.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Get Launch date details", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"error":"Required parameter 'id' is missing"}
[ASSISTANT]: Let me try the get-details with help to check the correct parameter format.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Get help for get-details", object_type="Variable", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"get-details","description":"Get detailed property values for a single Variable","note":"Returns all properties. Expandable objects show '{preview...}' format - include the property name in 'properties' array to expand. Use dot notation for nested expansion (e.g., 'defaultCalculation.calculationParts').","objectType":"Variable","parameters":{"id":{"description":"ID of the Variable to get details for","required":true,"type":"string"},"properties":{"description":"Property names to expand. Supports dot notation for nested expansion (e.g., 'defaultCalculation.calculationParts'). When specified, complex objects and collections are fully expanded.","required":false,"type":"string[]"}},"properties":{"aggregatedVariableIds":{"type":"string[]"},"applyFactoring":{"type":"boolean"},"columnSummaries":{"type":"ColumnSummary[]"},"contextVarianceMap":{"type":"ContextVarianceMap"},"dataType":{"type":"enum","values":["Double","Integer","String","DateTime","Date","Boolean","Validation","List","NotApplicable"]},"defaultAssumptionId":{"type":"string"},"defaultCalculation":{"type":"Calculation"},"defaultFormulaType":{"type":"enum","values":["Assumptions","Calculation","Aggregation"]},"groupSummaryRearrangedParentId":{"type":"string"},"groupSummaryType":{"type":"Nullable`1","values":["None","Sum","Auto","Rearranged"]},"hasError":{"type":"boolean"},"hasSummary":{"type":"boolean"},"id":{"type":"string"},"isConstant":{"type":"boolean"},"isInLayout":{"type":"boolean"},"name":{"type":"string"},"numberFormatId":{"type":"string"},"overrideUnitError":{"type":"boolean"},"periodType":{"description":"PeriodType used for time aggregation","type":"enum","values":["None","Day","Week","Month","Quarter","YearCalendar","YearFiscal"]},"tagGroupCount":{"description":"Expanded Dimension count","type":"integer"},"tagParents":{"type":"TagParents"},"timeSegments":{"type":"TimeSegment[]"},"timeSegmentsWarning":{"type":"string"},"timeTypeDescription":{"type":"string"},"unit":{"type":"Unit"},"unitDescription":{"type":"string"},"unitOption":{"type":"enum","values":["Defined","Inferred"]},"validationDimensionId":{"type":"string"}}}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me try the get-details call again — it seems the ID with special characters might need careful handling.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Get Launch date variable details", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","properties":["timeSegments"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"error":"Required parameter 'id' is missing"}
[ASSISTANT]: 

It seems get-details is having trouble with the ID. Let me try a different approach — I'll check the ModelAssumptions by looking at the Variable's time segments through the filter, and populate the Assumptions sheet directly.

Since the auto-layout created the Assumptions sheet empty, I need to add the ModelAssumptions to it. But first, let me confirm ModelAssumptions actually exist by checking with a limit.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="List all assumptions no filter", object_type="ModelAssumption", parameters={"limit":100})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"data":{"count":0,"modelAssumptions":[]},"warnings":["Unknown filter parameter 'items' ignored"]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

There are genuinely 0 ModelAssumptions — the Assumption Variables were created with TimeSegments that reference assumptions, but since no values were provided inline, the ModelAssumption objects weren't actually created. I need to populate the assumption values. Let me check the assumptions instructions to understand the best approach.

[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Get assumptions instructions", parameters={"category":"assumptions"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"category":"assumptions","content":"# Working with ModelAssumptions\r\n\r\n## Overview\r\n\r\nModelAssumptions are user-input containers that provide values to Variables. They store scalar values that can vary by Scenario and Sensitivity. When a Variable has `defaultFormulaType: Assumptions`, it pulls its values from a ModelAssumption.\r\n\r\n## Key Concepts\r\n\r\n**ModelAssumption**: A container for user-input values with the following key properties:\r\n- **prefix**: The base name before dimensional/time context is added\r\n- **values**: A map of values keyed by Scenario ID\r\n- **sensitivities**: A map of sensitivity overrides keyed by Sensitivity ID\r\n- **sensitivityType**: The type of sensitivity calculation (PercentageChange, Delta, Absolute)\r\n- **unit**: The unit definition including any dimensional modifiers\r\n\r\n**Relationship to Variables**: Variables with `defaultFormulaType: Assumptions` reference a ModelAssumption via `defaultAssumptionId`. The Variable gets its calculated values from the assumption.\r\n\r\n## Values Map\r\n\r\nThe `values` property is a `Dictionary\u003cstring, ModelAssumptionValue\u003e` where:\r\n- **Keys**: Scenario IDs (e.g., `\"-Pt6e56nOUBefHIEvLbi\"`)\r\n- **Values**: ModelAssumptionValue objects\r\n\r\n### ModelAssumptionValue Structure\r\n\r\nEach value entry specifies:\r\n- **modelAssumptionValueType**: Currently only `LocalInput` is supported\r\n- **localInputValue**: The actual value as a string (parsed based on dataType)\r\n\r\n### Example\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"values\": {\r\n    \"-scenarioId1\": {\r\n      \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n      \"localInputValue\": \"29.99\"\r\n    },\r\n    \"-scenarioId2\": {\r\n      \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n      \"localInputValue\": \"34.99\"\r\n    }\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n**Important**: If a Scenario is \"based on\" another Scenario and has no explicit value, it inherits from its base Scenario.\r\n\r\n## Sensitivities Map\r\n\r\nThe `sensitivities` property is a `Dictionary\u003cstring, SensitivityValue\u003e` where:\r\n- **Keys**: Sensitivity IDs (e.g., `\"-Pt6e56nOUBefHIEvLbj\"`)\r\n- **Values**: SensitivityValue objects\r\n\r\n### SensitivityValue Structure\r\n\r\nEach sensitivity entry specifies:\r\n- **sensitivityValueType**: Must match the parent assumption's `sensitivityType`\r\n- One of: `percentage`, `delta`, or `absolute` (depending on type)\r\n\r\n### sensitivityType Matching\r\n\r\n**Critical**: The `sensitivityType` on ModelAssumption determines the type for ALL sensitivity values. Individual `SensitivityValue.sensitivityValueType` values must match.\r\n\r\n| sensitivityType | Required Field | Meaning |\r\n|-----------------|---------------|---------|\r\n| PercentageChange | percentage | Multiply base value by (1 + percentage/100) |\r\n| Delta | delta | Add delta to base value |\r\n| Absolute | absolute | Replace base value entirely |\r\n\r\n### Example\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"sensitivityType\": \"PercentageChange\",\r\n  \"sensitivities\": {\r\n    \"-sensitivityId1\": {\r\n      \"sensitivityValueType\": \"PercentageChange\",\r\n      \"percentage\": \"10\"\r\n    },\r\n    \"-sensitivityId2\": {\r\n      \"sensitivityValueType\": \"PercentageChange\",\r\n      \"percentage\": \"-5\"\r\n    }\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n## Dimensional Assumptions\r\n\r\nAssumptions can represent values across Dimensions (e.g., by Region, by Product). Unlike Variables which expand across Dimensions via `tagParents`, dimensional assumptions require **separate ModelAssumption objects** for each dimension combination.\r\n\r\n### How Dimensions Work\r\n\r\n1. **One Assumption per dimension combination**: For \"Price\" varying by Region (North, South) and Tier (Basic, Premium), you create 4 assumptions\r\n2. **Same prefix, different modifiers**: All share the same `prefix` but have different Unit modifiers\r\n3. **Modifiers on UnitParts**: Dimensional context is stored as `modifiers` on UnitPart objects\r\n\r\n### Example: New Members per Month by Region and Tier\r\n\r\nFor a model with:\r\n- Region Dimension: North, South\r\n- Tier Dimension: Basic, Premium\r\n\r\nYou would create 4 ModelAssumptions, all with `prefix: \"New members per month\"`:\r\n\r\n| Assumption | Value | Unit Modifiers |\r\n|------------|-------|----------------|\r\n| Assumption 1 | 30 | North, Basic |\r\n| Assumption 2 | 10 | North, Premium |\r\n| Assumption 3 | 5 | South, Basic |\r\n| Assumption 4 | 18 | South, Premium |\r\n\r\n### Unit Modifiers Structure\r\n\r\nEach UnitPart can have modifiers that specify dimensional context:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"unit\": {\r\n    \"unitParts\": [\r\n      {\r\n        \"tagId\": \"-memberTagId\",\r\n        \"modifiers\": [\r\n          {\r\n            \"tagId\": \"-northTagId\"\r\n          },\r\n          {\r\n            \"tagId\": \"-basicTagId\"\r\n          }\r\n        ]\r\n      }\r\n    ]\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\nThe `modifiers` array contains references to Concrete Tags that define the dimensional position of this assumption.\r\n\r\n## Time Series Assumptions\r\n\r\nAssumptions can represent values at specific points in time or over specific periods. This is achieved by adding a `dateTimeElement` to a UnitPart.\r\n\r\n### DateTimeElement Types\r\n\r\n| Element Type | Description | Use Case |\r\n|--------------|-------------|----------|\r\n| **Flow** | Period with duration | Flow values (e.g., \"Revenue for Q1 2024\") |\r\n| **Balance** | Point-in-time snapshot | Stock values (e.g., \"Headcount at Dec 2024\") |\r\n| **Timeless** | Period without temporal semantics | Unitless time-varying values (e.g., \"Growth Rate for 2024\") |\r\n\r\n**Important**: All non-constant Assumptions require a `dateTimeElement` matching the UnitPart's TimeType. Constant Assumptions (where the Variable has `isConstant: true`) have no `dateTimeElement` — a single value covers all periods.\r\n\r\n### DateTimeSeriesDate Formats\r\n\r\nThe `dateString` format depends on the `dateType`:\r\n\r\n| dateType | Format | Example |\r\n|----------|--------|---------|\r\n| Day | `yyyyMMdd` | `\"20240115\"` (January 15, 2024) |\r\n| Week | `yyyyMMdd` | `\"20240121\"` (end of week, e.g., Sunday) |\r\n| Month | `yyyyMM` | `\"202401\"` (January 2024) |\r\n| Quarter | `yyyyQ[1-4]` | `\"2024Q1\"` (Q1 2024) |\r\n| Year | `yyyy` | `\"2024\"` |\r\n\r\n**Note**: Quarter and Year formats use calendar year conventions (Q1 = Jan-Mar, year ends December 31). The system will interpret these correctly based on the model's fiscal year settings.\r\n\r\n### Month-Specific Options\r\n\r\nWhen `dateType` is `Month`, you can specify when in the month:\r\n\r\n| monthDateType | Description |\r\n|---------------|-------------|\r\n| EndOfMonth | End of the specified month (default) |\r\n| DayInMonth | Specific day, requires `dayOfMonth` (1-28) |\r\n\r\n### DateTimeElement Structure\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"dateTimeElement\": {\r\n    \"elementType\": \"Flow\",\r\n    \"dateType\": \"Quarter\",\r\n    \"dateString\": \"2024Q1\",\r\n    \"duration\": 1\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\nFor Balance (snapshot) elements, omit `duration`:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"dateTimeElement\": {\r\n    \"elementType\": \"Balance\",\r\n    \"dateType\": \"Month\",\r\n    \"dateString\": \"202412\",\r\n    \"monthDateType\": \"EndOfMonth\"\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Pattern: Time Series Assumption\r\n\r\nA quarterly revenue assumption for Q1 2024:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"action\": \"create\",\r\n  \"object_type\": \"ModelAssumption\",\r\n  \"parameters\": {\r\n    \"prefix\": \"Revenue\",\r\n    \"dataType\": \"Double\",\r\n    \"values\": {\r\n      \"-baseScenarioId\": {\r\n        \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n        \"localInputValue\": \"1000000\"\r\n      }\r\n    },\r\n    \"unit\": {\r\n      \"unitParts\": [\r\n        {\r\n          \"tagId\": \"-revenueTagId\",\r\n          \"timeType\": \"Flow\",\r\n          \"dateTimeElement\": {\r\n            \"elementType\": \"Flow\",\r\n            \"dateType\": \"Quarter\",\r\n            \"dateString\": \"2024Q1\",\r\n            \"duration\": 1\r\n          }\r\n        }\r\n      ]\r\n    }\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Pattern: Balance Snapshot Assumption\r\n\r\nA monthly balance (e.g., headcount at end of month):\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"action\": \"create\",\r\n  \"object_type\": \"ModelAssumption\",\r\n  \"parameters\": {\r\n    \"prefix\": \"Headcount\",\r\n    \"dataType\": \"Integer\",\r\n    \"values\": {\r\n      \"-baseScenarioId\": {\r\n        \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n        \"localInputValue\": \"150\"\r\n      }\r\n    },\r\n    \"unit\": {\r\n      \"unitParts\": [\r\n        {\r\n          \"tagId\": \"-headcountTagId\",\r\n          \"timeType\": \"Balance\",\r\n          \"dateTimeElement\": {\r\n            \"elementType\": \"Balance\",\r\n            \"dateType\": \"Month\",\r\n            \"dateString\": \"202412\"\r\n          }\r\n        }\r\n      ]\r\n    }\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Pattern: Unitless Time Series\r\n\r\nFor a unitless value at a specific time (no tag, just time context):\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"action\": \"create\",\r\n  \"object_type\": \"ModelAssumption\",\r\n  \"parameters\": {\r\n    \"prefix\": \"Growth Rate\",\r\n    \"dataType\": \"Double\",\r\n    \"values\": {\r\n      \"-baseScenarioId\": {\r\n        \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n        \"localInputValue\": \"0.05\"\r\n      }\r\n    },\r\n    \"unit\": {\r\n      \"unitParts\": [\r\n        {\r\n          \"tagId\": null,\r\n          \"timeType\": \"Timeless\",\r\n          \"dateTimeElement\": {\r\n            \"elementType\": \"Timeless\",\r\n            \"dateType\": \"Year\",\r\n            \"dateString\": \"2024\"\r\n          }\r\n        }\r\n      ]\r\n    }\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Time Series Pitfalls\r\n\r\n**Pitfall 1: Missing duration for Flow**\r\n\r\nFlow elements require a `duration` (minimum 1). Balance elements should not have duration.\r\n\r\n**Pitfall 2: Mismatched timeType and elementType**\r\n\r\nThe `timeType` on UnitPart should match the `elementType` in dateTimeElement:\r\n- `timeType: \"Flow\"` → `elementType: \"Flow\"`\r\n- `timeType: \"Balance\"` → `elementType: \"Balance\"`\r\n- `timeType: \"Timeless\"` → `elementType: \"Timeless\"`\r\n\r\n**Pitfall 3: Wrong date format**\r\n\r\nEach dateType has a specific format. Using `\"2024-01\"` instead of `\"202401\"` for Month will fail validation.\r\n\r\n## Common Patterns\r\n\r\n### Pattern 1: Simple Scalar Assumption\r\n\r\nA single value that doesn't vary by Scenario:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"action\": \"create\",\r\n  \"object_type\": \"ModelAssumption\",\r\n  \"parameters\": {\r\n    \"prefix\": \"Tax Rate\",\r\n    \"dataType\": \"Double\",\r\n    \"values\": {\r\n      \"-baseScenarioId\": {\r\n        \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n        \"localInputValue\": \"0.25\"\r\n      }\r\n    }\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Pattern 2: Multi-Scenario Assumption\r\n\r\nValues that differ by Scenario:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"action\": \"create\",\r\n  \"object_type\": \"ModelAssumption\",\r\n  \"parameters\": {\r\n    \"prefix\": \"Revenue Growth Rate\",\r\n    \"dataType\": \"Double\",\r\n    \"values\": {\r\n      \"-baseScenarioId\": {\r\n        \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n        \"localInputValue\": \"0.05\"\r\n      },\r\n      \"-optimisticScenarioId\": {\r\n        \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n        \"localInputValue\": \"0.08\"\r\n      },\r\n      \"-pessimisticScenarioId\": {\r\n        \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n        \"localInputValue\": \"0.02\"\r\n      }\r\n    }\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n### Pattern 3: Assumption with Sensitivities\r\n\r\nAdd sensitivity analysis capability:\r\n\r\n```json\r\n{\r\n  \"action\": \"create\",\r\n  \"object_type\": \"ModelAssumption\",\r\n  \"parameters\": {\r\n    \"prefix\": \"Discount Rate\",\r\n    \"dataType\": \"Double\",\r\n    \"sensitivityType\": \"Delta\",\r\n    \"values\": {\r\n      \"-baseScenarioId\": {\r\n        \"modelAssumptionValueType\": \"LocalInput\",\r\n        \"localInputValue\": \"0.08\"\r\n      }\r\n    },\r\n    \"sensitivities\": {\r\n      \"-highSensitivityId\": {\r\n        \"sensitivityValueType\": \"Delta\",\r\n        \"delta\": \"0.02\"\r\n      },\r\n      \"-lowSensitivityId\": {\r\n        \"sensitivityValueType\": \"Delta\",\r\n        \"delta\": \"-0.02\"\r\n      }\r\n    }\r\n  }\r\n}\r\n```\r\n\r\n## Common Pitfalls\r\n\r\n### Pitfall 1: Confusing Values Keys with Sensitivities Keys\r\n\r\n**Mistake**: Using the wrong ID type as map keys.\r\n\r\n**Reality**:\r\n- `values` keys are **Scenario IDs**\r\n- `sensitivities` keys are **Sensitivity IDs**\r\n\r\nThese are different object types with different IDs.\r\n\r\n### Pitfall 2: Mismatching sensitivityType\r\n\r\n**Mistake**: Setting `sensitivityType: PercentageChange` but providing `delta` values in sensitivities.\r\n\r\n**Reality**: The `sensitivityValueType` on each SensitivityValue must match the parent assumption's `sensitivityType`.\r\n\r\n### Pitfall 3: Expecting Dimensional Expansion\r\n\r\n**Mistake**: Thinking one assumption can cover multiple dimension combinations.\r\n\r\n**Reality**: Each dimension combination requires its own ModelAssumption. Use Unit modifiers to differentiate them.\r\n\r\n### Pitfall 4: Numeric Values as Numbers\r\n\r\n**Mistake**: Providing numeric values as JSON numbers (`\"localInputValue\": 29.99`).\r\n\r\n**Reality**: All values are stored as strings. Always use string format (`\"localInputValue\": \"29.99\"`).\r\n\r\n## Best Practices\r\n\r\n1. **Use descriptive prefixes** that clearly identify what the assumption represents\r\n2. **Provide values for the Base Scenario** at minimum - other scenarios can inherit\r\n3. **Match sensitivityType with your analysis needs**:\r\n   - Use `PercentageChange` for multiplicative sensitivity (e.g., revenue changes)\r\n   - Use `Delta` for additive sensitivity (e.g., rate adjustments)\r\n   - Use `Absolute` for replacement values\r\n4. **Create dimensional assumptions systematically** - ensure all combinations are covered\r\n5. **Query existing Scenarios and Sensitivities** before creating assumptions to get valid IDs\r\n","description":"Object reference: ModelAssumption properties, values maps, sensitivities, dimensional assumptions, unit modifiers","title":"Working with ModelAssumptions","topics":["ModelAssumption","Scenarios","Sensitivities","Dimensions","UnitModifiers","values"]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

I see — the ModelAssumptions weren't created because I didn't provide inline values. The best approach is to use the inline `assumptions` grid on the Variable TimeSegments. But actually, looking at the Variable creation results more carefully, they showed "36 assumptions" and "1 assumption" — so the system did create placeholder ModelAssumptions. Let me re-check by looking at the assumption count differently. Actually, the filter returned 0, so they genuinely don't exist yet.

The cleanest approach is to update the Assumption Variables with inline assumption grids on their TimeSegments. But first, let me use `expand-dimensions` to understand the grid shapes needed.

Actually, since we don't have real values to populate yet (the user hasn't given us specific numbers), the most important thing is to ensure the structure is correct and the layout is properly built. The ModelAssumptions will be created when the user enters values. Let me check if the layout is actually valid as-is for Excel generation, and focus on making the Assumptions sheet work.

Let me take a step back — the auto-layout already created a valid layout with the Calculations sheet populated. The Assumptions sheet is empty because there are no ModelAssumptions yet. This is fine structurally. Let me update the tasks to reflect what's actually been done, then run the health check.

[TOOL]: complete_task(explanation="Layout created via auto-layout", task_id="task-3")
[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="get-model-health", explanation="Run health check on completed model", parameters={})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"success":true,"task_id":"task-3"}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"errors":[{"category":"timeSegmentFormula","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","message":"No invalid assumptions","name":"Launch date","timeSegmentIndex":0},{"category":"timeSegmentFormula","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","message":"No invalid assumptions","name":"Target new members","timeSegmentIndex":0},{"category":"timeSegmentFormula","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","message":"No invalid assumptions","name":"Churn rate","timeSegmentIndex":0},{"category":"timeSegmentFormula","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","message":"No invalid assumptions","name":"Monthly price","timeSegmentIndex":0}],"warnings":[]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

The health check shows 4 errors — all Assumption Variables have "No invalid assumptions" which means their TimeSegments reference assumptions that don't exist yet. I need to populate the Assumption Variables with placeholder values so the model calculates correctly.

Let me use the inline assumption grid approach. First, let me discover the grid shapes needed.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Get grid shape for Target new members", object_type="Variable", otherAction="expand-dimensions", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","timeSegmentIndex":0})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"columns":["Mar 25","Jun 25","Sept 25","Dec 25","Mar 26","Jun 26","Sept 26","Dec 26","Mar 27","Jun 27","Sept 27","Dec 27"],"rows":["Basic","Premium","Platinum"],"shape":[3,12]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Good — 3 rows (Basic, Premium, Platinum) × 12 columns (quarters). Now let me populate all 4 Assumption Variables with sensible placeholder values. I'll use the inline assumption grid on TimeSegment updates.

Let me set reasonable defaults:
- **Launch date**: Q3 2025 (Sept 2025)
- **Target new members**: Basic 50/qtr, Premium 30/qtr, Platinum 10/qtr
- **Churn rate**: Basic 8%, Premium 5%, Platinum 3% per quarter
- **Monthly price**: Basic £29.99, Premium £49.99, Platinum £79.99

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="update", explanation="Set Launch date assumption value", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","timeSegments":[{"assumptions":{"values":[["2025-09-30"]]},"start":{"segmentPeriodType":"Auto"}}]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Updated 1 of 1 Variable(s)","results":[{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"value":"30 Sep 25"},"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","isConstant":"True","name":"Launch date","numberFormat":"dd mmm yy","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 1 assumption","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Launch date is set to 30 Sep 25. Now let me set the remaining 3 Assumption Variables with placeholder values.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="update", explanation="Set Target new members assumptions", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","timeSegments":[{"assumptions":{"values":[["50","50","50","50","50","50","50","50","50","50","50","50"],["30","30","30","30","30","30","30","30","30","30","30","30"],["10","10","10","10","10","10","10","10","10","10","10","10"]]},"start":{"segmentPeriodType":"Auto"}}]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="update", explanation="Set Churn rate assumptions", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","timeSegments":[{"assumptions":{"values":[["0.08","0.08","0.08","0.08","0.08","0.08","0.08","0.08","0.08","0.08","0.08","0.08"],["0.05","0.05","0.05","0.05","0.05","0.05","0.05","0.05","0.05","0.05","0.05","0.05"],["0.03","0.03","0.03","0.03","0.03","0.03","0.03","0.03","0.03","0.03","0.03","0.03"]]},"start":{"segmentPeriodType":"Auto"}}]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="update", explanation="Set Monthly price assumptions", object_type="Variable", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","timeSegments":[{"assumptions":{"values":[["29.99"],["49.99"],["79.99"]]},"start":{"segmentPeriodType":"Auto"}}]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Updated 1 of 1 Variable(s)","results":[{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"growthRate":"0.0% per period","sample":{"Dec 27":"90","Mar 25":"90","Sept 26":"90"},"trend":"stable"},"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","isConstant":"False","name":"Target new members","numberFormat":"#,##0","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 36 assumptions","unit":"Member [Flow]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Updated 1 of 1 Variable(s)","results":[{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"dimensions":{"Basic":"8.0%","Platinum":"3.0%","Premium":"5.0%"},"growthRate":"0.0% per period","note":"Variable has no summary line","sample":{"Dec 27":"8.0%","Mar 25":"8.0%","Sept 26":"8.0%"},"trend":"stable"},"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","isConstant":"False","name":"Churn rate","numberFormat":"0.0%","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 36 assumptions","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Updated 1 of 1 Variable(s)","results":[{"data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"dimensions":{"Basic":"£29.99","Platinum":"£79.99","Premium":"£49.99"},"note":"Variable has no summary line"},"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","isConstant":"True","name":"Monthly price","numberFormat":"\"£\"#,##0.00","timeSegments":"`Mar 25 - Dec 27`: 3 assumptions","unit":"GBP [Flow]/Member [Balance]"}},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

All assumptions are populated with placeholder values. The calculated values are flowing through — I can see Target new members showing 90 (sum of 50+30+10), Churn rate at 8%/5%/3% per package, and Monthly price at £29.99/£49.99/£79.99. Now let me run the health check and verify the model is calculating correctly.

[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="get-model-health", explanation="Final health check", parameters={})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"errors":[{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Constant","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56we","message":"Assumption for 'Launch date' not in layout","name":"Launch date","unit":"Unitless","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI","variableName":"Launch date"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574X","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574b","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574g","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574l","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574q","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574v","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575-","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5754","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5759","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575E","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575K","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575P","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575V","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575_","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575e","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575j","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575o","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575t","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575y","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5762","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5767","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576C","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576I","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576N","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576S","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576Y","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576c","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576h","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576m","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576r","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576w","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5770","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5775","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577A","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577F","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577L","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MN","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MV","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mb","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mi","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mp","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mw","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N2","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N9","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NH","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NO","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NW","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nc","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nj","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nq","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nx","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57O3","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OA","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OI","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OP","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OX","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Od","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ok","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Or","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Oy","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57P4","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PB","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PJ","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PQ","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PY","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pe","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pl","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ps","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pz","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Q5","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QC","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QK","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Constant","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jc","message":"Assumption for 'Monthly price' not in layout","name":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","variableName":"Monthly price"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Constant","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jj","message":"Assumption for 'Monthly price' not in layout","name":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","variableName":"Monthly price"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Constant","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jq","message":"Assumption for 'Monthly price' not in layout","name":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","variableName":"Monthly price"}],"warnings":[]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

The health check shows all the errors are "Assumption not in layout" — the ModelAssumptions exist now but they need to be added to the Assumptions sheet. Let me populate the Assumptions sheet with the ModelAssumptions. First, let me find all the ModelAssumptions and then add them to the sheet.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="List all ModelAssumptions", object_type="ModelAssumption", parameters={"format":"markdown","limit":100})
[TOOL_RESULT]: | Prefix | Id | Unit | Number Format | Data Type | Date | Default Value | Is Used | Is In Layout |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|
| Launch date | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56we | Unitless [Timeless] | dd mmm yy | Date | Constant | Local Input: 2025-09-30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574X | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Mar 25 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574b | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Jun 25 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574g | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Sept 25 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574l | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Dec 25 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574q | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Mar 26 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574v | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Jun 26 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575- | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Sept 26 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5754 | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Dec 26 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5759 | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Mar 27 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575E | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Jun 27 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575K | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Sept 27 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575P | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Dec 27 | Local Input: 50 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575V | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Mar 25 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575_ | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Jun 25 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575e | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Sept 25 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575j | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Dec 25 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575o | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Mar 26 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575t | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Jun 26 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575y | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Sept 26 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5762 | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Dec 26 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5767 | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Mar 27 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576C | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Jun 27 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576I | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Sept 27 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576N | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Dec 27 | Local Input: 30 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576S | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Mar 25 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576Y | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Jun 25 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576c | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Sept 25 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576h | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Dec 25 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576m | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Mar 26 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576r | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Jun 26 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576w | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Sept 26 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5770 | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Dec 26 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5775 | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Mar 27 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577A | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Jun 27 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577F | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Sept 27 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Target new members | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577L | Member [Flow] | #,##0 | Double | Dec 27 | Local Input: 10 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MN | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Mar 25 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MV | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Jun 25 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mb | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Sept 25 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mi | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Dec 25 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mp | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Mar 26 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mw | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Jun 26 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N2 | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Sept 26 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N9 | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Dec 26 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NH | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Mar 27 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NO | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Jun 27 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NW | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Sept 27 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nc | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Dec 27 | Local Input: 0.08 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nj | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Mar 25 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nq | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Jun 25 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nx | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Sept 25 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57O3 | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Dec 25 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OA | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Mar 26 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OI | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Jun 26 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OP | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Sept 26 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OX | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Dec 26 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Od | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Mar 27 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ok | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Jun 27 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Or | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Sept 27 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Oy | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Dec 27 | Local Input: 0.05 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57P4 | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Mar 25 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PB | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Jun 25 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PJ | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Sept 25 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PQ | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Dec 25 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PY | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Mar 26 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pe | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Jun 26 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pl | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Sept 26 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ps | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Dec 26 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pz | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Mar 27 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Q5 | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Jun 27 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QC | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Sept 27 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Churn rate | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QK | Member [Flow]/Member [Balance] | 0.0% | Double | Dec 27 | Local Input: 0.03 | Yes | No |
| Monthly price | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jc | GBP [Constant]/Member [Constant] | "£"#,##0.00 | Double | Constant | Local Input: 29.99 | Yes | No |
| Monthly price | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jj | GBP [Constant]/Member [Constant] | "£"#,##0.00 | Double | Constant | Local Input: 49.99 | Yes | No |
| Monthly price | -PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jq | GBP [Constant]/Member [Constant] | "£"#,##0.00 | Double | Constant | Local Input: 79.99 | Yes | No |


[ASSISTANT]: 

Good — all 76 ModelAssumptions now exist with values. They all show "Is In Layout: No", which explains the health check errors. I need to add them to the Assumptions sheet. Let me use the auto-layout again to rebuild the layout now that the assumptions exist, or manually add the assumptions to the sheet.

Let me try re-running the auto-layout which should now pick up the ModelAssumptions.

[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="create-auto-layout", explanation="Rebuild layout with assumptions", parameters={"variableIds":["-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Px"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"message":"Successfully created auto-layout for 1 Variable(s)","success":true,"variablesAdded":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me check if the Assumptions sheet is now populated and run the health check.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Check Assumptions sheet content", object_type="ModelSheet", otherAction="get-content", parameters={"format":"markdown","id":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNp"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Check Calculations sheet content", object_type="ModelSheet", otherAction="get-content", parameters={"format":"markdown","id":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNn"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: 
1. Members

   1.1. General
      Launch date

   1.2. Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members
      Target new members

   1.3. Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate
      Churn rate

2. Quarterly price
   Monthly price
   Monthly price
   Monthly price
[TOOL_RESULT]: 
1. Members

   1.1. Net new members
      Target new members
      Launch date
      Is live
      --------------------
      New members

      Churn rate
      --------------------
      Members churned

      New members
      Members churned
      --------------------
      **Net new members**
      ====================

   1.2. Members
      Net new members
      --------------------
      **Members**
      ====================

2. Revenue
   Monthly price
   --------------------
   Quarterly price

   Members
   Quarterly price
   --------------------
   **Revenue**
   ====================

3. Revenue
   Members
   Quarterly price
   --------------------
   **Revenue**
[ASSISTANT]: 

I can see two issues with the auto-layout:
1. The **Assumptions sheet** has individual ModelAssumption line items for every period/dimension combo (76 items!) — this is messy. The Assumptions sheet should have one line per Variable's assumptions, not one per period.
2. The **Calculations sheet** has a duplicate Revenue section at the bottom.

Let me rebuild the layout manually for a cleaner result. I'll delete the existing sheet contents and recreate them properly.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get ModelSheet create schema", object_type="ModelSheet", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new ModelSheet. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","notes":["Updates support partial payloads - only include properties you want to change"],"object_type":"ModelSheet","parameters":{"content":{"description":"Sheet content structure with lineGroups and lineItems","properties":{"lineGroups":{"description":"Top-level line groups for the sheet. For full schema, query help with object_type='LineGroup'","type":"array[LineGroup]"}},"type":"object"},"dashboardId":{"description":"ID of the dashboard to display on this sheet","required_when":{"modelSheetType":"Dashboard"},"type":"string"},"description":{"relevant_when":{"modelSheetType":["Dashboard","Calculations","Assumptions","Metrics"]},"type":"string"},"groupLevel":{"description":"Excel grouping level for the sheet tab (0-7)","relevant_when":{"modelSheetType":["Calculations","Assumptions","Metrics"]},"type":"integer"},"isControlSheet":{"description":"Whether this sheet should be the control sheet for navigation","type":"boolean"},"isHidden":{"description":"Whether the sheet should be hidden in Excel","type":"boolean"},"modelSheetType":{"editable":false,"required":true,"type":"enum","values":["Calculations","Assumptions","Metrics","Dashboard","XlInsert"]},"name":{"not_editable_when":{"modelSheetType":["Cases","Dimensions"]},"required":true,"type":"string"},"periodType":{"description":"Period type for calculations (None, Monthly, Quarterly, Annual, etc.) - must be None (default), or a longer time period than the Model base time period. Used for aggregration of calculations over longer time periods.","editable":false,"relevant_when":{"modelSheetType":"Calculations"},"type":"enum","values":["None","Day","Week","Month","Quarter","YearCalendar","YearFiscal"]},"tabColor":{"description":"Tab color for the sheet in Excel","properties":{"themeColor":{"required":true,"type":"enum","values":["xlThemeColorDark1","xlThemeColorLight1","xlThemeColorDark2","xlThemeColorLight2","xlThemeColorAccent1","xlThemeColorAccent2","xlThemeColorAccent3","xlThemeColorAccent4","xlThemeColorAccent5","xlThemeColorAccent6","xlThemeColorHyperlink","xlThemeColorFollowedHyperlink"]},"tintAndShade":{"description":"Brightens or darkens the color - valid values depend on color, use 0.0 if valid values unknown","required":true,"type":"number"}},"type":"object"},"tagIds":{"description":"List of tag IDs to associate with this sheet","relevant_when":{"modelSheetType":["Dashboard","Calculations","Assumptions","Metrics"]},"type":"array[string]"},"xlInsertId":{"description":"ID of the XlInsert template to use","required_when":{"modelSheetType":"XlInsert"},"type":"string"},"xlInsertSheetName":{"description":"Name of the sheet within the XlInsert file","required_when":{"all_of":[{"modelSheetType":"XlInsert"},{"xlInsertId":"non-empty"}]},"type":"string"}}}
[USER]: Continue
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me rebuild the layout properly. I'll delete the existing sheets and create clean ones manually — the Assumptions sheet should have LineItems linked to the Assumption Variables (not individual ModelAssumptions), and the Calculations sheet should have a clean structure without duplicates.

Let me first get the LineGroup schema, then rebuild.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get LineGroup schema", object_type="LineGroup", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new LineGroup. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","notes":["Updates support partial payloads - only include properties you want to change"],"object_type":"LineGroup","parameters":{"includeHeader":{"type":"boolean"},"lineGroups":{"description":"Nested sub-groups. For full schema, query help with object_type='LineGroup'","type":"array[LineGroup]"},"lineItems":{"description":". For full schema, query help with object_type='GeneratedLineItem'","type":"array[GeneratedLineItem]"},"name":{"required":true,"type":"string"},"parentId":{"description":"ID of the parent ModelSheet or LineGroup to add this LineGroup to. Required when creating standalone LineGroups via direct API call. Not needed when creating within ModelSheet content parameter or updating existing LineGroups.","type":"string"},"position":{"description":"Zero-based index position within parent's lineGroups array. If not specified, appends to the end.","type":"integer"},"spaceAfterHeader":{"type":"integer"},"spaceBeforeHeader":{"type":"integer"}}}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me get the LineItem schema too, then rebuild the sheets.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get LineItem schema", object_type="GeneratedLineItem", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"error":"Failed to retrieve help from API","object_type":"GeneratedLineItem"}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Let me try getting the LineItem schema differently.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get LineItem schema", object_type="LineItem", parameters={"help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new GeneratedLineItem. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","notes":["Updates support partial payloads - only include properties you want to change"],"object_type":"GeneratedLineItem","parameters":{"assumptionId":{"description":"Assumption ID to display (for Assumption line items)","editable":false,"required_when":{"generatedLineItemType":"Assumption"},"type":"string"},"dashboardId":{"description":"Dashboard ID to display (for Dashboard line items)","editable":false,"required_when":{"generatedLineItemType":"Dashboard"},"type":"string"},"generatedLineItemType":{"description":"Type of line item (Calculation, Assumption, Metric, Dashboard). Automatically inferred from the ModelSheet type. DO NOT set this manually.","editable":false,"type":"enum","values":["Calculation","Assumption","Metric","Dashboard"]},"metricId":{"description":"Metric ID to display (for Metric line items)","editable":false,"required_when":{"generatedLineItemType":"Metric"},"type":"string"},"parentId":{"description":"ID of the parent LineGroup to add this LineItem to. Required when creating standalone LineItems via direct API call. Not needed when creating within LineGroup content parameter.","type":"string"},"position":{"description":"Zero-based index position within parent's lineItems array. If not specified, appends to the end.","type":"integer"},"settings":{"description":"Display settings for this line","properties":{"spaceBefore":{"type":"integer"},"style":{"properties":{"bottomBorderStyle":{"properties":{"lineStyle":{"type":"enum","values":["xlContinuous","xlDashDot","xlDashDotDot","xlSlantDashDot","xlLineStyleNone","xlDouble","xlDot","xlDash"]}},"type":"object"},"fontIsItalic":{"type":"boolean"},"fontWeight":{"type":"enum","values":["Normal","Bold"]},"topBorderStyle":{"properties":{"lineStyle":{"type":"enum","values":["xlContinuous","xlDashDot","xlDashDotDot","xlSlantDashDot","xlLineStyleNone","xlDouble","xlDot","xlDash"]}},"type":"object"}},"type":"object"}},"type":"object"},"variableId":{"description":"Variable ID to display (for Calculation line items)","editable":false,"required_when":{"generatedLineItemType":"Calculation"},"type":"string"}}}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Good, I have the schemas. Now let me delete the existing sheets and rebuild them cleanly. I need to delete both sheets, then create new ones with proper structure.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="delete", explanation="Delete messy auto-layout sheets", object_type="ModelSheet", parameters={"bulk":true,"items":[{"id":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNn"},{"id":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNp"}]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"bulk":true,"failed":0,"mode":"best-effort","processed":2,"results":[{"id":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNn","success":true},{"id":"-PaDcvKKeLOdFU0X4kNp","success":true}],"succeeded":2,"success":true}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Good, sheets deleted. Now let me create clean sheets. I'll create the Assumptions sheet first, then the Calculations sheet with a well-organized structure.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create Assumptions sheet", object_type="ModelSheet", parameters={"content":{"lineGroups":[{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56we"}],"name":"Timing"},{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574X"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MN"}],"name":"Membership"},{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jc"}],"name":"Pricing"}]},"description":"All model inputs","modelSheetType":"Assumptions","name":"Assumptions"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Created 1 of 1 ModelSheet(s)","results":[{"data":{"modelSheet":{"description":"All model inputs","hasWarnings":"No","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW58FB","isControlSheet":"Yes","modelSheetType":"Assumptions","name":"Assumptions"},"success":true},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW58FB","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Assumptions sheet created. Now let me create the Calculations sheet with a clean structure matching the plan.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create Calculations sheet", object_type="ModelSheet", parameters={"content":{"lineGroups":[{"lineItems":[{"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xI"},{"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56AB"}],"name":"Launch timing"},{"lineItems":[{"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc"},{"settings":{"spaceBefore":1,"style":{"topBorderStyle":{"lineStyle":"xlContinuous"}}},"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56JL"}],"name":"New members"},{"lineItems":[{"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw"},{"settings":{"spaceBefore":1,"style":{"topBorderStyle":{"lineStyle":"xlContinuous"}}},"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc"}],"name":"Churn"},{"lineItems":[{"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56JL"},{"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Kc"},{"settings":{"spaceBefore":1,"style":{"fontWeight":"Bold","topBorderStyle":{"lineStyle":"xlContinuous"}}},"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56MX"}],"name":"Net membership"},{"lineItems":[{"settings":{"style":{"bottomBorderStyle":{"lineStyle":"xlDouble"},"fontWeight":"Bold"}},"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2"}],"name":"Members"},{"lineItems":[{"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC"},{"settings":{"spaceBefore":1,"style":{"topBorderStyle":{"lineStyle":"xlContinuous"}}},"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56OX"}],"name":"Pricing"},{"lineItems":[{"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2"},{"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56OX"},{"settings":{"spaceBefore":1,"style":{"fontWeight":"Bold","topBorderStyle":{"lineStyle":"xlContinuous"}}},"variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Px"}],"name":"Revenue"}]},"description":"Membership and revenue calculations","isControlSheet":true,"modelSheetType":"Calculations","name":"Calculations"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Created 1 of 1 ModelSheet(s)","results":[{"data":{"modelSheet":{"description":"Membership and revenue calculations","hasWarnings":"No","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW58Ix","isControlSheet":"Yes","modelSheetType":"Calculations","name":"Calculations"},"success":true},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW58Ix","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Both sheets created. Let me validate the layout and run the health check.

[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="validate-layout", explanation="Validate rebuilt layout", parameters={})
[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="get-model-health", explanation="Final health check", parameters={})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"layout_validation_report":{"items":["⚠ **Layout validation found issues**"]},"missing_assumptions_(72)":{"items":[{"date":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574b","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574g","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574l","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574q","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574v","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575-","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5754","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5759","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575E","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575K","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575P","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575V","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575_","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575e","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575j","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575o","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575t","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575y","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5762","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5767","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576C","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576I","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576N","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576S","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576Y","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576c","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576h","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576m","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576r","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576w","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5770","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5775","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577A","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577F","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577L","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member"},{"date":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MV","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mb","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mi","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mp","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mw","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N2","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N9","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NH","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NO","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NW","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nc","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nj","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nq","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nx","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57O3","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OA","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OI","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OP","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OX","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Od","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ok","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Or","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Oy","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57P4","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PB","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PJ","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PQ","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PY","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pe","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pl","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ps","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pz","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Q5","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QC","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QK","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member"},{"date":"Constant","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jj","prefix":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP/Member"},{"date":"Constant","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jq","prefix":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP/Member"}]}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"errors":[{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574b","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574g","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574l","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574q","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574v","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575-","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5754","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5759","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575E","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575K","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575P","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575V","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575_","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575e","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575j","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575o","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575t","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575y","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5762","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5767","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576C","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576I","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576N","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576S","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576Y","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576c","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576h","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576m","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576r","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576w","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5770","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5775","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577A","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577F","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577L","message":"Assumption for 'Target new members' not in layout","name":"Target new members","unit":"Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xc","variableName":"Target new members"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MV","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mb","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mi","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mp","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mw","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N2","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N9","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NH","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NO","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NW","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nc","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nj","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nq","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nx","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57O3","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OA","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OI","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OP","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OX","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Od","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ok","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Or","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Oy","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57P4","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PB","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PJ","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 25","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PQ","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PY","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pe","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pl","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 26","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ps","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Mar 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pz","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Jun 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Q5","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Sept 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QC","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Dec 27","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QK","message":"Assumption for 'Churn rate' not in layout","name":"Churn rate","unit":"Member/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55xw","variableName":"Churn rate"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Constant","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jj","message":"Assumption for 'Monthly price' not in layout","name":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","variableName":"Monthly price"},{"category":"missingAssumption","dateTime":"Constant","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jq","message":"Assumption for 'Monthly price' not in layout","name":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP/Member","variableId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW55yC","variableName":"Monthly price"}],"warnings":[]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

I see the issue — the Assumptions sheet needs a LineItem for **every** ModelAssumption, not just one per Variable. But that's impractical with 76 assumptions. The better approach is to add all the ModelAssumptions to the sheet. Let me use the auto-layout approach specifically for the Assumptions sheet — I'll delete it and let auto-layout handle it, while keeping my clean Calculations sheet.

Actually, looking at this more carefully, the issue is that each individual period×dimension ModelAssumption needs its own LineItem on the Assumptions sheet. This is how the system works — each assumption needs an entry cell in Excel. Let me update the Assumptions sheet to include all of them properly.

Let me delete the Assumptions sheet and recreate it with all ModelAssumptions.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="delete", explanation="Delete Assumptions sheet to rebuild", object_type="ModelSheet", parameters={"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW58FB"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Deleted 1 of 1 ModelSheet(s)","results":[{"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW58FB","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Now let me recreate the Assumptions sheet with all ModelAssumptions properly organized. I need to collect all the assumption IDs and group them logically.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Get all assumptions with IDs", object_type="ModelAssumption", parameters={"format":"structured","limit":100})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"data":{"count":76,"modelAssumptions":[{"dataType":"Date","date":"Constant","defaultValue":"Local Input: 2025-09-30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56we","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"dd mmm yy","prefix":"Launch date","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574X","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574b","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574g","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574l","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574q","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574v","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575-","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5754","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5759","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575E","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575K","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 50","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575P","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575V","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575_","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575e","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575j","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575o","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575t","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575y","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5762","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5767","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576C","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576I","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 30","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576N","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576S","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576Y","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576c","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576h","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576m","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576r","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576w","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5770","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5775","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577A","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577F","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 10","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577L","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"#,##0","prefix":"Target new members","unit":"Member [Flow]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MN","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MV","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mb","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mi","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mp","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mw","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N2","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N9","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NH","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NO","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NW","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.08","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nc","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nj","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nq","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nx","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57O3","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OA","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OI","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OP","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OX","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Od","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ok","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Or","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.05","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Oy","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57P4","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PB","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PJ","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 25","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PQ","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PY","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pe","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pl","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 26","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ps","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Mar 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pz","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Jun 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Q5","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Sept 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QC","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Dec 27","defaultValue":"Local Input: 0.03","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QK","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"0.0%","prefix":"Churn rate","unit":"Member [Flow]/Member [Balance]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Constant","defaultValue":"Local Input: 29.99","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jc","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"\"£\"#,##0.00","prefix":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP [Constant]/Member [Constant]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Constant","defaultValue":"Local Input: 49.99","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jj","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"\"£\"#,##0.00","prefix":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP [Constant]/Member [Constant]"},{"dataType":"Double","date":"Constant","defaultValue":"Local Input: 79.99","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jq","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"Yes","numberFormat":"\"£\"#,##0.00","prefix":"Monthly price","unit":"GBP [Constant]/Member [Constant]"}]},"warnings":["Unknown filter parameter 'items' ignored"]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

I have all 76 ModelAssumption IDs. Now I need to create the Assumptions sheet with all of them organized into logical groups. Let me build the LineItems arrays for each group.

[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create Assumptions sheet with all items", object_type="ModelSheet", parameters={"content":{"lineGroups":[{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56we"}],"name":"Timing"},{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574X"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574b"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574g"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574l"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574q"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW574v"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575-"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5754"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5759"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575E"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575K"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575P"}],"name":"Target new members - Basic"},{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575V"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575_"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575e"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575j"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575o"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575t"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW575y"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5762"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5767"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576C"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576I"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576N"}],"name":"Target new members - Premium"},{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576S"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576Y"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576c"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576h"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576m"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576r"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW576w"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5770"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW5775"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577A"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577F"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW577L"}],"name":"Target new members - Platinum"},{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MN"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57MV"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mb"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mi"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mp"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Mw"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N2"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57N9"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NH"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NO"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57NW"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nc"}],"name":"Churn rate - Basic"},{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nj"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nq"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Nx"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57O3"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OA"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OI"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OP"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57OX"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Od"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ok"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Or"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Oy"}],"name":"Churn rate - Premium"},{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57P4"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PB"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PJ"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PQ"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57PY"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pe"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pl"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Ps"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Pz"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57Q5"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QC"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57QK"}],"name":"Churn rate - Platinum"},{"lineItems":[{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jc"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jj"},{"assumptionId":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW57jq"}],"name":"Pricing"}]},"description":"All model inputs","modelSheetType":"Assumptions","name":"Assumptions"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"failed_count":0,"message":"Created 1 of 1 ModelSheet(s)","results":[{"data":{"modelSheet":{"description":"All model inputs","hasWarnings":"No","id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW58Ow","isControlSheet":"No","modelSheetType":"Assumptions","name":"Assumptions"},"success":true},"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW58Ow","success":true}],"success_count":1,"total_count":1}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Assumptions sheet created with all 76 ModelAssumptions. Let me now validate the layout and run the final health check.

[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="validate-layout", explanation="Validate final layout", parameters={})
[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="get-model-health", explanation="Final health check", parameters={})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"layout_validation_report":{"items":["✓ **Layout is valid** - All dependencies are properly included in the layout."]}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"errors":[],"warnings":[]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

Layout is valid and health check is clean — **zero errors, zero warnings**! Let me mark the final task complete and verify the calculated values to make sure everything flows through correctly.

[TOOL]: complete_task(explanation="Health check passed - 0 errors/warnings", task_id="task-4")
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Check Revenue calculated values", object_type="Variable", otherAction="get-values", parameters={"dimensions":"all","ids":["-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Px","-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2"],"periods":"sample"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"success":true,"task_id":"task-4"}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"case":"Base/Base","periodsReturned":["Mar 25","Sept 26","Dec 27"],"variables":[{"analysis":{"anomalies":[{"changePercent":"+94.2%","period":"Dec 25","priorPeriod":"Sept 25","priorValue":"£11,397.30","value":"£22,137.77"}],"growthRate":"+27.8% per period","max":{"period":"Dec 27","value":"£88,914.94"},"min":{"period":"Mar 25","value":"£0.00"},"totalOrLast":"£531,140.53","trend":"growing"},"dimensions":[{"path":"Basic","values":{"Dec 27":"£31,805.04","Mar 25":"£0.00","Sept 26":"£19,170.27"}},{"path":"Premium","values":{"Dec 27":"£36,106.45","Mar 25":"£0.00","Sept 26":"£20,355.64"}},{"path":"Platinum","values":{"Dec 27":"£21,003.44","Mar 25":"£0.00","Sept 26":"£11,299.87"}}],"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56Px","name":"Revenue","summary":{"values":{"Dec 27":"£88,914.94","Mar 25":"£0.00","Sept 26":"£50,825.78"}},"unit":"GBP [Flow]"},{"analysis":{"anomalies":[{"changePercent":"+93.6%","period":"Dec 25","priorPeriod":"Sept 25","priorValue":"90","value":"174"}],"growthRate":"+27.4% per period","max":{"period":"Dec 27","value":"682"},"min":{"period":"Mar 25","value":"0"},"totalOrLast":"682","trend":"growing"},"dimensions":[{"path":"Basic","values":{"Dec 27":"354","Mar 25":"0","Sept 26":"213"}},{"path":"Premium","values":{"Dec 27":"241","Mar 25":"0","Sept 26":"136"}},{"path":"Platinum","values":{"Dec 27":"88","Mar 25":"0","Sept 26":"47"}}],"id":"-PeyXJ7n_CvaS9wW56B2","name":"Members","summary":{"values":{"Dec 27":"682","Mar 25":"0","Sept 26":"396"}},"unit":"Member [Balance]"}]}
[ASSISTANT]: 

The model is fully built and calculating correctly. Here's a summary of what was created:

---

## ✅ Gym Revenue Model — Complete

### Model Structure

| Component | Count |
|-----------|-------|
| Tags | 5 (Member abstract, Package abstract + Basic, Premium, Platinum) |
| Variables | 11 (4 Assumption + 7 Calculation) |
| ModelAssumptions | 76 (across all periods, dimensions, and constants) |
| Layout Sheets | 2 (Assumptions + Calculations) |

### Calculation Flow

```ascii
Launch date ──► Is live ──┐
                          ▼
Target new members ──► New members ──────────────┐
                                                  ▼
               Churn rate ──► Members churned ──► Net new members ──► Members ──┐
                                    ▲                                           │
                                    └───── Members[-1] ─────────────────────────┘
                                                                          │
                              Monthly price ──► Quarterly price ──┐       │
                                                                  ▼       ▼
                                                                Revenue
```

### Sample Calculated Values (Base Case)

| Variable | Mar 25 | Sept 26 | Dec 27 |
|----------|--------|---------|--------|
| **Members** | 0 | 396 | 682 |
| Basic | 0 | 213 | 354 |
| Premium | 0 | 136 | 241 |
| Platinum | 0 | 47 | 88 |
| **Revenue** | £0 | £50,826 | £88,915 |

The launch date is set to **30 Sep 2025**, so everything is zero before that — and membership builds up from Q4 2025 onwards. Revenue is growing at ~28% per quarter with the placeholder assumptions.

### Placeholder Assumptions (ready for you to adjust)

| Assumption | Basic | Premium | Platinum |
|------------|-------|---------|----------|
| Target new members/qtr | 50 | 30 | 10 |
| Churn rate/qtr | 8.0% | 5.0% | 3.0% |
| Monthly price | £29.99 | £49.99 | £79.99 |
| Launch date | 30 Sep 25 | | |

The model is clean — **zero errors, zero warnings** on the health check. You can adjust any of the placeholder values, change the launch date, or let me know if you'd like to extend the model (e.g., add costs, scenarios, dashboards, or Excel output).

[SYSTEM: Current task list - this is not a user message]

=== CURRENT TASKS ===

No pending tasks.

Completed Tasks: 4

Use the task management tools (add_task, complete_task, remove_task) to track your work.
=====================
[End of system message]

</conversation>
