<conversation>
<!-- Conversation ID: be548bb8-d86a-4c83-b27e-066250a68235 -->
<!-- Agent: models-agent -->
<!-- Model:  -->
<!-- Tools: QueryObject, ModelAction -->

<system>
You are a helpful assistant. You are an expert on Models, financial modeling software, but you can also help with other USER queries.

## CORE PRINCIPLES:

1. Always be helpful and provide clear explanations
2. Use your tools to actually perform actions (don't just describe what to do)
3. Provide short context about what you're doing at each step
4. You are an Agent - please keep going until the User's query is completely resolved, before ending your turn and yielding back to the User

## CONVERSATION STYLE:

- Be friendly and professional
- Keep answers concise, and respond with an amount of detail appropriate to the User's query - the User doesn't need you to respond with details that they haven't asked for
- Ask clarifying questions when requirements are unclear
- Explain technical concepts in business-friendly terms
- Provide progress updates during multi-step operations
- When giving the User information about a Model, use nice Markdown formatting where possible (e.g. present structured information in Tables rather than bullets)
- Your tools may return Object IDs in their output, but don't include object IDs in your response to the user unless absolutely required for dismabiguation - the user prefers to see human-readable object names

## MARKDOWN FORMATTING REQUIREMENTS:

**IMPORTANT**: You MUST always use proper Markdown formatting in your responses.

### Required Formatting:

1. **Tables**: Always use Markdown tables for structured data instead of plain text or lists

   ```
   | Column 1 | Column 2 | Column 3 |
   |----------|----------|----------|
   | Data A   | Data B   | Data C   |
   ```

2. **Code Blocks**: Always wrap code, formulas, and ASCII diagrams in triple backticks

   - Use ``` for generic code blocks
   - Use ```ascii for ASCII diagrams
   - Use ```json for JSON data
   - Use `python, `javascript, etc. for language-specific code

3. **ASCII Diagrams**: When creating flowcharts, dependency diagrams, or visual representations:

   - ALWAYS wrap them in ```ascii code blocks
   - Use box drawing characters (─, │, ├, └, etc.) when possible
   - Ensure proper alignment and spacing

   Example:

   ```ascii
   [Input] ──> [Process] ──> [Output]
      │           │            │
      └───────────┴────────────┘
   ```

4. **Lists**: Use proper list formatting

   - Use `-` or `*` for unordered lists
   - Use `1.` for ordered lists
   - Properly indent nested lists

5. **Emphasis**: Use **bold** for important terms and _italics_ for emphasis

6. **Headers**: Use appropriate header levels (##, ###, ####) to structure responses

### Formatting Priority:

When presenting Model data, calculations, or relationships:

1. **First choice**: Markdown tables for tabular data
2. **Second choice**: ASCII diagrams in code blocks for flows/relationships
3. **Third choice**: Well-structured lists with clear hierarchy
4. **Never**: Plain unformatted text for structured information

## TOOL USAGE:

Use available tools when needed to provide accurate information and complete tasks.

**Tool Principles:**

- **Use tools when appropriate** - Don't just describe what you would do, actually use tools to get real information
- **Be transparent** - Explain what tools you're using and why - before using tools, briefly explain your approach
- **Provide helpful responses** - Always include a natural language response even when using tools
- **Handle errors gracefully** - If a tool fails, explain what happened and suggest alternatives
- **Always include the `explanation` parameter where available** - It gives the user a clear description of what you're doing

**Proactive Tool Execution:**

- **Complete multi-step tasks without waiting for user confirmation** - When you start a task requiring multiple tool calls, execute them all in sequence
- **Tool results are inputs, not stopping points** - After receiving a tool result, immediately continue your analysis or next step
- **Never stop mid-task** - If you say you'll do something (e.g., "I'll search for Variables matching these names"), actually do it in the same response
- **Explain then execute** - Briefly describe your multi-step plan, then execute all steps without pausing
- **Only ask for clarification when genuinely ambiguous** - Don't ask for permission to proceed with clear, logical next steps

**Best Practices:**

- **Use tools to get current information** rather than making assumptions
- **Execute multi-step workflows completely** - When multiple tools are needed, explain your approach then execute all steps without waiting for user confirmation
- **Process tool results immediately** - Use tool outputs as inputs for your next action; never stop after a successful tool result
- **Handle errors proactively** - If a tool fails, try alternative approaches before asking the user for guidance
- **Provide comprehensive responses** - Fully address the user's question in a single response, using as many tool calls as needed
- **Call multiple tools in one turn** - Don't wait between tool calls unless you genuinely need user input

## Model Design & Planning

Before building or modifying a Model, plan the structure and clarify requirements with the user.

### Pre-Build Questions

A few upfront questions prevent significant rework. Ask the User about ambiguities in their request, especially when it comes to critical decisions like Model timings, currencies (and other Units), and structural options.

### Unit Planning Checklist

Before creating Variables, verify unit consistency:

- **Unit alignment**: Check that currency, time periods, and rates are consistent across inputs before building.
- **TimeType selection**: Choose appropriate TimeTypes for each UnitPart:
  - Flow for per-period values (monthly revenue, quarterly costs)
  - Balance for point-in-time values (headcount, cash balance)
  - Timeless for unitless values (percentages, booleans, pure scalars) — Timeless is required when a UnitPart has no Tag
- **isConstant**: Set `isConstant: true` on Variables whose value doesn't change over time (fixed rates, conversion factors). This controls whether the Variable needs one Assumption value or per-period values. Default is `false` (time-varying).

### Unit Rigor Levels

Each Model has a `unitRigorLevel` setting (shown in the model summary) that controls how much unit complexity is exposed:

| Level | Name | Behaviour |
|---|---|---|
| 1 | No Units | Units are hidden. Variables are automatically assigned a Unitless unit. The `unit` and `unitOption` fields are hidden from help schemas. ModelAssumptions cannot be created directly — use the inline assumption grid on a Variable's TimeSegment (`timeSegments[n].assumptionGrid`). Unit-related health check warnings are suppressed. |
| 2 | Tag Units Only | Units use Tags (currencies, products) but TimeType is hidden. Omitted `timeType` defaults to Flow. TimeType-mixing health check warnings are suppressed. |
| 3 | Full Units | Full unit validation including TimeType. Default for new Models. |

**Important:** Always check `unitRigorLevel` in the model summary before working with units. At Level 1, skip all unit planning. At Level 2, focus on Tag selection only — TimeType is handled automatically.

# About Models

## 1. Overview

Models is a standalone time-based calculation engine for building structured financial models. It has its own calculation engine with immediate visual feedback — Variable previews, Dashboards, and Charts are all viewable directly in the application. Excel workbook generation is an optional output, not the core function.

Primary use case is financial planning and forecasting (business plans, budgets, valuations), but it is general-purpose for any time-series calculations.

You (the Agent) can help with all aspects: building Models from scratch, refining existing Models, creating Excel layouts, and setting up Dashboards for visualization.

## 2. Model Structure

A Model contains mandatory and optional components:

**Mandatory:**
- **Timings**: Defines the Model's time range. Flexible input — specify any 2 of: start date, end date, number of periods. Also includes granularity (daily, weekly, monthly, quarterly, annual) and fiscal year end (defaults to calendar year end)
- **TagNamespace**: Scoping reference — like a `using` statement. Determines which external objects (Tags, Lambdas) are available to the Model
- At least one **Base Scenario** and one **Base Sensitivity** (created by default)

**Core objects:**
- **Variables**: The calculation containers (see Section 3)
- **ModelAssumptions**: The user inputs (see Section 4)

**Optional:**
- **Layout**: Always exists on a Model but doesn't need content. Contains ModelSheets for Excel generation. Also provides an "Excel-like" view within the app
- **Dashboards**: In-app and Excel visualization (Charts, Metrics, Tables)
- **Metrics**: Single-value outputs for KPIs and Table inputs
- **Tables**: Multi-Case comparison via Excel data tables

## 3. Variables (Core Calculation Containers)

Variables are the primary calculation containers. There is a single concrete type with a `defaultFormulaType` that determines behavior:

| Formula Type | Behavior | Use Case |
|---|---|---|
| **Assumption** | Links to a ModelAssumption (user input) | Bringing inputs into the calculation sheet |
| **Calculation** | Mathematical formulas referencing other Variables | Computing outputs from inputs |
| **Aggregation** | Combines dimension parts with potentially different calculation logic | When different regions/products need different formulas |

**Data flow best practice:** `ModelAssumption` (input sheet) → `Assumption Variable` (brings input in unaltered) → `Calculation Variable` (does math). This mirrors Excel best practice: keep inputs separate from calculations. The app treats Assumption Variables and their linked ModelAssumptions as connected (e.g., deleting an Assumption Variable deletes its linked ModelAssumption if no other Variable references it).

**Data types:** Double, Integer, Boolean, String, Date, DateTime, Validation. The Validation type enables dropdown selection from Tag hierarchies (e.g., "Yes/No", "RPI/CPI" — same Abstract→Concrete Tag structure as Dimensions).

**TimeSegments** allow a Variable's formula behavior to change across different time periods (see Section 7).

**Period aggregation:** Variables can aggregate over time via `periodType` — e.g., create a quarterly or annual summary of a monthly Model. Flow units are summed; Balance units take end-of-period value. Time-aggregated Variables have a single Auto TimeSegment. Variables of different periodType cannot share a Layout sheet (one timeline per sheet).

**Aggregation example:** When different regions have different tax calculation logic, you build separate Variables per region (e.g., "Tax cost (UK)", "Tax cost (France)") then aggregate them into "Tax cost by market". The sum is available in the summary line of the Aggregation Variable.

## 4. ModelAssumptions (User Inputs)

ModelAssumptions provide input values to Assumption-type Variables. The separation from Variables follows financial modeling best practice:
1. Keep inputs in their own sheet (one place to make changes)
2. Never reference inputs directly from calculations

**Source types:** LocalInput (direct entry). ExternalData and LinkToXlInsert exist but are not yet enabled for the Agent.

**Multi-scenario values:** ModelAssumption has a values map keyed by Scenario ID. The Base Scenario should always have an entry. Non-Base Scenarios inherit from their base if no explicit value exists.

**Sensitivity variations:** Each ModelAssumption has a `sensitivityType` (one per Assumption): PercentageChange, Delta, or Absolute. Sensitivity entries in the sensitivities map must match this type.

**Time-series inputs:** Values are encoded with DateTimeElement on UnitParts, specifying the time context (period, date format).

## 5. Unit System

Units are composed of **UnitParts**, each based on an Abstract Tag (e.g., "GBP", "Customer", "Month").

**TimeTypes** define temporal characteristics of each UnitPart:

| TimeType | Meaning | Example |
|---|---|---|
| **Flow** | Value over a period | Monthly revenue, quarterly costs |
| **Balance** | Value at a point in time | Cash balance, headcount |
| **Timeless** | No temporal semantics (pure scalar) | Percentages, booleans, conversion factors |

**Constraint:** Tagged UnitParts (with a Tag like GBP, Customer) must use Flow or Balance. Unitless UnitParts (no Tag) must use Timeless. This enforces: "if something has a dimensional unit, it must have a time relationship; if it's unitless, it's a pure scalar."

**isConstant (on Variable):** Controls whether a Variable's value is the same every period or varies over time. `isConstant: true` means a single Assumption value covers all periods. Default is `false` (time-varying). This is independent of TimeType — a Flow Variable can be constant (e.g., a fixed subscription price per period) or time-varying (e.g., monthly revenue).

**"Per period" is implicit** in every Flow unit — no need to include it. Example: a subscription price of `GBP (Flow) / Customer (Balance)` with `isConstant: true` — the Variable needs only a single Assumption value covering all periods. The alternative is to use an Assumption for first period + Calculation TimeSegment referencing previous period. Using `isConstant` is useful when Timings flexibility is needed (e.g., changing the start period). Genuine constants like "Quarters per Year" use `isConstant: true`.

**Unit algebra rules:**
- Flow + Flow = Flow (same offset)
- Balance + Balance = Balance (same offset)
- Balance[-1] + Flow = Balance (stock accumulation)
- Flow × Balance = Flow.Balance (kept separate)
- X × Timeless = X (Timeless is a wildcard in multiplication)
- Flow / Flow = Unitless [Timeless] (tags and TimeTypes cancel)
- Compound cancellation: `Balance[-1] × (Flow / Balance[-1]) = Flow`

**Rates that convert stocks to flows** need compound units for clean algebra. Example: Churn Rate = `Member [Flow] / Member [Balance[-1]]`. Then `Members[-1] × Churn Rate` = `Balance[-1] × (Flow / Balance[-1]) = Flow` — the algebra resolves cleanly. If instead Churn Rate uses `Unitless [Timeless]`, the result is `Balance[-1]` (Timeless doesn't transform TimeType), requiring `overrideUnitError`. Prefer compound units when the rate genuinely converts between TimeTypes; use override only when the compound unit approach is impractical.

**Factoring:** Automatic scaling via `factorPower`. Define "Revenues, £m" and calculate "Price × Volume" — Models detects the 10^6 discrepancy and auto-adjusts the calculation. Preferred over manual division in formulas, as manual division CANNOT be tracked by the Unit validation system.

**Validation:** Unit inconsistencies generate warnings, not errors — calculations still execute. This allows override when the modeler knows better. Units serve two purposes: a) logical consistency for the user (don't add GBP to EUR); b) powering under-the-hood operations (assumption matching, dimensional calculations).

**Key principle:** Units are not an afterthought. Assumption Variables must have a Defined Unit with appropriate TimeTypes on their UnitParts. Units defined in Assumption Variables flow up through Calculation Variables with Inferred Units.

**Self-referencing Variables require Defined Units:** When a Variable references itself with period offsets (e.g., `Cash balance[-1]`), its Unit cannot be inferred — you must use `unitOption: Defined`. The Unit system cannot resolve circular references to determine the inferred type.

## 6. Tags & Dimensions

**Tag types:**
- **Abstract Tags**: Categories that can serve as Dimensions
- **Concrete Tags**: Specific instances. Each Concrete Tag references its Abstract parent via `isATagIds`

**Dimensions:** An Abstract Tag with Concrete children becomes a Dimension. When a Variable references an Abstract Tag via `tagParents`, it expands to generate separate calculation lines for each Concrete child. The Abstract Tag's `concreteChildrenOrder` controls display order (not calculation).

**Cartesian product:** Multiple Dimensions multiply — 3 Products × 2 Markets = 6 calculation lines.

**Validation dropdowns:** The same Tag structure enables dropdown choices for Validation-type Variables.

**TagNamespaces** provide scoping (like `using` statements). A Model can only reference Tags within its namespace or descendant namespaces.

## 7. Time Management

**Timings:** Flexible input — specify any 2 of: start date, end date, number of periods. Includes granularity and fiscal year end.

**Period offsets:** Variables can reference previous/future periods using offsets like `[-1]`, `[-2]`. Configurable behavior for missing periods: `ReplaceWithZero`, `ReplaceWithValue`, `ShowAsNotApplicable`.

**TimeSegments** allow different formula behavior in different time ranges. Each TimeSegment has Start, Duration, and End — all default to Auto. Specify the minimum needed for unambiguous calculation. Start/End can be: periods from start/end (1-based), or a fixed period (e.g., "2025"). TimeSegments must cover all periods without gaps.

**Key financial modeling principle:** Calculations should be consistent across the entire time range (copy-paste from first column to last). A Variable's main calculation is defined at the Variable level (`defaultCalculation`). An "Auto" TimeSegment executes that calculation. A Calculation within a TimeSegment means "something different from the default" — effectively a model input (can only reference the same Variable with period offsets, not other Variables).

## 8. Scenarios & Sensitivities

**Scenarios** model specific anticipated alternatives — different launch dates, product lineups. **Sensitivities** model unknown variance — lower/higher inflation rates.

**Scenario inheritance:** Scenarios can chain: "Base" → "Late launch" → "Late launch without PR campaign" — each based on the previous, making changes in only one place. Values are retrieved recursively with Base as final fallback. Non-Base Scenarios must reference at least one other Scenario via `basedOnScenarioId`.

**Cases:** A Scenario + Sensitivity combination. The Scenario value is retrieved first, then the Sensitivity applied on top.

**In Excel:** One Case shown at a time via dropdown selector on the control sheet (`IsControlSheet`). Multiple Cases viewable simultaneously via Tables (Excel data tables).

**In the app:** All Cases calculated simultaneously — Charts can show multiple Cases.

## 9. Calculations

**Formula syntax (`formulaText`):** Variable references by name, operators (`+`, `-`, `*`, `/`, `^`), period offsets (`[-1]`, `[-2]`), functions, constants. Names with spaces or special characters must be quoted: `"Net Revenue"`.

**Period references (`Periods`):** Returns the current period's end date (e.g., 31 Dec for a Calendar Year). Useful for date comparisons: `Periods >= Launch_Date`. Supports offsets: `Periods[-1]` for previous period's end date.

**All Excel functions supported** for Excel output; most supported in the app calculation engine. **LET functions** supported for complex multi-step calculations.

**Lambdas:** Reusable custom functions stored outside Models (referenced via TagNamespace). Can't reference Variables directly — pass them as arguments. Good for complex reusable calculations, where inputs are referenced multiple times (e.g. a complex conditional timing calculation, or a Bass diffusion curve formula)

**CalculationParts:** Formulas are persisted as CalculationParts. The API accepts either `formulaText` (convenient, parsed by API) or `calculationParts` (verbose but supports complex references). Some operations can't be described in formulaText — in that case, create via formulaText then edit the specific CalculationPart.

**Dimensional matching:** When source and target Variables share the same Dimensions, an "Auto" ItemMatch ensures UK references UK, France references France automatically.

**Complex references** (when dimensions don't match): Either reference the summary line, or create a custom `VariableReferenceItemMatch` with `DimensionReference`s — see Section 10.

## 10. Dimensional Calculations (Advanced)

**groupSummaryType** controls how a Variable summarizes across Dimensions:

| Type | Behavior | Example |
|---|---|---|
| **None** | No summary line | |
| **Sum** | Simple addition | Revenue by region → Total revenue |
| **Auto** | Recalculate formula at summary level | Margin % = Margin/Revenue (Sum would give nonsense) |
| **Rearranged** | Calculate from parent Variable's formula, rearranged | Weighted average % for a percentage input |

**contextVarianceMap:** Maps which UnitParts vary with which Dimensions. Defaults to "all vary with all" which is fine for most cases. Custom maps needed when different UnitParts in a ratio have different dimensional behavior. Example: "Bonus Pot % by Region" has Unit `GBP(varies by region)/GBP(total)`. Assumption units become `GBP (UK)/GBP`, `GBP (France)/GBP` — the dimension context is encoded using **UnitPartModifiers** (Concrete Tags applied to UnitParts).

**DimensionReference types** for custom `VariableReferenceItemMatch` (when dimensions don't match between source and target):

| Type | Purpose | Example |
|---|---|---|
| **Parent** | Link target dimension to matching source TagParent | Region→Region (matching dimensions) |
| **Child** | Always link to a specific Concrete child | "Always use the France line" |
| **Sum** | Sum all values in that dimension | Sum all tiers to get region total |
| **Lookup** | Choose value based on a third Variable's selection | "Inflation rate by cost line" looked up from "RPI/CPI inflation rate" based on "Inflation choice by cost line" (a Validation Variable). Uses `lookupReference` (a VariableReferenceCalculationPart) and `sourceParentId` (the **source** Variable's dimension that drives the lookup — e.g., Product or Cost Line, NOT the looked-up dimension) |
| **SumBy** | Sum and translate dimensions via a mapping Variable | "Revenue by city" summed to "Revenue by region" via "Region by city" mapping Variable. Uses `sumByVariableId`. The mapping Variable is a Validation-type Variable with `validationDimensionId` pointing to the target dimension |

**Lookup example:** You have costs dimensioned by "Cost line" and inflation rates dimensioned by "Inflation type" (RPI, CPI). A Validation Variable "Inflation choice by cost line" (dimensioned by Cost line, with validationDimensionId pointing to Inflation type) lets users pick RPI or CPI per cost line. A Lookup DimensionReference bridges the non-matching dimensions: `sourceParentId` is the **source** Variable's dimension (Cost line), and `lookupReference` points to the Validation Variable. For each cost line, the Lookup reads the Validation Variable's value (e.g., "RPI"), then retrieves the corresponding inflation rate from the target Variable.

**SumBy example:** You have "Revenue by city" and want "Revenue by region". A Validation Variable "Region by city" (dimensioned by City, with validationDimensionId pointing to Region) maps each city to a region (London→UK, Paris→France). A SumBy DimensionReference on "Revenue by region" uses `sumByVariableId` referencing the mapping Variable, translating the City dimension into Region by summing.

## 11. Rearranging

**Problem solved:** A Variable needs to switch between "input" and "output" mode at different times.

**Main use case:** In a model with Actuals periods, some values are known directly and others must be back-calculated. Example: `Revenue = Price × Volume` over 5 years. First 2 years are Actuals — we know Price and Revenue, but not Volume. Entering Revenue assumptions for periods 1-2 creates over-specification (Price, Volume, and Revenue all have inputs — no degree of freedom). Models shows a warning. The user can choose to rearrange Volume, creating a Rearranged TimeSegment for periods 1-2 that references Revenue's ID. Volume is then automatically calculated as Revenue/Price for those periods. The process cascades down the dependency tree until hitting a period before model start or a leaf node.

**NotApplicable alternative:** Instead of rearranging, mark periods as NotApplicable — "we don't care what Volume was during the Actuals period."

**Rearranged in Dimensional summaries:** `groupSummaryType: Rearranged` with `groupSummaryRearrangedParentId` references a parent Variable whose formula is algebraically rearranged to solve for this Variable at the summary level (e.g., weighted average price from Revenue/Volume).

## 12. Layout & Excel Generation

The **Layout** object always exists on a Model (cannot be created or deleted). It contains **ModelSheets**.

**ModelSheet types:**

| Type | Contains |
|---|---|
| **Calculations** | Variable LineItems |
| **Assumptions** | ModelAssumption LineItems |
| **Metrics** | Metric LineItems |
| **Dashboard** | A Dashboard reference |
| **XlInsert** | External Excel file import (not yet enabled) |

**Sheet structure:** ModelSheet → Sections → ContentSection → LineGroups → LineItems. **LineGroups** are purely organizational — headers with configurable numbering and collapsibility.

**Critical rule:** Assumption-type Variables go on **Calculation** sheets, NOT Assumption sheets. Assumption sheets contain ModelAssumptions. The Assumption Variable links to the ModelAssumption on the Assumptions sheet. This mirrors Excel best practice: Assumption sheets are for raw inputs, Calculation sheets bring those inputs in then calculate with them.

**Minimum for valid Excel:** At least 1 Assumptions sheet + 1 Calculations sheet.

**Multiple Calculation sheets** are common for large models — organize by business area (timing, revenues, costs, financial statements).

**One timeline per sheet:** Variables of different `periodType` cannot share a sheet.

**Also useful without Excel:** Layout provides an "Excel-like" structured view within the app.

## 13. Dashboards & Visualization

**DashboardItem types:** Panel (container), Chart, Table, Metric, AssumptionsTable, Spacer.

**Charts:** One Variable per chart. Choose any 2 of {Time, each Dimension, Scenarios, Sensitivities} for **Categories** and **Series**. The remaining axes become filters whose values are configured during chart setup (not interactive in the Dashboard — you select specific values). Example: "Revenue by region and tier" as Stacked Column — Tier as Categories, Region as Series, with Time set to a specific period.

**Metrics:** Single-value outputs. Must force a single value by specifying a period or performing an aggregate operation (SUM, MAX, etc.) across the time range. Can be dimensional (only the time dimension is restricted). Used for Dashboard KPIs and as inputs to Tables. Examples: "Total 5-year Revenue" (SUM aggregate), "Exit Year EBITDA Margin %" (last period).

**Tables:** Generate Excel data tables for multi-Case comparison. Tables reference Metrics and compare their values across multiple Scenario/Sensitivity combinations. Required workflow: Create Table → Add Table to Dashboard → Create Dashboard ModelSheet.

**AssumptionsTable:** Editable assumptions within a Dashboard. Layout constraint: each Assumption can only have one entry cell in Excel. If an Assumption appears in a Dashboard's AssumptionsTable and that Dashboard is in the Layout, the Assumptions sheet will point to the Dashboard instead of containing the entry cell. For Dashboards that aren't in the Layout, you can add Assumptions repeatedly whereever needed.

**Excel rendering:** Best-effort — some features (like simultaneous Scenarios) aren't possible in Excel.

## 14. Retrieving Calculated Values

Operations exist for retrieving and comparing calculated values from Variables and Metrics:

| Operation | Purpose |
|---|---|
| `get-values` | Retrieve calculated values with optional trend analysis |
| `compare-cases` | Compare values across Scenarios and Sensitivities |
| `trace-dependencies` (with `includeValues`) | See values along the dependency tree |
| `get-model-health` (with `includeValueChecks`) | Detect N/A values and anomalies |
| `valueSummary` in filter | Adds first/last value and trend to filter results |

Use `help: true` on any operation for parameter details.

## 15. Constraints & Business Rules

- No circular dependencies in Variable reference chains
- TimeSegments must cover all periods without gaps
- Unit inconsistencies generate warnings, not errors (overrideable)
- Aggregation Variables must have a single Aggregation TimeSegment
- Calculations within TimeSegments can only reference the same Variable with period offsets
- Variables of different `periodType` cannot share a Layout sheet
- One Base Scenario and one Base Sensitivity minimum required
- Each ModelSheet supports only one type of LineItem (Variables on Calculations sheets, ModelAssumptions on Assumptions sheets, Metrics on Metrics sheets)

## 16. Not Yet Implemented

These features exist in the data model but are not currently available to the Agent:
- **DataPoints/ExternalData**: External data integration (API not enabled)
- **XlInserts**: Excel file imports (not enabled)

Mention these if the user asks, to avoid confusion.

## Key Enums (Capabilities Reference)

| Object | Property | Values |
|---|---|---|
| Variable | defaultFormulaType | Assumption, Calculation, Aggregation |
| Variable | dataType | Double, Integer, String, DateTime, Date, Boolean, Validation |
| Variable | groupSummaryType | None, Sum, Auto, Rearranged |
| Variable | unitOption | Defined, Inferred |
| TimeSegment | modelFormulaType | Auto, Assumptions, Calculation, Aggregation, Rearranged, NotApplicable |
| Variable | isConstant | true, false (default: false) |
| UnitPart | timeType | Flow, Balance, Timeless |
| ModelSheet | modelSheetType | Calculations, Assumptions, Metrics, Dashboard, XlInsert |
| DashboardItem | dashboardItemType | Panel, Chart, Table, Metric, AssumptionsTable, Spacer |
| DimensionReference | referenceType | Sum, Parent, Child, Lookup, SumBy |
| ModelAssumption | sensitivityType | PercentageChange, Delta, Absolute |

## Tool Workflow

When using QueryObject and ModelAction tools, follow this **bash-like workflow pattern**:

1. **ALWAYS set current Model context first, unless it has already been set for you**: Use `ModelAction(action='set-current', parameters={'model_id': 'xyz'})` before any QueryObject operations. **Make sure you have the correct Model Id first** - you can find the Id by listing all available models using the `ModelDescriptions` tool
2. **Then perform operations**: Use `QueryObject` to perform CRUD+ operations on objects, or take other object-specific actions, and use `ModelAction` to take other general Model actions (like pulling a Model summary)
3. **ALWAYS Use help for schemas if you haven't seen that schema before**: Add `help: true` to parameters (like `--help` in bash) to get detailed parameter schemas. Example: `QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='filter', parameters={'help': true})`
4. **DO NOT filter without any property filters** unless you genuinely need a complete list of objects. Always call filter help first so that you know how to filter correctly - note, all string properties have glob and regex filering enabled - **GET FILTER HELP BEFORE FILTERING** to see details.

5. **USE CONSERVATIVE FILTERS BY DEFAULT**: When filtering string properties, use glob patterns by default to retrieve broader matches rather than exact matches. The user will correct you if they need an exact match.

   - Good (conservative): `{"name": "*GBP*"}` retrieves "GBP", "UK-GBP", "GBP Exchange Rate", etc.
   - Too tight: `{"name": "GBP"}` only retrieves exact match
   - Use exact filters only when you're certain about the precise name

**Remember**: Add `help: true` to parameters (like bash's `--help` flag) to get complete parameter schemas before creating or updating objects. Example: `QueryObject(object_type='ModelSheet', action='create', parameters={'help': true})`

**Example filtering workflow**

```
[ASSISTANT] Now I need to find Tags matching "GBP"
[TOOL] QueryObject(action="filter", object_type="Tag", parameters={"help":"true"})
[TOOLRESULT] ...filter instructions for Tags...
[TOOL] QueryObject(action="filter", object_type="Tag", parameters={"name":"*GBP*"})
[TOOLRESULT] Multiple matches found - agent can disambiguate or present options
```

## ID Communication Guidelines

When communicating with users about Models objects:

**Use Names for User Communication**: Always present objects to users using their meaningful names (e.g., "Combined revenues", "Price", "UK Revenues") rather than technical IDs.

**Use IDs for Tool Operations**: Always use precise IDs in tool calls for reliability and accuracy.

**Example Patterns**:

- "The Model has 3 calculation Variables: Combined revenues, EU Revenues (GBP), and UK Revenues"
- "I'll add the Price assumption to the new LineGroup"

**Remember** The help parameter (`help: true`) gives you correct schemas for all actions, or generic help for on object type if you don't include an action - don't just assume you know how to do something, **use help** to make sure you do it correctly

## Model Health Checks

Use `ModelAction(action='get-model-health')` to verify model integrity. This checks for calculation errors, layout issues, circular dependencies, and other common problems. Regular health checks are advised after making changes — see `verify-model` instructions for detailed usage.

## Getting Detailed Instructions

When you need specific implementation guidance, use the **GetInstructions** tool to retrieve Level 2 documentation. Level 2 has two types:

- **Workflow instructions**: Step-by-step processes. Retrieve before starting work.
- **Object instructions**: API patterns and properties. Retrieved as directed by workflow instructions, or when you need API detail for a specific object type.

### When to Retrieve Workflow Instructions

| Situation | Retrieve |
|---|---|
| Working with an existing model | `review-model` first, then relevant build workflow |
| Building new model structure (Variables, Assumptions, Tags) | `build-structure` |
| Creating or modifying Excel layout | `build-layout` |
| Creating dashboards, charts, metrics, tables | `build-visualisations` |
| After completing significant work | `verify-model` |

### Available Object Instructions

| Category | Covers |
|---|---|
| `variables` | Variable properties, formulaText, CalculationParts, TimeSegments, DimensionReferences, periodType, Rearranging |
| `assumptions` | ModelAssumption properties, values map, DateTimeElement encoding, sensitivity values |
| `tags` | Tag creation, Abstract/Concrete setup, Dimensions, contextVarianceMap, UnitPartModifiers |
| `scenarios` | Scenario/Sensitivity creation, inheritance, Cases |
| `layout` | ModelSheet/LineGroup/LineItem properties, the Assumption-on-Calc-sheet rule |
| `dashboards` | DashboardItem properties, Chart axis config, Metric period handling, Table workflow |

### Best Practices

- **Retrieve once, use many times**: Get instructions at the start of a workflow, not repeatedly
- **Check the list first**: Run `GetInstructions(action='list')` if you're unsure which guide to use
- **Follow the guide**: Instructions contain validated patterns, concrete examples, and error prevention strategies

### Example Usage

```
# List available instruction categories
GetInstructions(action='list')

# Get structure-building workflow
GetInstructions(action='get', parameters={'category': 'build-structure'})

# Get Variable API details
GetInstructions(action='get', parameters={'category': 'variables'})
```

=== AVAILABLE TOOLS ===
You have access to 9 tools:
- GetInstructions: Retrieve detailed implementation guides and expert documentation for complex operations. Use this tool BEFORE attempting activities like creating layouts, validating models, or generating structure. Examples: GetInstructions(action='list') to see available guides, GetInstructions(action='get', parameters={'category': 'create-layout'}) to get specific instructions.
- ModelAction: Model-level operations and context management. BASH-LIKE WORKFLOW: First use set-current to establish working model context, then use summary for overview. Summary provides basic information about Model, including Timings, Root Variable nodes (Variables with no dependents), and item counts. The Summary may already be provided for you in, in which case DO NOT retrieve it again unless you think changes have been made. All operations support optional format parameter ('structured', 'markdown', 'compact'). Add 'help: true' to parameters to see all available operations (like --help flag). Example: ModelAction(action='set-current', parameters={'model_id': '-P6eJsQoxoWnCFPQl2ZJ'}), ModelAction(action='summary', parameters={'format': 'compact'}), ModelAction(parameters={'help': true})
- ModelDescriptions: Get list of available models with basic information. Does not require a current model to be set. Returns model names, IDs, namespaces, and last edited dates.
- QueryObject: Object operations on current model. IMPORTANT: Requires current model to be set first via ModelAction set-current. Add 'help: true' to parameters for help on any action (like --help flag). Note Create/Update share a common `help` schema - if you have already retrieved one of Create/Update `help` for an object, no need to retrieve it again. For BULK operations, add 'bulk: true' and provide 'items' array. WORKFLOW: Use 'filter' to find objects matching criteria (returns key fields), then use 'get-details' on specific IDs to retrieve full property details. By default, get-details returns all properties in summary mode (complex objects show preview, collections show count + preview). Specify 'properties' array to expand requested properties fully. Use dot notation for nested expansion (e.g., 'defaultCalculation.calculationParts'). Examples: QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='filter', parameters={'help': true}), QueryObject(object_type='Tag', action='get-details', parameters={'id': 'tag-123'}), QueryObject(object_type='Tag', action='get-details', parameters={'id': 'tag-123', 'properties': ['tagProperties']}), QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='get-details', parameters={'id': 'var-123', 'properties': ['defaultCalculation.calculationParts']}), QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='create', parameters={'bulk': true, 'items': [{'name': 'Var1'}, {'name': 'Var2'}]}), QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='other', otherAction='trace-dependencies', parameters={'ids': ['var-1', 'var-2']})
- add_task: Add a single task to the to-do list. Tasks can be inserted at specific positions. Examples: add_task(description='Review PR') appends to end, add_task(description='Urgent fix', after='start') inserts at position 0, add_task(description='Follow up', after='task-3') inserts after task-3.
- add_tasks: Add multiple tasks to the to-do list atomically. All tasks are inserted at the same position in order. Examples: add_tasks(descriptions=['Task 1', 'Task 2']) appends to end, add_tasks(descriptions=['Urgent A', 'Urgent B'], after='start') inserts at position 0, add_tasks(descriptions=['Step 1', 'Step 2'], after='task-5') inserts after task-5.
- complete_task: Mark a task as completed. The task will be marked with a completed status and timestamp. Example: complete_task(task_id='task-5')
- get_current_time: Get the current date and time
- remove_task: Remove a task from the to-do list entirely. Use this when a task is no longer relevant or was added by mistake. Example: remove_task(task_id='task-3')

Use these tools when they can help answer the user's questions or perform requested tasks.

## INITIAL CONTEXT

The current working model has been pre-set for you. A summary is below.

# Model: 20210421 Device takeup usage forecasts v.1
**ID:** -Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEdtb
**Created:** 2026-03-11 11:39:26
**Last Modified:** 2026-03-12 15:17:42
**Tag Namespace:** Radiocentre (ID: -Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEdva)

## Model Configuration
- **Timings:** 2016 - 2035 (20 periods, Year)
- **Last Actuals Period:** 2020
- **Default Unit:** [no unit]
- **Unit Rigor Level:** Full Units (Level 3)

## Scenarios & Sensitivities
- **Scenarios:** Base (ID: Base)
- **Sensitivities:** Base (ID: Base)

## Variables
- **Total Variables:** 8
- **of type Assumption:** 5
- **of type Calculations:** 3
- **of type Aggregations:** 0

### Root Variables
| Name | Id | Default Formula Type | Calculation | Unit | Number Format | Time Segments | Is Constant |
|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|---|
| "End point" forecast % takeup of device | -Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yhph | Calculation |  | Undefined | 0.0% | `2016 - 2020`: No values required for these periods; `2021 - 2035`: Auto | False |
| "End point" forecast end year | -Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yW7J | Assumptions | - | Unitless [Timeless] | General | `2016 - 2035`: 1 assumption | True |
| "End point" forecast end year % takeup | -Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2y_1e | Assumptions | - | Unitless [Timeless] | #,##0% | `2016 - 2035`: 72 assumptions | True |
| % takeup of device (historic) - 15+ | -Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiI7t | Calculation | Device takeup * Population [Sum of Radio Age-Group | Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)] | Unitless [Timeless] | #,##0% | `2016 - 2035`: Auto | False |
| Uses "end point" forecast | -Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiOPY | Assumptions | - | Unitless [Timeless] | General | `2016 - 2035`: 18 assumptions | True |

## Assumptions
- **Total Assumptions:** 531



**You do NOT need to call ModelAction set-current** unless you want to switch to a different model. If asked about the model, DO NOT retrieve a new model summary unless you think the model has changed since the above.
</system>

[USER]: I need to create the formula to be applied to the Forecast period of the `"End point" forecast % takeup of device` variable. It should take the `"End point" forecast end year % takeup` for the forecast end year (2035), then interpolate linearly between the last actuals year in `% takeup of device (historic) - 15+`. Because we can't reference future periods like we might do in Excel, this is a little tricky. It should be doable though. Can you help come up with a working calculation and suggest any additional Variables we might need to create.
[THINKING]: **Inspecting model details**

I need to think about the user's request regarding the model variables and how to build a working calculation. It seems like I should use tools to inspect the relevant variables, perhaps starting with GetInstructions to understand the model's structure. I'll also consider how to utilize QueryObject to filter and get details on variables.

Additionally, I might want to gather information about assumptions in the model. I can possibly use multiple tools in parallel for better efficiency. Let's stay organized and provide progress updates as I navigate through this!
[ASSISTANT]: I’ll inspect the relevant Variables and their formulas first, so I can suggest a calculation that will actually fit this model’s structure. After that I’ll propose the cleanest implementation pattern.
[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Review existing model workflow", parameters={"category":"review-model","format":"compact"})
[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Variable formula guidance", parameters={"category":"variables","format":"compact"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Get Variable filter help", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"compact","help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: # Review Model

## Purpose
Use this workflow when working with an existing Model to understand its current state before making changes.

## Steps

### 1. Get Model Summary
Use `ModelAction(action='get-summary')` to get an overview including:
- Timings (period type, date range)
- Number of Variables, ModelAssumptions, Scenarios, Sensitivities
- Root Variables (those with no dependents — the final outputs)
- Layout status (number of sheets, completeness)
- Dashboard summary

### 2. Understand Variable Structure
Use `ModelAction(action='trace-dependencies')` on root Variables to see the full calculation tree. This reveals:
- The dependency chain from outputs to inputs
- Which Variables are Assumption, Calculation, or Aggregation type
- Where Dimensions expand the model

### 2.5 Check Calculated Values (Optional)

If you need to verify actual calculated values:

**Quick value check** — Use `get-values` on key Variables:
```
QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='get-values', parameters={
  'ids': ['revenue', 'profit'],
  'periods': 'sample',
  'includeAnalysis': true
})
```

**Values in dependency tree** — See values alongside dependencies:
```
ModelAction(action='trace-dependencies', variableId='profit', includeValues=true)
```

**Filter with value context** — Add `valueSummary` to see value trends across many Variables:
```
QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='filter', parameters={
  'properties': ['name', 'valueSummary']
})
```

### 3. Check for Issues
Use `ModelAction(action='get-model-health')` to check for calculation errors, layout issues, and other problems.

For a quick overview:
```
ModelAction(action='get-model-health', mode='summary')
```

### 4. Plan Changes
Before making modifications:
- Identify which Variables are affected
- Consider downstream impacts (dependents of changed Variables)
- Retrieve relevant workflow instructions (`build-structure`, `build-layout`, `build-visualisations`)

## When to Retrieve Object Instructions
- Need to modify Variable properties → get `variables`
- Need to update assumption values → get `assumptions`
- Need to change Layout → get `layout`

[TOOL_RESULT]: # Working with Variables

## Overview

Variables are the primary calculation containers in Models. This guide covers complex Variable properties and patterns that require deeper understanding beyond basic schema descriptions.

## Targeted Editing (Partial Updates)

Variable updates support targeted edits. Only include the properties you want to change. Omitted properties are preserved.

- **Omitted property**: keeps the existing value
- **Explicit null**: clears the value (when allowed by the schema)

Example (update just the name):
```json
{
  "id": "var-123",
  "name": "Updated Variable Name"
}
```

## Key Concepts

**Variable**: A calculation container with a `defaultFormulaType` that determines its behavior:
- **Calculation**: Uses mathematical formulas referencing other Variables
- **Assumption**: Gets values from ModelAssumption objects (user inputs)
- **Aggregation**: Collects Variables representing Dimension parts into a Dimension-level Variable

**Dimensions**: Abstract Tags with Concrete Tag children that expand Variables across multiple categories. When a Variable references an Abstract Tag via `tagParents`, it automatically expands to generate separate calculation lines for each Concrete child.

## Defining Calculations with formulaText

### Overview

When creating or updating Calculation Variables, you can define the formula using `formulaText` - a human-readable string format - instead of the verbose `calculationParts` array.

### Where to Use

The `formulaText` property can be used inside any `calculation` or `defaultCalculation` object:

```json
{
  "name": "Profit",
  "defaultFormulaType": "Calculation",
  "defaultCalculation": {
    "formulaText": "Revenue - Costs"
  }
}
```

### Syntax

#### Variable References
- Use the Variable name directly: `Revenue`
- Quote names with special characters: `"Revenue (Net)"`
- Quote names with spaces: `"Total Revenue"`

#### Operators
- Addition: `+`
- Subtraction: `-`
- Multiplication: `*`
- Division: `/`
- Exponentiation: `^`
- Parentheses for grouping: `(Revenue - Costs) * 100`

#### Constants
- Numbers: `100`, `3.14`, `-5`
- Negative values: `-100` or `0 - 100`

#### Period Offsets
- Previous period: `Revenue[-1]`
- Two periods back: `Revenue[-2]`
- Useful for growth calculations: `Revenue - Revenue[-1]`

#### Period References
The `Periods` keyword returns the current period's end date as a date value. This is useful for creating timing flexibility, e.g. `Is Live = Periods > Launch Date`

Key points:
- Returns the **end date** of the period (e.g., 31 Dec for a Calendar Year)
- Supports offsets: `Periods[-1]` returns the previous period's end date
- Compare against date-type Assumption Variables (Variables with date values)

Financial modeling best practice with Periods:
- When flexible timing is required use Variables with DateType `Date` (Model periods don't have a time component)
- It is always best to create a `Boolean` Variable for a timing condition (e.g. `Service is live`) and then to multiply that by the relevant Variable, rather than perform both timing logic and calculation in a single Variable

#### Functions
- Standard functions: `SUM(...)`, `MAX(...)`, `MIN(...)`, `IF(...)`
- Example: `IF(Revenue > 0, Profit / Revenue, 0)`

### Examples

**Simple calculation:**
```json
{
  "defaultCalculation": {
    "formulaText": "Revenue - Costs"
  }
}
```

**With period offset (growth calculation):**
```json
{
  "defaultCalculation": {
    "formulaText": "Revenue - Revenue[-1]"
  }
}
```

**With parentheses and constants:**
```json
{
  "defaultCalculation": {
    "formulaText": "(Revenue - Costs) / Revenue * 100"
  }
}
```

**With quoted variable names:**
```json
{
  "defaultCalculation": {
    "formulaText": "\"Net Revenue\" - \"Operating Costs\""
  }
}
```

**With period reference (date comparison):**
```json
{
  "defaultCalculation": {
    "formulaText": "Periods > \"Launch Date\""
  }
}
```

### Precedence Rules

- If both `formulaText` and `calculationParts` are provided, `calculationParts` takes precedence
- `formulaText` is converted to `calculationParts` before the Variable is created/updated
- The API response includes `formulaText` generated from the stored `calculationParts`

### Error Handling

Parse errors return structured error messages with:
- Position in the formula where the error occurred
- What was found vs. what was expected
- Hints for resolution (e.g., "Variable 'Unknown' not found in Model")

## Aggregation Variables

### Critical Understanding: Aggregation is NOT Summing

**Common Misconception**: Aggregation Variables "sum" other Variables.

**Reality**: Aggregation Variables **collect** Variables that each represent a part of a Dimension into a Variable of that Dimension.

### Example: Regional Revenues

Suppose you have:
- **Revenues-South**: Calculation Variable for southern region revenues
- **Revenues-North**: Calculation Variable for northern region revenues
- Both are Concrete Tags under the "Region" Abstract Tag (Dimension)

You can create:
- **Revenues by Region**: Aggregation Variable that collects Revenues-South and Revenues-North

The Aggregation Variable expands to show:
- Revenues by Region (South) = Revenues-South
- Revenues by Region (North) = Revenues-North

Each region may calculate revenues differently, but the Aggregation Variable provides a unified Dimension-level view.

### When to Use Aggregation

- When you have Variables representing Dimension parts (e.g., regions, products, markets)
- When you want a Dimension-level Variable that combines these parts
- When each part may have different calculation logic

### Property: `aggregatedVariableIds`

- **Type**: `array[string]` - Array of Variable IDs
- **Relevant When**: `defaultFormulaType` is `Aggregation`
- **Purpose**: Lists the Variables representing Dimension parts to collect
- **Note**: These Variables must represent parts of the same Dimension(s) that the Aggregation Variable uses

## contextVarianceMap

### Purpose

The `contextVarianceMap` defines which unit parts vary with which Dimensions. This is critical for Variables with both:
- **Dimensions** (via `tagParents`)
- **Defined units** (via `unitOption: Defined`)

### When It's Relevant

- Variable has `unitOption: Defined` (not Inferred)
- Variable has Dimensions (via `tagParents` with at least one parent)
- **Both conditions must be true**

### Structure

The map is a dictionary where:
- **Key**: Unit part ID (e.g., "GBP", "Member", "Month")
- **Value**: Set of Dimension (TagParent) IDs that this unit part varies with

### Example

Suppose a Variable has:
- Unit: "GBP per Member per Month" (with UnitPart IDs: `up-gbp-123`, `up-member-456`, `up-month-789`)
- Dimensions: "Region" (Tag ID: `tag-region-abc`) and "Product" (Tag ID: `tag-product-def`)

The default `contextVarianceMap` would be:
```json
{
  "up-gbp-123": ["tag-region-abc", "tag-product-def"],
  "up-member-456": ["tag-region-abc", "tag-product-def"],
  "up-month-789": ["tag-region-abc", "tag-product-def"]
}
```

**Important**: The map uses actual object IDs, not human-readable names:
- **Keys**: UnitPart IDs from the Variable's Unit (use `get-details` on the Unit to find these)
- **Values**: Tag IDs of the Dimensions from `tagParents` (Abstract Tag IDs)

This means all unit parts vary with all Dimensions (the default).

### Custom contextVarianceMap

You only need to provide a custom `contextVarianceMap` when:
- You want specific unit parts to vary with specific Dimensions only
- The default "all vary with all" doesn't match your requirements

**Important**: Each Dimension must vary with at least one unit part. Otherwise, there wouldn't be variance for that Dimension.

### Property: `contextVarianceMap`

- **Type**: `object` (dictionary mapping unit part IDs to Dimension ID sets)
- **Relevant When**: `unitOption` is `Defined` AND Variable has Dimensions
- **Default**: Automatically generated as "all Dimensions vary with all unit parts"
- **Rarely Required**: Most Variables use the default map

## groupSummaryType

### Purpose

Controls how a Variable summarizes across all Dimensions when creating summary lines.

### Values

#### `None`
- No automatic summary behavior
- Variable appears only at the detailed Dimension level

#### `Sum`
- Always performs a simple sum across all Dimension items
- Example: If you have Revenues by Region (South, North), Sum gives Total Revenues = South + North

#### `Auto`
- Performs the Variable's calculation on the summary lines of referenced Variables
- Useful when the result differs from a simple sum
- **Example**: Weighted average price
  - If Price = Revenue / Volume
  - Auto calculates: Total Price = Total Revenue / Total Volume
  - This is different from averaging individual prices

#### `Rearranged`
- Similar to Auto, but requires a parent Variable reference
- Used when the summary calculation can only be computed from parent Variables
- **Example**: Average price when Price is an input (not calculated)
  - If Price is an input Variable (not Revenue/Volume)
  - You need to rearrange: Price = Revenue / Volume
  - But Revenue and Volume are parent Variables
  - Rearranged uses `groupSummaryRearrangedParentId` to reference the parent for calculation

### When to Use Each

| Use Case | groupSummaryType | Notes |
|----------|------------------|-------|
| Simple totals | `Sum` | Direct sum of all Dimension items |
| Calculated metrics | `Auto` | Recalculate formula on summary lines |
| Input-based metrics | `Rearranged` | Calculate from parent Variables |

### Property: `groupSummaryType`

- **Type**: `enum` - `None`, `Sum`, `Auto`, `Rearranged`
- **Default**: `None`
- **Purpose**: Controls Dimension summary behavior

### Property: `groupSummaryRearrangedParentId`

- **Type**: `string` - Variable ID
- **Required When**: `groupSummaryType` is `Rearranged`
- **Purpose**: References the parent Variable to base the Rearranged summary calculation on
- **Example**: For weighted averages requiring parent data

## Unit System

### Defined vs Inferred

#### `unitOption: Defined`
- Unit is explicitly set via the `unit` property
- Used for Assumption and Aggregation Variables (default)
- Can also be used for Calculation Variables

#### `unitOption: Inferred`
- Unit is automatically calculated from the formula
- Only available for Calculation Variables
- Based on the Variables referenced in the calculation
- If unit cannot be calculated, a unit error is shown

### Unit Factoring (`applyFactoring`)

**Purpose**: Automatically adjusts calculations when the Variable's unit factor differs from the calculated unit factor.

**How It Works**:
- Factoring is done automatically based on units
- Only works if `unitOption` is `Defined`
- The Variable's unit must have a different factor from the calculated unit
- Example: Variable has unit in millions (factorPower 6/1), but calculation returns thousands (factorPower 3/1)
- Setting `applyFactoring: true` automatically adjusts the calculation (divides by 10^3)

**Property**: `applyFactoring`
- **Type**: `boolean`
- **Default**: `false`
- **Purpose**: Auto-adjust when Variable unit factor differs from calculated unit factor
- **Note**: User doesn't need to multiply or divide within the Variable's calculation

### Unit Validation

- Automatic unit compatibility checking across Variable references
- Unit inconsistencies generate warnings, not errors - calculations still execute
- `overrideUnitError: true` allows bypassing unit validation when needed

**When to use `overrideUnitError`:**
- The calculated unit doesn't match the Defined unit, but the result is semantically correct
- Example: `Balance[-1] × Timeless` infers as `Balance[-1]`, but you know it should be `Flow`
- Always set `overrideUnitError: true` at the same time as setting the Defined unit — don't set the Defined unit first and then override in a separate step

**When to use a compound unit instead:**
- When a rate converts between TimeTypes (e.g., stock to flow), give it a compound unit
- Example: Churn Rate = `Member [Flow] / Member [Balance[-1]]` — then `Members[-1] × Churn Rate` resolves to `Member [Flow]` without needing an override
- Compound units are preferred over overrides because they make the algebra self-documenting

## NumberFormat Selection

The `numberFormatId` property controls how Variable values are displayed. Always set an appropriate format.

### Common Inbuilt Format IDs

| ID | Format | Use For |
|----|--------|---------|
| `General` | General | Boolean, Validation, String |
| `ThousandSeparator0Dp` | #,##0 | Standard integers (default) |
| `TwoDecimalPlaces` | 0.00 | Decimals without thousands separator |
| `Pct1Dp` | 0.0% | Percentages (growth, rate, margin, yield) |
| `Date1` | dd mmm yy | Date values |
| `GBP2Dp` | £#,##0.00 | GBP currency |
| `USD2Dp` | $#,##0.00 | USD currency |
| `EUR2Dp` | €#,##0.00 | EUR currency |

Use `Pct1Dp` when Variable name contains: %, pct, percentage, growth, rate, inflation, margin, yield.

If the required format isn't listed above, use `filter` to find other available formats, or `create` to add a new one.

## TimeSegments

### Purpose

Allow Variables to change formula behavior across different time periods.

### Types of TimeSegments

#### Assumption TimeSegments
- Provide values from ModelAssumption objects for specific periods/dimensions
- Can override the default assumption for specific time ranges

#### Calculation TimeSegments
- Provide different calculation formulas for specific time periods
- **Critical Constraint**: Calculation formulas within TimeSegments can only reference the same Variable with period offsets (e.g., `[-1]` for previous period)
- They cannot reference other Variables to prevent circular dependencies

### SegmentPeriod Types

Each TimeSegment has a `start` and optionally an `end`, each defined by a SegmentPeriod. Available types:

- **Auto** — automatically determined from adjacent segments
- **FixedPeriod** — a specific date code (requires `fixedPeriodDateCode`)
- **PeriodsFromStartGeneric** — Nth period from model start (requires `genericPeriodsFromStart`, 1-indexed)
- **PeriodsFromEndGeneric** — Nth period from model end (requires `genericPeriodsFromEnd`, 1-indexed)
- **RelativeToActuals** — offset from the last Actuals period (requires `lastActualsOffset`)
  - `0` = last period of Actuals
  - `+1` = 1st period of Forecast
  - `-1` = 2nd-to-last period of Actuals
  - Requires `lastActualsPeriodId` to be set on model Timings; if unset, resolution returns null

Use `help` with `objectType: "SegmentPeriod"` for full schema details.

### Creating Assumptions Inline with TimeSegments

When creating a Variable with Assumption TimeSegments, you can provide assumption values directly as a 2D grid. This eliminates the need to create ModelAssumption objects separately.

#### Grid Convention

- **Columns**: Time periods (chronological order, determined by TimeSegment's date range)
- **Rows**: Dimension cross-product (if Variable has dimensions via `tagParents`)
- **Empty/null values**: Skip (no assumption created for that cell)

#### Example: Simple Time Series (No Dimensions)

```json
{
  "name": "Growth Rate",
  "defaultFormulaType": "Assumptions",
  "timeSegments": [{
    "start": { "segmentPeriodType": "Auto" },
    "duration": { "segmentDurationType": "PeriodsGeneric", "genericPeriods": 6 },
    "assumptions": {
      "values": [
        ["0.05", "0.06", "0.07", "0.08", "0.09", "0.10"]
      ]
    }
  }]
}
```

The Variable's name ("Growth Rate") is automatically used as the assumption prefix.

#### Example: Dimensional Variable (Region Dimension)

For a Variable with Region dimension (North, South) and 3 time periods:

```json
{
  "name": "Sales Growth",
  "defaultFormulaType": "Assumptions",
  "tagParents": { "parents": [{ "tagId": "-regionDimensionId" }] },
  "timeSegments": [{
    "start": { "segmentPeriodType": "Auto" },
    "duration": { "segmentDurationType": "PeriodsGeneric", "genericPeriods": 3 },
    "assumptions": {
      "values": [
        ["0.05", "0.06", "0.07"],
        ["0.04", "0.05", "0.06"]
      ]
    }
  }]
}
```

Row order is deterministic (ordered by TagGroupWithParents.OrderedId). Use `expand-dimensions` action to discover the exact grid shape.

#### Grid Shape Discovery

Before providing values, you can use the `expand-dimensions` action to discover the expected grid shape:

```json
{
  "objectType": "Variable",
  "action": "expand-dimensions",
  "id": "var-123",
  "timeSegmentIndex": 0
}
```

Returns:
```json
{
  "columns": ["2021", "2022", "2023"],
  "rows": ["North", "South"],
  "shape": [2, 3]
}
```

This tells you:
- The Variable expects a 2×3 grid
- Rows are "North" then "South" (dimension cross-product)
- Columns are "2021", "2022", "2023" (time periods)

#### How It Works

When you provide an `assumptions` object on a TimeSegment:
1. The TimeSegment's formula type is automatically set to `Assumptions`
2. After the Variable is created, ModelAssumption objects are generated from the grid
3. Each grid cell creates one assumption with the correct Unit (including time and dimension modifiers)
4. Assumptions are linked to the TimeSegment's formula
5. Values use the Base Scenario by default

#### When to Use

- **Creating new Variables with Assumption TimeSegments**: Simplest approach
- **Simple time series**: Just need to provide values across periods
- **Dimensional assumptions**: Values vary by dimension and time

#### When NOT to Use

- **Updating existing assumptions**: Use direct ModelAssumption updates instead
- **Multi-scenario values**: Use standard ModelAssumption creation with explicit values per scenario
- **Complex sensitivity setups**: Create ModelAssumptions directly with sensitivity configuration

### defaultAssumptionId

**Purpose**: Fallback assumption for any period/dimensions in a TimeSegment that doesn't have a matching assumption.

**When Used**:
- Very rarely in practice
- Typically, all assumption IDs are provided within TimeSegments
- Example: If you want the Variable to have the value 0 except for periods that you provide a value for

**Property**: `defaultAssumptionId`
- **Type**: `string` - ModelAssumption ID
- **Available For**: All formula types (even Calculation Variables can have Assumption TimeSegments)
- **Purpose**: Fallback assumption for periods/dimensions without matching TimeSegment assumption

### TimeSegment Coverage

TimeSegments must collectively cover all periods without gaps or overlaps.

## periodType

### Purpose

Overrides the Model's default period for this specific Variable.

### Rules

- Must be set to a broader time interval than the Model timings
- Example: If Model is in weeks, you can define a Variable in months
- `None` means "use the Model's default period"

### Property: `periodType`

- **Type**: `enum` - `None`, `Day`, `Week`, `Month`, `Quarter`, `YearCalendar`, `YearFiscal`
- **Default**: `None` (use Model default)
- **Purpose**: Override Model's default period for this Variable

## validationDimensionId

### Purpose

Defines dropdown options for Validation-type Variables.

### How It Works

- Variable must have `dataType: Validation`
- `validationDimensionId` references an Abstract Tag (Dimension)
- The Concrete Tag children of that Abstract Tag become the dropdown options
- Example: "Yes/No" Dimension with Concrete children "Yes" and "No"

### Property: `validationDimensionId`

- **Type**: `string` - Abstract Tag ID
- **Required When**: `dataType` is `Validation`
- **Purpose**: Abstract Tag defining dropdown options for Validation-type Variables

## Common Patterns and Pitfalls

### Pattern 1: Dimensional Aggregation

**Scenario**: You have revenue calculations for each region, and want a total revenue Variable.

**Correct Approach**:
1. Create Calculation Variables: "Revenues-South", "Revenues-North" (each with Region Dimension)
2. Create Aggregation Variable: "Total Revenues" with `aggregatedVariableIds: ["Revenues-South", "Revenues-North"]`
3. Set `groupSummaryType: Sum` if you want summary lines

**Incorrect**: Trying to sum the Variables in a Calculation formula - use Aggregation instead.

### Pattern 2: Unit Factoring

**Scenario**: Your Model works in thousands, but you want to display a Variable in millions.

**Correct Approach**:
1. Set Variable unit to millions (factorPower 6/1)
2. Ensure calculation returns thousands (factorPower 3/1)
3. Set `applyFactoring: true`
4. System automatically adjusts (divides by 10^3)

**Incorrect**: Manually dividing in the calculation formula.

### Pattern 3: Weighted Averages

**Scenario**: You want average price across all products.

**If Price is Calculated** (Price = Revenue / Volume):
- Use `groupSummaryType: Auto`
- System recalculates: Total Price = Total Revenue / Total Volume

**If Price is an Input**:
- Use `groupSummaryType: Rearranged`
- Set `groupSummaryRearrangedParentId` to reference Revenue or Volume parent
- System rearranges calculation from parent Variables

### Pitfall 1: Confusing Aggregation with Summing

**Mistake**: Thinking `aggregatedVariableIds` creates a sum.

**Reality**: Aggregation collects Dimension parts, not sums values.

### Pitfall 2: Missing contextVarianceMap Condition

**Mistake**: Providing `contextVarianceMap` when Variable has no Dimensions.

**Reality**: `contextVarianceMap` is only relevant when Variable has both Dimensions AND Defined unit.

### Pitfall 3: Wrong groupSummaryType

**Mistake**: Using `Sum` for calculated metrics that need recalculation.

**Reality**: Use `Auto` or `Rearranged` when the summary result differs from a simple sum.

### Pitfall 4: Self-Referencing Variable with Inferred Unit

**Mistake**: Creating a Calculation Variable that references itself with a period offset (e.g., `Balance[-1] + Inflow`) and leaving `unitOption: Inferred`.

**Reality**: Self-referencing Variables require `unitOption: Defined`. The Unit system cannot resolve self-references to determine the inferred type. Always define the Unit explicitly with the appropriate TimeType (typically Balance for accumulator patterns).

## Best Practices

1. **Use Aggregation for Dimension-based collection**, not for simple summing
2. **Rely on default contextVarianceMap** unless you have specific requirements
3. **Use Auto for calculated metrics** that need recalculation on summary lines
4. **Use Rearranged only when necessary** - when calculation requires parent Variables
5. **Set applyFactoring when unit factors differ** - don't manually adjust in formulas
6. **Use defaultAssumptionId sparingly** - prefer explicit TimeSegment assumptions
7. **Validate periodType compatibility** - must be broader than Model timings

## Retrieving Calculated Values

### get-values Operation

Retrieve calculated values for one or more Variables:

```
QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='get-values', parameters={
  'ids': ['var-1', 'var-2'],
  'periods': 'sample',        # 'all', 'first', 'last', 'first-N', 'last-N', 'sample', or specific periods
  'dimensions': 'summary',    # 'summary', 'all', or specific paths like 'UK/Small'
  'case': 'Base/Base',        # Scenario/Sensitivity
  'includeAnalysis': true     # Adds trend, min/max, growth rate
})
```

**Key considerations**:
- Use `periods: 'sample'` for a quick snapshot (first, middle, last)
- Use `dimensions: 'summary'` unless you need individual dimension values
- The `includeAnalysis` option adds trend classification and growth rate

### compare-cases Operation

Compare values between two cases (Scenario/Sensitivity combinations):

```
QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='compare-cases', parameters={
  'ids': ['profit'],
  'baseCase': 'Base/Base',      # Required: baseline for comparison
  'compareCase': 'Lean/Base',   # Required: case to compare against baseline
  'periods': 'last'
})
```

Returns values with variance from baseline (absolute and percentage difference).

### trace-dependencies with Values

Add `includeValues: true` to see values alongside the dependency tree:

```
ModelAction(action='trace-dependencies', variableId='profit', includeValues=true, valuePeriod='last')
```

### valueSummary in Filter

Add `valueSummary` to filter properties to see first/last values and trend:

```
QueryObject(object_type='Variable', action='filter', parameters={
  'properties': ['name', 'valueSummary']
})
```

Returns `valueSummary: { first: { period, value }, last: { period, value }, trend: 'growing' }` for each Variable.

[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"filter","description":"Filter Variable objects based on their properties","object_type":"Variable","operators":{"$and":{"description":"Matches objects where all conditions are true (explicit AND for nesting)","syntax":{"$and":[{"property1":"value1"},{"property2":"value2"}]}},"$not":{"description":"Inverts a condition","syntax":{"$not":{"property":"value"}}},"$or":{"description":"Matches objects where at least one condition is true","syntax":{"$or":[{"property1":"value1"},{"property2":"value2"}]}},"note":"Top-level properties are implicitly ANDed. Operators can be nested for complex queries."},"options":{"includeValueSummary":{"default":false,"description":"Include first/last period values and trend indicator for each result.","type":"boolean"}},"pagination":{"limit":{"default":"Set by session (typically 50)","description":"Maximum number of results to return. A truncation warning is included when results exceed this limit.","type":"integer"},"skip":{"default":0,"description":"Number of results to skip (for pagination).","type":"integer"}},"parameters":{"allAssumptionsAreInLayout":{"type":"boolean"},"dataType":{"type":"enum","values":["Double","Integer","String","DateTime","Date","Boolean","Validation","List","NotApplicable"]},"hasError":{"type":"boolean"},"hasSummary":{"type":"boolean"},"hasTagParents":{"type":"boolean"},"id":{"type":"string"},"isConstant":{"type":"boolean"},"isInLayout":{"type":"boolean"},"name":{"type":"string"},"numberFormatId":{"type":"string"},"periodType":{"type":"enum","values":["None","Day","Week","Month","Quarter","YearCalendar","YearFiscal"]},"unitDescription":{"type":"string"},"unitOption":{"type":"enum","values":["Defined","Inferred"]}},"pattern_guide":{"boolean":["true/false"],"enum":["exact (case-insensitive)"],"string":["exact","glob (*?)","regex (/pattern/)"]}}
[ASSISTANT]: Next I’m pulling the exact details for the three relevant Variables so I can see current time segments, units, and any existing formula structure before proposing the interpolation design.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Find endpoint forecast variable", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","limit":10,"name":"*End point*forecast % takeup of device*"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Find endpoint takeup assumption", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","limit":10,"name":"*End point*forecast end year % takeup*"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Find historic takeup variable", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","limit":10,"name":"*% takeup of device (historic) - 15+*"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":1,"variables":[{"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yhph","isConstant":"False","name":"\"End point\" forecast % takeup of device","numberFormat":"0.0%","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2020`: No values required for these periods; `2021 - 2035`: Auto","unit":"Undefined"}]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":1,"variables":[{"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2y_1e","isConstant":"True","name":"\"End point\" forecast end year % takeup","numberFormat":"#,##0%","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: 72 assumptions","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":1,"variables":[{"calculation":"Device takeup * Population [Sum of Radio Age-Group | Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)]","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","id":"-Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiI7t","isConstant":"False","name":"% takeup of device (historic) - 15+","numberFormat":"#,##0%","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: Auto","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[THINKING]: **Tracing relevant variables**

I’m thinking about gathering details on the relevant variables and possibly tracing their dependencies and values. The current model summary seems sufficient for now. I’ll use the get-details function to focus on properties like tagParents, timeSegments, defaultCalculation, dataType, and unitOption. For the assumptions, I’m also considering the defaultAssumption. Alright, it’s time to proceed with that!
[ASSISTANT]: I’ve identified the three Variables. Now I’m checking their full structure and a few sample values so the interpolation logic matches the model’s dimensions and timing.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Inspect forecast calc variable", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yhph","properties":["name","dataType","unitOption","unit","tagParents","defaultCalculation","timeSegments","numberFormatId","isConstant"]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Inspect forecast end year pct", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2y_1e","properties":["name","dataType","unitOption","unit","tagParents","timeSegments","numberFormatId","isConstant"]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Inspect historic takeup variable", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiI7t","properties":["name","dataType","unitOption","unit","tagParents","defaultCalculation","timeSegments","numberFormatId","isConstant"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"calculationParts":{"count":0,"items":[]},"description":"","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yj36","isValid":false,"isWellFormed":false},"isConstant":false,"name":"\"End point\" forecast % takeup of device","numberFormatId":"Pct1Dp","tagParents":{"parents":{"count":2,"items":["{Radio Age-Group...}","{Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)...}"]}},"timeSegments":[{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Last period of Actuals...}","endPeriodDescription":"Last period of Actuals (2020)","formula":"{NotApplicable: No values required for these periods...}","formulaDescription":"No values required for these periods","hasError":false,"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yj8l","modelFormulaType":"NotApplicable","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Start"},{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Auto...}","endPeriodDescription":"End","formula":"{Auto: ...}","formulaDescription":"","hasError":false,"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yj30","modelFormulaType":"Auto","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Auto (2021)"}],"unit":{"description":"Undefined","factorPower":"0","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yjp9","isUndefined":true,"isUnitless":true,"modifiersDescription":"","timeTypeDescription":"","unitParts":{"count":0,"items":[]}},"unitOption":"Inferred"}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"dataType":"Double","isConstant":true,"name":"\"End point\" forecast end year % takeup","numberFormatId":"-PdjtMVve_uilkRXsJ0O","tagParents":{"parents":{"count":2,"items":["{Radio Age-Group...}","{Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)...}"]}},"timeSegments":[{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Auto...}","endPeriodDescription":"End","formula":"{Assumptions: 72 assumptions...}","formulaDescription":"72 assumptions","hasError":false,"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2y_xW","modelFormulaType":"Assumptions","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Start"}],"unit":{"description":"Unitless [Timeless]","factorPower":"0","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2y_x7","isUndefined":false,"isUnitless":true,"modifiersDescription":"","timeTypeDescription":"Timeless","unitParts":{"count":1,"items":["{Unitless...}"]}},"unitOption":"Defined"}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"calculationParts":{"count":1,"items":["{Device takeup * Population [Sum of Radio Age-Group | Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)]...}"]},"description":"Device takeup * Population [Sum of Radio Age-Group | Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)]","id":"-Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiKP6","isValid":true,"isWellFormed":true,"unit":"{...}"},"isConstant":false,"name":"% takeup of device (historic) - 15+","numberFormatId":"-PdjtMVve_uilkRXsJ0O","tagParents":{"parents":{"count":1,"items":["{Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)...}"]}},"timeSegments":[{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Auto...}","endPeriodDescription":"End","formula":"{Auto: ...}","formulaDescription":"","hasError":false,"id":"-Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiKP0","modelFormulaType":"Auto","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Start"}],"unit":{"description":"Unitless [Timeless]","factorPower":"0","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yjop","isUndefined":false,"isUnitless":true,"modifiersDescription":"","timeTypeDescription":"Timeless","unitParts":{"count":1,"items":["{Unitless...}"]}},"unitOption":"Inferred"}}
[THINKING]: **Investigating end year assumptions**

Alright, I need to figure out if there's an assumption regarding the end year. I’m looking at phrases like "Uses end point forecast" and "End point forecast end year." I'll inspect these elements to understand their context better, as they could give me insights into the time frame or assumptions being made. I'll keep digging to clarify and ensure I’m interpreting everything correctly!
[ASSISTANT]: I can already see one important structural issue: the forecast Variable has **two dimensions** while the historic Variable only has **Device type**. I’m checking the supporting timing assumptions now, because that affects whether we can do the interpolation directly or need helper Variables.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Find forecast toggle variable", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","limit":10,"name":"*Uses*end point*forecast*"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Find forecast end year variable", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","limit":10,"name":"*End point*forecast end year"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":1,"variables":[{"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiOPY","isConstant":"True","name":"Uses \"end point\" forecast","numberFormat":"General","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: 18 assumptions","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":1,"variables":[{"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yW7J","isConstant":"True","name":"\"End point\" forecast end year","numberFormat":"General","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: 1 assumption","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[ASSISTANT]: I’ve found the timing controls too. One more step: I’m checking sample values and whether the formula engine supports period/date helpers we can use cleanly, so I can recommend a robust implementation rather than a brittle one.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Sample historic values", object_type="Variable", otherAction="get-values", parameters={"case":"Base/Base","dimensions":"all","format":"structured","ids":["-Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiI7t"],"includeAnalysis":false,"periods":"last-5"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Sample endpoint values", object_type="Variable", otherAction="get-values", parameters={"case":"Base/Base","dimensions":"all","format":"structured","ids":["-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2y_1e"],"includeAnalysis":false,"periods":"last"})
[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="help", explanation="Check model action help", parameters={"format":"compact","help":true,"model_id":""})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"case":"Base/Base","periodsReturned":["2031","2032","2033","2034","2035"],"variables":[{"dimensions":[{"path":"Desktop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Laptop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Tablet","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Digital music player","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Smartphone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Standard mobile phone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Any TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Smart TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Wearable technology","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Voice activated speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Car: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Car: Connected car","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Home: Any radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Home: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"Home: Internet radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}}],"id":"-Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiI7t","name":"% takeup of device (historic) - 15+","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"case":"Base/Base","periodsReturned":["2035"],"variables":[{"dimensions":[{"path":"15-24/Desktop computer","values":{"2035":"20%"}},{"path":"15-24/Laptop computer","values":{"2035":"93%"}},{"path":"15-24/Tablet","values":{"2035":"55%"}},{"path":"15-24/Digital music player","values":{"2035":"10%"}},{"path":"15-24/Smartphone","values":{"2035":"98%"}},{"path":"15-24/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2035":"1%"}},{"path":"15-24/Any TV","values":{"2035":"95%"}},{"path":"15-24/Smart TV","values":{"2035":"90%"}},{"path":"15-24/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Wearable technology","values":{"2035":"40%"}},{"path":"15-24/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2035":"77%"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: Connected car","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Any radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Desktop computer","values":{"2035":"25%"}},{"path":"25-34/Laptop computer","values":{"2035":"85%"}},{"path":"25-34/Tablet","values":{"2035":"65%"}},{"path":"25-34/Digital music player","values":{"2035":"20%"}},{"path":"25-34/Smartphone","values":{"2035":"95%"}},{"path":"25-34/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2035":"1%"}},{"path":"25-34/Any TV","values":{"2035":"94%"}},{"path":"25-34/Smart TV","values":{"2035":"93%"}},{"path":"25-34/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Wearable technology","values":{"2035":"45%"}},{"path":"25-34/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2035":"77%"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: Connected car","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Any radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Desktop computer","values":{"2035":"30%"}},{"path":"35-54/Laptop computer","values":{"2035":"80%"}},{"path":"35-54/Tablet","values":{"2035":"70%"}},{"path":"35-54/Digital music player","values":{"2035":"20%"}},{"path":"35-54/Smartphone","values":{"2035":"93%"}},{"path":"35-54/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2035":"2%"}},{"path":"35-54/Any TV","values":{"2035":"96%"}},{"path":"35-54/Smart TV","values":{"2035":"95%"}},{"path":"35-54/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Wearable technology","values":{"2035":"45%"}},{"path":"35-54/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2035":"77%"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: Connected car","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Any radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"55+/Desktop computer","values":{"2035":"35%"}},{"path":"55+/Laptop computer","values":{"2035":"55%"}},{"path":"55+/Tablet","values":{"2035":"60%"}},{"path":"55+/Digital music player","values":{"2035":"15%"}},{"path":"55+/Smartphone","values":{"2035":"80%"}},{"path":"55+/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2035":"10%"}},{"path":"55+/Any TV","values":{"2035":"98%"}},{"path":"55+/Smart TV","values":{"2035":"85%"}},{"path":"55+/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Wearable technology","values":{"2035":"35%"}},{"path":"55+/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"55+/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2035":"77%"}},{"path":"55+/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Car: Connected car","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Any radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2035":"0%"}}],"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2y_1e","name":"\"End point\" forecast end year % takeup","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"details":"API error UNEXPECTED_ERROR: Model operation 'help' not found","error":"Failed to retrieve model operation help from API"}
[USER]: Sorry, I pointed you to the wrong historic Variable. We're interested in the `% takeup of device (historic)`, not the 15+ aggregated version.
[THINKING]: **Determining calculations and variables**

I need to help the user by establishing a working calculation and identifying any additional variables needed. We have a preset context to work from, so my next step is to inspect the correct variables. It's also essential to maintain progress updates throughout this process. I'll likely use a QueryObject filter to assist with what’s already been done. This includes ensuring that values and dimensions match correctly. It's all about utilizing the tools effectively!
[ASSISTANT]: Thanks — that makes more sense. I’ll inspect the correct historic Variable now and then I’ll lay out the interpolation pattern using the actual dimension structure.
[USER]: Ok
[THINKING]: **Examining forecast periods**

I need to gather details on key periods, especially around 2020 and 2035, and check the "End point forecast end year" value. This assumption seems constant across dimensions and periods, likely set at 2035. I should explore the formula possibilities, especially regarding how to use periods and quoted variable names. Maybe creating helper variables to anchor from the endpoint backward could help avoid referencing future periods. I’ll need to think this through carefully!**Clarifying variable calculations**

I need to tackle the challenge of not referencing future periods in my calculations. I should find a working calculation and consider suggesting additional variables if needed. It’s also essential to inspect the correct historic variable dimensions, which are likely the same two dimensions. I might look into the existing variable "Uses end point forecast," possibly a boolean by device. Since the user is specifically asking for the formula for this variable, I’ll inspect that closely without integrating it into the overall output.
[ASSISTANT]: I’m checking the correct historic Variable and a couple of sample values so I can align the interpolation to the actual dimensionality and timing.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Find correct historic variable", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","limit":20,"name":"*% takeup of device (historic)*"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Inspect forecast end year var", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yW7J","properties":["name","dataType","timeSegments","isConstant"]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Inspect forecast toggle var", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiOPY","properties":["name","dataType","tagParents","timeSegments","isConstant"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":2,"variables":[{"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEiHF","isConstant":"False","name":"% takeup of device (historic)","numberFormat":"0.0%","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2020`: 360 assumptions; `2021 - 2035`: No values required for these periods","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"},{"calculation":"Device takeup * Population [Sum of Radio Age-Group | Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)]","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","id":"-Pdo38V0Wv0gRNwfiI7t","isConstant":"False","name":"% takeup of device (historic) - 15+","numberFormat":"#,##0%","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: Auto","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"dataType":"Integer","isConstant":true,"name":"\"End point\" forecast end year","timeSegments":[{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Auto...}","endPeriodDescription":"End","formula":"{Assumptions: 1 assumption...}","formulaDescription":"1 assumption","hasError":false,"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yX__","modelFormulaType":"Assumptions","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Start"}]}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"dataType":"Boolean","isConstant":true,"name":"Uses \"end point\" forecast","tagParents":{"parents":{"count":1,"items":["{Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)...}"]}},"timeSegments":[{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Auto...}","endPeriodDescription":"End","formula":"{Assumptions: 18 assumptions...}","formulaDescription":"18 assumptions","hasError":false,"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yS_e","modelFormulaType":"Assumptions","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Start"}]}}
[ASSISTANT]: Great — now I have the right historic input. I’m pulling its full details and some values alongside the forecast Variable so I can design the interpolation cleanly.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Inspect correct historic var", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEiHF","properties":["name","dataType","unitOption","unit","tagParents","timeSegments","numberFormatId","isConstant"]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Sample historic values", object_type="Variable", otherAction="get-values", parameters={"case":"Base/Base","dimensions":"all","format":"structured","ids":["-Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEiHF"],"includeAnalysis":false,"periods":"last-5"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Sample historic last actuals", object_type="Variable", otherAction="get-values", parameters={"case":"Base/Base","dimensions":"all","format":"structured","ids":["-Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEiHF"],"includeAnalysis":false,"periods":"2020"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"dataType":"Double","isConstant":false,"name":"% takeup of device (historic)","numberFormatId":"Pct1Dp","tagParents":{"parents":{"count":2,"items":["{Radio Age-Group...}","{Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)...}"]}},"timeSegments":[{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Last period of Actuals...}","endPeriodDescription":"Last period of Actuals (2020)","formula":"{Assumptions: 360 assumptions...}","formulaDescription":"360 assumptions","hasError":false,"id":"-PdjgP9oVsm2mHq67JOP","modelFormulaType":"Assumptions","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Start"},{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Auto...}","endPeriodDescription":"End","formula":"{NotApplicable: No values required for these periods...}","formulaDescription":"No values required for these periods","hasError":false,"id":"-PdjgP9oVsm2mHq67JH-","modelFormulaType":"NotApplicable","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Auto (2021)"}],"unit":{"description":"Unitless [Timeless]","factorPower":"0","id":"-PdjgP9oVsm2mHq67JFZ","isUndefined":false,"isUnitless":true,"modifiersDescription":"","timeTypeDescription":"Timeless","unitParts":{"count":1,"items":["{Unitless...}"]}},"unitOption":"Defined"}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"case":"Base/Base","periodsReturned":["2031","2032","2033","2034","2035"],"variables":[{"dimensions":[{"path":"15-24/Desktop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Laptop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Tablet","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Digital music player","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Smartphone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Any TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Smart TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Wearable technology","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: Connected car","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Any radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Desktop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Laptop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Tablet","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Digital music player","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Smartphone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Any TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Smart TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Wearable technology","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: Connected car","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Any radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Desktop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Laptop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Tablet","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Digital music player","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Smartphone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Any TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Smart TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Wearable technology","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: Connected car","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Any radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Desktop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Laptop computer","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Tablet","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Digital music player","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Smartphone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Any TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Smart TV","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Wearable technology","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Car: Connected car","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Any radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2031":"N/A","2032":"N/A","2033":"N/A","2034":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}}],"id":"-Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEiHF","name":"% takeup of device (historic)","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"case":"Base/Base","periodsReturned":["2020"],"variables":[{"dimensions":[{"path":"15-24/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"52.4%"}},{"path":"15-24/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"91.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Tablet","values":{"2020":"60.3%"}},{"path":"15-24/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"22.7%"}},{"path":"15-24/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"96.4%"}},{"path":"15-24/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"2.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Any TV","values":{"2020":"97.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"73.8%"}},{"path":"15-24/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"33.8%"}},{"path":"15-24/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"40.3%"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"41.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"50.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"43.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"27.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"0.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"48.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"91.7%"}},{"path":"25-34/Tablet","values":{"2020":"65.2%"}},{"path":"25-34/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"34.6%"}},{"path":"25-34/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"92.2%"}},{"path":"25-34/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"1.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Any TV","values":{"2020":"96.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"73.8%"}},{"path":"25-34/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"42.6%"}},{"path":"25-34/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"41.5%"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"40.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"49.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"42.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"29.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"0.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"50.3%"}},{"path":"35-54/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"85.6%"}},{"path":"35-54/Tablet","values":{"2020":"75.4%"}},{"path":"35-54/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"38.6%"}},{"path":"35-54/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"92.2%"}},{"path":"35-54/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"3.5%"}},{"path":"35-54/Any TV","values":{"2020":"98.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"75.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"37.6%"}},{"path":"35-54/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"39.6%"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"40.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"45.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"59.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"44.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"0.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"47.2%"}},{"path":"55+/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"65.6%"}},{"path":"55+/Tablet","values":{"2020":"59.6%"}},{"path":"55+/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"27.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"64.5%"}},{"path":"55+/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"20.5%"}},{"path":"55+/Any TV","values":{"2020":"98.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"53.7%"}},{"path":"55+/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"15.2%"}},{"path":"55+/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"21.3%"}},{"path":"55+/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"37.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"27.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"77.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"44.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"0.0%"}}],"id":"-Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEiHF","name":"% takeup of device (historic)","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[THINKING]: **Considering calculation variables**

I need to help the user come up with a working calculation and suggest additional variables. I don't think we need to modify the model unless specifically asked; it's about forming a robust formula pattern in Markdown. The forecast variable has an auto segment from 2021-2035, while the historic variable uses 2020 data, which isn't applicable afterward. I’ll need to interpolate linearly, and possibly use a self-referencing recursive formula or helper variables. It sounds like self-reference might work, but I'll need to ensure the units are properly defined.**Clarifying self-reference and dimensions**

I'm thinking about the self-reference with time semantics and how it connects to a unitless timeless variable. It seems like I can reference the previous period just fine, even if it's unitless. I need to remember that self-referencing variables require defined units, which could be Unitless [Timeless]. 

For my formula, I might use the previous period plus an annual step, and I could benefit from a helper variable for that. Both historic and endpoint dimensions align well, which is a plus! I see my assumptions for the forecast end year variable span 72 values, but it seems I’m only dealing with one value for each dimension. This means I’ll have to interpolate linearly over the 2021-2035 periods, using the 2020 actuals and the 2035 endpoint.**Breaking down forecast intervals**

I’m figuring out the forecast intervals from 2020 to 2035, which give me 15 total intervals. The formula I’m using is: for any year \( t \), the forecast equals the actual value from 2020 plus the difference between the endpoint for 2035 and the 2020 actual, multiplied by how far along the year is in the interval range. For 2021, the ratio would be \( \frac{1}{15} \), and then it goes all the way to 2035, where the ratio would be \( \frac{15}{15} \).**Evaluating calculation formula**

I'm considering how to create a formula for calculating figures based on annual increments and the time segment for 2021, but I'm wondering about the variables. Should I use a default calculation referencing itself and other variables? That might work, especially with an IF statement for the year 2021. Still, I need to clarify whether certain conditions can reference self offsets or need a distinct unit defined. Also, can I compare periods to integers? It’s a bit complex!**Creating forecast variables**

I'm thinking it might be better to utilize a helper boolean variable like "Is first forecast period" or "Interpolation years since last actual" that uses date comparison. I could also consider a variable that counts recursively, but a cleaner non-recursive solution might be to create "Forecast interpolation weight." This weight would be based on the difference between the periods and the endpoint year. I just need to determine the right historic reference for the forecast variable formula!**Evaluating forecast formulas**

I’m working on a non-recursive forecast formula: LastActualCarryForward plus InterpolationFraction times (Endpoint minus LastActualCarryForward). I'll define InterpolationFraction as the difference in years since 2020 divided by the endpoint forecast year minus 2020. I need to check if the formula parser supports YEAR and whether I can use basic date arithmetic. Since the endpoint year can vary, I should consider how to handle projections beyond that year to ensure clarity in the model’s output.**Evaluating last actuals integration**

I'm considering whether to hardcode the last actual year as 2020 or create a helper variable for it. A constant for "Last actuals year" could provide flexibility. If the model's last actuals period shifts, I might leverage self-carry-forward calculations to avoid hardcoding altogether. However, this still requires careful thought since it could limit updates. Overall, creating a single helper variable for the last actual year would likely be the best route.**Considering last actuals access**

I’m figuring out if there's a built-in way to access last actuals in the formulas; it seems not. I might need to hardcode or create a separate assumption like "End point forecast start year" or "Last actuals year." 

For a cleaner approach, I could design a minimal variable count solution. One option is to create a variable for "Last actual % takeup carried forward," which uses a formula to reference historic data. Another could be an "Interpolation weight" to help manage variable dimensions.**Evaluating forecast formulas**

I’m considering a simpler approach for the forecast formula without needing extra carry-forward helpers. The formula segments into two conditions for different years. However, I’m pondering if I can reference historical data dynamically. If I try to reference historic data with an offset, it might not work correctly for future years, leading to an issue. I realize I might need a helper method or a recursive setup to keep everything consistent as I move forward each year.**Considering helper variables**

I'm thinking about using helper variables for the formula, specifically for annual steps in forecasting. It seems the formula could measure the difference between the endpoint forecast and the last historic data. However, it turns out the historic reference is only valid for 2021. Instead, I could use a carried-forward variable for historic take-up, allowing me to apply a recursive approach where the annual step is calculated based on the endpoint minus this carried-forward value divided by the years remaining since 2020.**Considering dynamic maintainability**

If I prefer dynamic maintainability, I should suggest adding new variables, like an "End point" forecast start year or "Last actuals year for end point forecast," which would be set to 2020. This way, the formula uses this variable instead of hardcoding the year. I could also propose a helper variable like "Interpolation fraction." Since the user asked for additional variable suggestions, it's good to mention at least two helpers, maybe three, and discuss any divide-by-zero potential when the endpoint year equals the last actual year, adding an IF statement for the denominator.**Evaluating forecasting formula**

I'm considering a formula that checks if an "end point" forecast is being used. If it is, I want to see whether the end year is less than or equal to the last actuals year. If so, I'd carry forward the last actual percentage takeup. Otherwise, I'd adjust this based on the difference between the years and the percentage takeup difference. I need to confirm whether the boolean works in the IF statement and if N/A is a constant. I might skip the toggle if I'm unsure about it and mention optional wrapping. Also, variables not using the endpoint forecast could just be N/A or handled elsewhere.**Considering interpolation calculations**

I'm thinking about creating a variable named `Years from interpolation start`, which would involve calculating the maximum of 0 and the difference between the year of `Periods` and the start year of the interpolation. Then, I'll weigh this by dividing by the difference between the forecast end year and the interpolation start year. This approach seems maintainable, and I might prefer using integers for simplicity to avoid self-referencing in the main forecast variable. Let's get to crafting this with a table of suggestions!
[ASSISTANT]: Yes — with the **correct historic Variable**, this becomes much cleaner.

## Recommended approach

Because Models can’t directly “look forward” to 2035 from 2021 in the same way Excel sometimes can, the cleanest pattern is:

1. **Carry the 2020 actual forward** into all forecast periods
2. Compute a **linear interpolation weight**
3. Apply:
   ```text
   Start value + Weight × (End value - Start value)
   ```

Since `% takeup of device (historic)` and `"End point" forecast end year % takeup` both have the same dimensions:

| Variable | Dimensions |
|----------|------------|
| `% takeup of device (historic)` | Radio Age-Group × Device type |
| `"End point" forecast end year % takeup` | Radio Age-Group × Device type |
| `"End point" forecast % takeup of device` | Radio Age-Group × Device type |

…dimension matching should work nicely.

---

## Best implementation pattern

I’d suggest **2 helper Variables**, with a **3rd optional one** if you want to avoid hard-coding 2020.

### Helper Variables

| Variable | Why |
|----------|-----|
| **Last actual % takeup of device** | Carries the final historic actual forward into forecast years |
| **End point interpolation weight** | Gives 0 at the last actual year and 1 at the forecast end year |
| **Optional: End point interpolation start year** | Lets you avoid hardcoding 2020 in formulas |

---

## 1) `Last actual % takeup of device`

### Purpose
This Variable should equal the historic actual while actuals exist, then keep repeating the final actual into forecast periods.

### Why this helps
It avoids needing to reference a specific past period like 2020 from every future year.

### Suggested formula
```text
IF(
  YEAR(Periods) <= 2020,
  "% takeup of device (historic)",
  "Last actual % takeup of device"[-1]
)
```

### Notes
- This Variable should have:
  - **same dimensions** as the historic/forecast Variables
  - **Defined unit** = `Unitless [Timeless]`
- Because it self-references with `[-1]`, it **must use Defined unit**, not Inferred.

---

## 2) `End point interpolation weight`

### Purpose
This gives the interpolation progress by year:

| Year | Weight |
|------|--------|
| 2020 | 0 |
| 2021 | 1/15 |
| 2022 | 2/15 |
| ... | ... |
| 2035 | 1 |

### Suggested formula
If you’re happy to hard-code 2020:

```text
MIN(
  1,
  MAX(
    0,
    (YEAR(Periods) - 2020) / ("End point" forecast end year - 2020)
  )
)
```

### Notes
- This can be a **scalar Variable** with **no dimensions**
- Data type: **Double**
- Unit: `Unitless [Timeless]`
- Number format: percentage is useful, though not essential

---

## 3) Main forecast formula

Then `"End point" forecast % takeup of device"` can be:

```text
"Last actual % takeup of device"
+ "End point interpolation weight"
  * (
      "\"End point\" forecast end year % takeup"
      - "Last actual % takeup of device"
    )
```

More cleanly formatted:

```text
"Last actual % takeup of device"
+ "End point interpolation weight" *
(
  "\"End point\" forecast end year % takeup"
  - "Last actual % takeup of device"
)
```

That gives:

- **2021** = start + 1/15 of the gap
- **2035** = endpoint assumption
- everything in between = straight-line interpolation

---

## Optional: avoid hard-coding 2020

If you want this to stay flexible when actuals move, add:

### `End point interpolation start year`
A constant Integer Variable or Assumption = `2020`

Then the helper formulas become:

#### Last actual carry-forward
```text
IF(
  YEAR(Periods) <= "End point interpolation start year",
  "% takeup of device (historic)",
  "Last actual % takeup of device"[-1]
)
```

#### Interpolation weight
```text
MIN(
  1,
  MAX(
    0,
    (YEAR(Periods) - "End point interpolation start year")
    / (
        "\"End point\" forecast end year"
        - "End point interpolation start year"
      )
  )
)
```

This is the version I’d recommend if the model may be rolled forward later.

---

## If you want to use `Uses "end point" forecast`

If that Boolean is intended to switch interpolation on only for certain device types, you can wrap the final formula.

### Example
```text
IF(
  "Uses ""end point"" forecast",
  "Last actual % takeup of device"
  + "End point interpolation weight" *
    (
      "\"End point\" forecast end year % takeup"
      - "Last actual % takeup of device"
    ),
  "% takeup of device (historic)"
)
```

### Important caveat
`Uses "end point" forecast` only has **Device type** dimension, not **Radio Age-Group × Device type**.

That may still be fine — Models should usually match on the shared Device dimension and apply the same flag across all age groups — but this is one thing I’d test after implementation.

---

## My recommended final design

| Priority | Variable | Type | Dimensions | Formula role |
|----------|----------|------|------------|--------------|
| 1 | `Last actual % takeup of device` | Calculation | Radio Age-Group × Device type | Carries 2020 actual forward |
| 2 | `End point interpolation weight` | Calculation | None | Linear 0→1 progression |
| 3 | `"End point" forecast % takeup of device` | Calculation | Radio Age-Group × Device type | Start + weight × gap |
| Optional | `End point interpolation start year` | Assumption or constant calc | None | Avoid hard-coded 2020 |

---

## Why I prefer this over a self-referencing forecast formula

You *could* make the forecast Variable itself recursive, but this split is better because it is:

| Benefit | Why it matters |
|---------|----------------|
| **More transparent** | Easy to inspect the starting point and interpolation path |
| **More maintainable** | If timing changes, you only update one helper |
| **Less brittle** | Main forecast formula stays simple |
| **Easier to debug** | You can test each helper independently |

---

## One small caution

For some device/age combinations your historic values are `N/A` in 2020. If those same combinations also have endpoint values, the interpolation will still fail unless you decide what the start value should be.

For example:

| Situation | Result |
|----------|--------|
| 2020 actual exists + 2035 endpoint exists | Works |
| 2020 actual is `N/A` + 2035 endpoint exists | Needs fallback logic |
| 2020 actual is `N/A` + 2035 endpoint is `N/A` | Fine to remain `N/A` |

If needed, I can help design a fallback such as:
- use `0%` if no last actual exists
- or make forecast stay `N/A`
- or start from first non-`N/A` historic value

---

## Recommended formulas summary

### Helper 1
```text
IF(
  YEAR(Periods) <= 2020,
  "% takeup of device (historic)",
  "Last actual % takeup of device"[-1]
)
```

### Helper 2
```text
MIN(
  1,
  MAX(
    0,
    (YEAR(Periods) - 2020) / ("End point" forecast end year - 2020)
  )
)
```

### Main forecast Variable
```text
"Last actual % takeup of device"
+ "End point interpolation weight" *
(
  "\"End point\" forecast end year % takeup"
  - "Last actual % takeup of device"
)
```

---

If you want, I can next do one of these:

| Option | What I’ll do |
|--------|---------------|
| **A** | Turn this into exact Variable specs ready to create in Models |
| **B** | Check whether the formula parser will accept this exact `formulaText` syntax |
| **C** | Propose fallback logic for the `N/A` device combinations |
[USER]: Have a go at creating them yourself. And let's not hardcode 2020 in, let's create a constant assumption variable for it.
[THINKING]: **Optimizing calculations**

I’m setting up a helper variable called defaultCalculation, which will pull from historic data. For the second time segment, I'll reference Calculation self[-1] for the forecast. I need to keep in mind that Calculation within TimeSegment must relate to the same variable with offsets, avoiding IF and branch evaluation risk. The user wants a constant start year assumption, but if I use the last actual variable with RelativeToActuals, I might not need it. Still, I should probably keep it for the weight formula.
[ASSISTANT]: I’ll build this in the model now. First I’m pulling the structure workflow and Variable create/update schema so I can create the helper Variables cleanly and then update the forecast formula safely.
[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Build structure workflow", parameters={"category":"build-structure","format":"compact"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get Variable create schema", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: # Build Model Structure

## Purpose
Use this workflow when creating or modifying the Model's Variable and Assumption structure.

## Prerequisites
- Model context is set (`ModelAction(action='set-current')`)
- You understand the Model's purpose (what outputs are needed)
- Retrieve `variables` and `assumptions` object instructions if you haven't already

## Build Order

Building a Model structure follows a bottom-up approach for inputs and top-down for planning:

### 1. Plan Top-Down
Start with the desired outputs and work backwards:
- What are the final output Variables? (e.g., Revenue, Profit, Cash Flow)
- What calculations produce those outputs?
- What inputs (Assumptions) feed those calculations?
- Are there Dimensions? (e.g., by Region, by Product)

### 2. Create Tags and Dimensions (if needed)
If the Model uses Dimensions:
- Create Abstract Tags for each Dimension (e.g., "Region", "Product")
- Create Concrete Tags as children (e.g., "UK", "France" under "Region")
- Concrete Tags reference their parent via `isATagIds`
- Retrieve `tags` object instructions for API details

### 3. Create Scenarios and Sensitivities (if beyond Base)
If the Model needs multiple Scenarios or Sensitivities:
- Create additional Scenarios with `basedOnScenarioId` referencing Base or another Scenario
- Create Sensitivities for variance analysis
- Retrieve `scenarios` object instructions for API details

### 4. Build Variables Bottom-Up
Create Variables from inputs to outputs:

**a) Assumption Variables first:**
- Create the Variable with `defaultFormulaType: Assumption`
- Set `unitOption: Defined` and define the Unit with correct TimeType
- Add `tagParents` for Dimensional Variables
- ModelAssumptions are created automatically when providing inline assumption values via TimeSegments
- OR create ModelAssumptions separately and link via TimeSegments

**b) Calculation Variables next:**
- Create with `defaultFormulaType: Calculation`
- Define `defaultCalculation` with `formulaText` referencing previously-created Variables
- Set `unitOption: Inferred` (default for Calculations) unless you need a specific Unit
- For Dimensional Variables, add matching `tagParents`

**c) Aggregation Variables (if needed):**
- Create when different Dimension parts have different calculation logic
- Set `aggregatedVariableIds` to reference the part Variables
- Set `groupSummaryType` (usually `Sum`)

### 5. Validate Structure
After creating all Variables:
- Check for unit warnings
- Verify calculation dependencies resolve correctly
- Use `get-details` on key Variables to confirm their computed values

## Common Patterns

### Simple Linear Model
Input -> Calculation -> Output
```
Price (Assumption) -> Revenue = Price x Volume (Calculation) -> Profit = Revenue - Costs (Calculation)
Volume (Assumption) /
Costs (Assumption) /
```

### Dimensional Model
Same structure but with `tagParents` on Variables that need to expand across Dimensions.

### Model with Time Flexibility (Rearranging)
For Actuals + Forecast models, see the Rearranging section in `variables` object instructions.

## Key Rules
- Assumption Variables must have `unitOption: Defined` with appropriate TimeTypes: Flow or Balance for tagged UnitParts, Timeless for unitless UnitParts
- Set `isConstant: true` on Variables with time-invariant values (fixed rates, conversion factors)
- Calculation Variables default to `unitOption: Inferred`
- Each ModelSheet type supports only one kind of LineItem
- Assumption-type Variables belong on Calculation sheets, not Assumption sheets

[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new Variable. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","notes":["Updates support partial payloads - only include properties you want to change. For detailed guidance on complex properties (Aggregation, contextVarianceMap, groupSummary), use GetInstructions(category='variables')","Assumption and Aggregation Variables require unitOption: 'Defined' (the default). When unitOption is 'Defined', the unit property is required.","Minimal Unitless unit: {\"unitParts\": [{\"timeType\": \"Timeless\"}]}. For time-varying units, use timeType 'Flow' or 'Balance' with a tag. To mark a Variable as constant (no time variance), set isConstant: true. Note: {\"unitParts\": []} creates an Undefined unit (invalid for Assumptions)."],"object_type":"Variable","parameters":{"aggregatedVariableIds":{"description":"IDs of Variables representing Dimension parts to combine (not a sum - see GetInstructions)","relevant_when":{"defaultFormulaType":"Aggregation"},"type":"array[string]"},"applyFactoring":{"default":false,"description":"Auto-adjust when Variable unit factor differs from calculated unit factor","type":"boolean"},"columnSummaries":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='ColumnSummary'","type":"array[ColumnSummary]"},"contextVarianceMap":{"description":"Maps which unit parts vary with which Dimensions. Only relevant when Variable has Dimensions and Defined unit. Defaults to all-vary-with-all.","properties":{"contextVarianceMap":{"description":"Map from string key to HashSet`1. For value schema, query help with object_type='HashSet`1'.","properties":{},"type":"object"}},"relevant_when":{"unitOption":"Defined"},"type":"object"},"dataType":{"type":"enum","values":["Double","Integer","String","DateTime","Date","Boolean","Validation"]},"defaultAssumptionId":{"description":"Fallback assumption for periods/dimensions without matching TimeSegment assumption","type":"string"},"defaultCalculation":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='Calculation'","relevant_when":{"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation"},"type":"Calculation"},"defaultFormulaType":{"description":"The formula type for this Variable","required":true,"type":"enum","values":["Assumptions","Calculation","Aggregation"]},"groupSummaryRearrangedParentId":{"description":"Parent Variable for Rearranged summary calculation (e.g., weighted averages)","required_when":{"groupSummaryType":"Rearranged"},"type":"string"},"groupSummaryType":{"description":"Controls Dimension summary behavior: None, Sum (simple sum), Auto (recalculate), Rearranged (from parent)","type":"enum","values":["None","Sum","Auto","Rearranged"]},"isConstant":{"default":false,"description":"Whether this Variable's value is constant across all time periods","type":"boolean"},"name":{"required":true,"type":"string"},"numberFormatId":{"type":"string"},"overrideUnitError":{"default":false,"type":"boolean"},"periodType":{"description":"Overrides Model's default period. Must be broader than Model timings. None = use default.","type":"enum","values":["None","Day","Week","Month","Quarter","YearCalendar","YearFiscal"]},"tagIds":{"type":"array[string]"},"tagParents":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='TagParents'","type":"TagParents"},"timeSegments":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='TimeSegment'","type":"array[TimeSegment]"},"unit":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='Unit'","required_when":{"unitOption":"Defined"},"type":"Unit"},"unitOption":{"description":"Defined by default for Assumption/Aggregation Variables","relevant_when":{"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation"},"type":"enum","values":["Defined","Inferred"]},"validationDimensionId":{"description":"Abstract Tag defining dropdown options for Validation dataType Variables","required_when":{"dataType":"Validation"},"type":"string"}}}
[THINKING]: **Evaluating formula adjustments**

I need to think about dimension matching with scalar weight, ensuring there are no dimensions involved. The formula uses an end year assumption as a variable integer scalar. Using integer division might be necessary, as it likely returns double due dates. I should create a forecast formula to update the variable defaultCalculation, particularly when there's an Auto forecast with NotApplicable actuals. I also need to consider how to handle names with quotes inside, ensuring I escape internal quotes properly in the formula text.**Determining variable handling**

I might consider using variable IDs via calculationParts, but formulaText seems easier to work with. I need to identify the exact parser style to ensure safe quoting. Existing variable names start and end with quotes, so should I generate formulaText for these? Better yet, I could opt for calculationParts, though it's more complex. I need to figure out how to handle quoted names with doubled internal quotes or backslash escaping. The variable name "% takeup of device (historic)" clearly needs quoting as `"% takeup of device (historic)"`, but for `"End point" forecast end year % takeup`, I might represent it as `"\"End point\" forecast end year % takeup"` in formulaText.**Exploring variable referencing**

I'm considering whether to use triple double quotes in an Excel style, maybe like in an SQL example. I could inspect existing formulaText for variable names containing quotes, though I wonder if it'd be helpful. Alternatively, I could avoid directly referencing quoted variables by creating a helper variable with a simpler name and using that in the formula. If I'm creating helper variables, I could name one "End point interpolation end takeup" to reference the endpoint variable. But I still need to reference the quoted variable somehow.**Evaluating assumptions for time segments**

I’m considering using `isConstant true` alongside `timeSegments` with assumed values, possibly just one cell. The existing assumption variable has one assumption spanning all periods labeled `2016-2035: 1 assumption`, and declaring `isConstant true` seems to align with that. So, it looks like one value might work, which leads me to think `assumptions.values: [["2020"]]` could be suitable. This approach seems logical, but I want to ensure it fits the overall framework.**Considering data structure options**

I’m thinking that a basic structured summary might not be enough. I could involve properties like ["tagParents.parents"], which could give me IDs. I’ll need an exact unit, perhaps a simple unitless one, and I might require the forecast variable tagParents if I want consistency with the IDs. If I omit tagParents, there could be dimensional issues, which isn’t ideal. It might be possible to copy from existing historic data by updating with tagParents for the IDs I need. Let’s fetch more detailed nested data.
[ASSISTANT]: I’ve got the overall design. Before creating anything, I’m pulling the exact dimension IDs from the existing Variables so the helper Variables inherit the same age-group × device structure cleanly, then I’ll create them and update the forecast formula.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Expand historic tag parents", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEiHF","properties":["tagParents.parents"]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Expand forecast tag parents", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yhph","properties":["tagParents.parents"]})
[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Assumption variable guidance", parameters={"category":"assumptions","format":"compact"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"tagParents":{"parents":[{"name":"Radio Age-Group","tagId":"-PdiHAQz-DLqL0tEIrQv"},{"name":"Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)","tagId":"-PdiHAQz-DLqL0tEIvrR"}]}}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"tagParents":{"parents":[{"name":"Radio Age-Group","tagId":"-PdiHAQz-DLqL0tEIrQv"},{"name":"Device type (inc. Home: Any Radio)","tagId":"-PdiHAQz-DLqL0tEIvrR"}]}}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: # Working with ModelAssumptions

## Overview

ModelAssumptions are user-input containers that provide values to Variables. They store scalar values that can vary by Scenario and Sensitivity. When a Variable has `defaultFormulaType: Assumptions`, it pulls its values from a ModelAssumption.

## Key Concepts

**ModelAssumption**: A container for user-input values with the following key properties:
- **prefix**: The base name before dimensional/time context is added
- **values**: A map of values keyed by Scenario ID
- **sensitivities**: A map of sensitivity overrides keyed by Sensitivity ID
- **sensitivityType**: The type of sensitivity calculation (PercentageChange, Delta, Absolute)
- **unit**: The unit definition including any dimensional modifiers

**Relationship to Variables**: Variables with `defaultFormulaType: Assumptions` reference a ModelAssumption via `defaultAssumptionId`. The Variable gets its calculated values from the assumption.

## Values Map

The `values` property is a `Dictionary<string, ModelAssumptionValue>` where:
- **Keys**: Scenario IDs (e.g., `"-Pt6e56nOUBefHIEvLbi"`)
- **Values**: ModelAssumptionValue objects

### ModelAssumptionValue Structure

Each value entry specifies:
- **modelAssumptionValueType**: Currently only `LocalInput` is supported
- **localInputValue**: The actual value as a string (parsed based on dataType)

### Example

```json
{
  "values": {
    "-scenarioId1": {
      "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
      "localInputValue": "29.99"
    },
    "-scenarioId2": {
      "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
      "localInputValue": "34.99"
    }
  }
}
```

**Important**: If a Scenario is "based on" another Scenario and has no explicit value, it inherits from its base Scenario.

## Sensitivities Map

The `sensitivities` property is a `Dictionary<string, SensitivityValue>` where:
- **Keys**: Sensitivity IDs (e.g., `"-Pt6e56nOUBefHIEvLbj"`)
- **Values**: SensitivityValue objects

### SensitivityValue Structure

Each sensitivity entry specifies:
- **sensitivityValueType**: Must match the parent assumption's `sensitivityType`
- One of: `percentage`, `delta`, or `absolute` (depending on type)

### sensitivityType Matching

**Critical**: The `sensitivityType` on ModelAssumption determines the type for ALL sensitivity values. Individual `SensitivityValue.sensitivityValueType` values must match.

| sensitivityType | Required Field | Meaning |
|-----------------|---------------|---------|
| PercentageChange | percentage | Multiply base value by (1 + percentage/100) |
| Delta | delta | Add delta to base value |
| Absolute | absolute | Replace base value entirely |

### Example

```json
{
  "sensitivityType": "PercentageChange",
  "sensitivities": {
    "-sensitivityId1": {
      "sensitivityValueType": "PercentageChange",
      "percentage": "10"
    },
    "-sensitivityId2": {
      "sensitivityValueType": "PercentageChange",
      "percentage": "-5"
    }
  }
}
```

## Dimensional Assumptions

Assumptions can represent values across Dimensions (e.g., by Region, by Product). Unlike Variables which expand across Dimensions via `tagParents`, dimensional assumptions require **separate ModelAssumption objects** for each dimension combination.

### How Dimensions Work

1. **One Assumption per dimension combination**: For "Price" varying by Region (North, South) and Tier (Basic, Premium), you create 4 assumptions
2. **Same prefix, different modifiers**: All share the same `prefix` but have different Unit modifiers
3. **Modifiers on UnitParts**: Dimensional context is stored as `modifiers` on UnitPart objects

### Example: New Members per Month by Region and Tier

For a model with:
- Region Dimension: North, South
- Tier Dimension: Basic, Premium

You would create 4 ModelAssumptions, all with `prefix: "New members per month"`:

| Assumption | Value | Unit Modifiers |
|------------|-------|----------------|
| Assumption 1 | 30 | North, Basic |
| Assumption 2 | 10 | North, Premium |
| Assumption 3 | 5 | South, Basic |
| Assumption 4 | 18 | South, Premium |

### Unit Modifiers Structure

Each UnitPart can have modifiers that specify dimensional context:

```json
{
  "unit": {
    "unitParts": [
      {
        "tagId": "-memberTagId",
        "modifiers": [
          {
            "tagId": "-northTagId"
          },
          {
            "tagId": "-basicTagId"
          }
        ]
      }
    ]
  }
}
```

The `modifiers` array contains references to Concrete Tags that define the dimensional position of this assumption.

## Time Series Assumptions

Assumptions can represent values at specific points in time or over specific periods. This is achieved by adding a `dateTimeElement` to a UnitPart.

### DateTimeElement Types

| Element Type | Description | Use Case |
|--------------|-------------|----------|
| **Flow** | Period with duration | Flow values (e.g., "Revenue for Q1 2024") |
| **Balance** | Point-in-time snapshot | Stock values (e.g., "Headcount at Dec 2024") |
| **Timeless** | Period without temporal semantics | Unitless time-varying values (e.g., "Growth Rate for 2024") |

**Important**: All non-constant Assumptions require a `dateTimeElement` matching the UnitPart's TimeType. Constant Assumptions (where the Variable has `isConstant: true`) have no `dateTimeElement` — a single value covers all periods.

### DateTimeSeriesDate Formats

The `dateString` format depends on the `dateType`:

| dateType | Format | Example |
|----------|--------|---------|
| Day | `yyyyMMdd` | `"20240115"` (January 15, 2024) |
| Week | `yyyyMMdd` | `"20240121"` (end of week, e.g., Sunday) |
| Month | `yyyyMM` | `"202401"` (January 2024) |
| Quarter | `yyyyQ[1-4]` | `"2024Q1"` (Q1 2024) |
| Year | `yyyy` | `"2024"` |

**Note**: Quarter and Year formats use calendar year conventions (Q1 = Jan-Mar, year ends December 31). The system will interpret these correctly based on the model's fiscal year settings.

### Month-Specific Options

When `dateType` is `Month`, you can specify when in the month:

| monthDateType | Description |
|---------------|-------------|
| EndOfMonth | End of the specified month (default) |
| DayInMonth | Specific day, requires `dayOfMonth` (1-28) |

### DateTimeElement Structure

```json
{
  "dateTimeElement": {
    "elementType": "Flow",
    "dateType": "Quarter",
    "dateString": "2024Q1",
    "duration": 1
  }
}
```

For Balance (snapshot) elements, omit `duration`:

```json
{
  "dateTimeElement": {
    "elementType": "Balance",
    "dateType": "Month",
    "dateString": "202412",
    "monthDateType": "EndOfMonth"
  }
}
```

### Pattern: Time Series Assumption

A quarterly revenue assumption for Q1 2024:

```json
{
  "action": "create",
  "object_type": "ModelAssumption",
  "parameters": {
    "prefix": "Revenue",
    "dataType": "Double",
    "values": {
      "-baseScenarioId": {
        "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
        "localInputValue": "1000000"
      }
    },
    "unit": {
      "unitParts": [
        {
          "tagId": "-revenueTagId",
          "timeType": "Flow",
          "dateTimeElement": {
            "elementType": "Flow",
            "dateType": "Quarter",
            "dateString": "2024Q1",
            "duration": 1
          }
        }
      ]
    }
  }
}
```

### Pattern: Balance Snapshot Assumption

A monthly balance (e.g., headcount at end of month):

```json
{
  "action": "create",
  "object_type": "ModelAssumption",
  "parameters": {
    "prefix": "Headcount",
    "dataType": "Integer",
    "values": {
      "-baseScenarioId": {
        "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
        "localInputValue": "150"
      }
    },
    "unit": {
      "unitParts": [
        {
          "tagId": "-headcountTagId",
          "timeType": "Balance",
          "dateTimeElement": {
            "elementType": "Balance",
            "dateType": "Month",
            "dateString": "202412"
          }
        }
      ]
    }
  }
}
```

### Pattern: Unitless Time Series

For a unitless value at a specific time (no tag, just time context):

```json
{
  "action": "create",
  "object_type": "ModelAssumption",
  "parameters": {
    "prefix": "Growth Rate",
    "dataType": "Double",
    "values": {
      "-baseScenarioId": {
        "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
        "localInputValue": "0.05"
      }
    },
    "unit": {
      "unitParts": [
        {
          "tagId": null,
          "timeType": "Timeless",
          "dateTimeElement": {
            "elementType": "Timeless",
            "dateType": "Year",
            "dateString": "2024"
          }
        }
      ]
    }
  }
}
```

### Time Series Pitfalls

**Pitfall 1: Missing duration for Flow**

Flow elements require a `duration` (minimum 1). Balance elements should not have duration.

**Pitfall 2: Mismatched timeType and elementType**

The `timeType` on UnitPart should match the `elementType` in dateTimeElement:
- `timeType: "Flow"` → `elementType: "Flow"`
- `timeType: "Balance"` → `elementType: "Balance"`
- `timeType: "Timeless"` → `elementType: "Timeless"`

**Pitfall 3: Wrong date format**

Each dateType has a specific format. Using `"2024-01"` instead of `"202401"` for Month will fail validation.

## Common Patterns

### Pattern 1: Simple Scalar Assumption

A single value that doesn't vary by Scenario:

```json
{
  "action": "create",
  "object_type": "ModelAssumption",
  "parameters": {
    "prefix": "Tax Rate",
    "dataType": "Double",
    "values": {
      "-baseScenarioId": {
        "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
        "localInputValue": "0.25"
      }
    }
  }
}
```

### Pattern 2: Multi-Scenario Assumption

Values that differ by Scenario:

```json
{
  "action": "create",
  "object_type": "ModelAssumption",
  "parameters": {
    "prefix": "Revenue Growth Rate",
    "dataType": "Double",
    "values": {
      "-baseScenarioId": {
        "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
        "localInputValue": "0.05"
      },
      "-optimisticScenarioId": {
        "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
        "localInputValue": "0.08"
      },
      "-pessimisticScenarioId": {
        "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
        "localInputValue": "0.02"
      }
    }
  }
}
```

### Pattern 3: Assumption with Sensitivities

Add sensitivity analysis capability:

```json
{
  "action": "create",
  "object_type": "ModelAssumption",
  "parameters": {
    "prefix": "Discount Rate",
    "dataType": "Double",
    "sensitivityType": "Delta",
    "values": {
      "-baseScenarioId": {
        "modelAssumptionValueType": "LocalInput",
        "localInputValue": "0.08"
      }
    },
    "sensitivities": {
      "-highSensitivityId": {
        "sensitivityValueType": "Delta",
        "delta": "0.02"
      },
      "-lowSensitivityId": {
        "sensitivityValueType": "Delta",
        "delta": "-0.02"
      }
    }
  }
}
```

## Common Pitfalls

### Pitfall 1: Confusing Values Keys with Sensitivities Keys

**Mistake**: Using the wrong ID type as map keys.

**Reality**:
- `values` keys are **Scenario IDs**
- `sensitivities` keys are **Sensitivity IDs**

These are different object types with different IDs.

### Pitfall 2: Mismatching sensitivityType

**Mistake**: Setting `sensitivityType: PercentageChange` but providing `delta` values in sensitivities.

**Reality**: The `sensitivityValueType` on each SensitivityValue must match the parent assumption's `sensitivityType`.

### Pitfall 3: Expecting Dimensional Expansion

**Mistake**: Thinking one assumption can cover multiple dimension combinations.

**Reality**: Each dimension combination requires its own ModelAssumption. Use Unit modifiers to differentiate them.

### Pitfall 4: Numeric Values as Numbers

**Mistake**: Providing numeric values as JSON numbers (`"localInputValue": 29.99`).

**Reality**: All values are stored as strings. Always use string format (`"localInputValue": "29.99"`).

## Best Practices

1. **Use descriptive prefixes** that clearly identify what the assumption represents
2. **Provide values for the Base Scenario** at minimum - other scenarios can inherit
3. **Match sensitivityType with your analysis needs**:
   - Use `PercentageChange` for multiplicative sensitivity (e.g., revenue changes)
   - Use `Delta` for additive sensitivity (e.g., rate adjustments)
   - Use `Absolute` for replacement values
4. **Create dimensional assumptions systematically** - ensure all combinations are covered
5. **Query existing Scenarios and Sensitivities** before creating assumptions to get valid IDs

[THINKING]: **Creating variables for time segments**

I need to create variables and figure out a schema for time segments based on certain assumptions. Since the user asked for a constant assumption variable for the start year, using an inline assumptions grid might be easier. I’m considering whether to get help on TimeSegment or if a schema is sufficient. I might need to inspect existing constant assumption variables for details to create a new one effectively.**Exploring time segments and formulas**

I might need to get details about time segments, but it could show only a summary without full subproperties. I’m uncertain about using properties like ['timeSegments.formula.assumptions'] and whether QueryObject help is available for creating TimeSegment. There are instructions to use SegmentPeriod for schema details, but it's unclear if QueryObject can handle TimeSegment. I should also check if the formula parser supports the YEAR function for periods since the user wanted a constant start year. Creating an interpolation weight variable based on integer formulas might be easier.**Clarifying the assumption variable**

If the assumption variable is an integer, it should be okay to subtract an integer from the year using a date. I need to verify that the formula parser supports quoted variable names. I could potentially avoid the YEAR function if the model periods are annual, possibly using a self-referencing weight variable instead. However, I still need a variable formula for the span of years. Creating a recursive "years since start" variable could work, but the YEAR function should be reliable since it supports Excel functions. Let's explore a more robust approach.**Considering assumption variables**

I'm thinking about simplifying how I create assumption variables. Maybe I can omit the timeSegments object and just use a defaultAssumption. But for the Assumptions type, it feels like having timeSegments or a defaultAssumptionId is still necessary. I could create ModelAssumption separately and link it through defaultAssumptionId, though that might complicate things with more schemas. It might be easier to include inline timeSegments assumptions as per my variable instructions. I should reach out for help with the full TimeSegment schema.
[ASSISTANT]: I’m doing two quick checks before writing: whether these helper names already exist, and the exact shape of an existing constant assumption Variable so I can create the start-year assumption in the same pattern.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Check helper variable names", object_type="Variable", parameters={"$or":[{"name":"*End point interpolation start year*"},{"name":"*End point interpolation weight*"},{"name":"*Last actual % takeup of device*"}],"format":"structured","limit":20})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Inspect existing end year fully", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yW7J","properties":["name","defaultFormulaType","dataType","unit","timeSegments","defaultAssumptionId"]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Get assumption filter help", object_type="ModelAssumption", parameters={"format":"compact","help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":0,"variables":[]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"dataType":"Integer","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","name":"\"End point\" forecast end year","timeSegments":[{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Auto...}","endPeriodDescription":"End","formula":"{Assumptions: 1 assumption...}","formulaDescription":"1 assumption","hasError":false,"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yX__","modelFormulaType":"Assumptions","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Start"}],"unit":{"description":"Unitless [Timeless]","factorPower":"0","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yXK-","isUndefined":false,"isUnitless":true,"modifiersDescription":"","timeTypeDescription":"Timeless","unitParts":{"count":1,"items":["{Unitless...}"]}}}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"filter","description":"Filter ModelAssumption objects based on their properties","object_type":"ModelAssumption","operators":{"$and":{"description":"Matches objects where all conditions are true (explicit AND for nesting)","syntax":{"$and":[{"property1":"value1"},{"property2":"value2"}]}},"$not":{"description":"Inverts a condition","syntax":{"$not":{"property":"value"}}},"$or":{"description":"Matches objects where at least one condition is true","syntax":{"$or":[{"property1":"value1"},{"property2":"value2"}]}},"note":"Top-level properties are implicitly ANDed. Operators can be nested for complex queries."},"pagination":{"limit":{"default":"Set by session (typically 50)","description":"Maximum number of results to return. A truncation warning is included when results exceed this limit.","type":"integer"},"skip":{"default":0,"description":"Number of results to skip (for pagination).","type":"integer"}},"parameters":{"dataType":{"type":"enum","values":["Double","Integer","String","DateTime","Date","Boolean","Validation","List","NotApplicable"]},"dateTimeDescription":{"type":"string"},"dateTimeLongDateString":{"type":"string"},"id":{"type":"string"},"isInLayout":{"type":"boolean"},"isUsed":{"type":"boolean"},"notes":{"type":"string"},"numberFormatText":{"type":"string"},"prefix":{"type":"string"},"searchText":{"type":"string"},"sensitivityType":{"type":"enum","values":["PercentageChange","Delta","Absolute"]},"timeTypeDescription":{"type":"string"},"unitDescription":{"type":"string"}},"pattern_guide":{"boolean":["true/false"],"enum":["exact (case-insensitive)"],"string":["exact","glob (*?)","regex (/pattern/)"]}}
[THINKING]: **Considering variable creation**

I need to create helper variables and determine the schema for timeSegments, possibly using inline assumptions. It's interesting that while I know I should help with the TimeSegment, I’m not entirely sure if it's necessary. I’ve encountered variable creation before but not specifically for TimeSegment or TagParents. Perhaps I should retrieve assistance for the Variable creation object type. I definitely want to understand the exact payload and check if nested schemas are indeed supported.**Exploring operations and assumptions**

I’m considering that all operations are available for different object types, and asking for help with the TimeSegment action create might return the schema—likely yes. I may need details on the Calculation schema too. I’m thinking about retrieving help for updating variables since it’s similar to creating them. For the assumption variable, I’ll use inline assumptions with timeSegments. It seems like I need to clarify the exact shape of the assumption grid and consider defaults for the assumption variable. Updating existing segments might also be necessary since they're already in use.**Setting up calculations**

I need to create a calculation variable called "Last actual % takeup of device" using the same tagParents. The default calculation will be a recursive IF statement that checks if the year is less than or equal to the end point start year. If so, it'll refer to historic takeup data; if not, it'll reference the last actual takeup. I plan to define the unit as unitless and timeless for the self-reference. For time segments, I think defaulting to auto for all periods is probably fine, calculating historic data from 2016-2020 and recursively for 2021 and beyond. Next, I should set up the "End point interpolation weight" as a scalar calculation, possibly using YEAR(Periods) for the formula.**Clarifying formatting needs**

I need to specify the numberFormatId for calculation variables. For unitless percentage variables, I could use Pct1Dp, while for the start year, I’m considering existing options like General or ThousandSeparator0Dp. The existing end year variable seems to use General too, which might be fine for an integer year. Maybe the numberFormatId can be omitted if it defaults? I should double-check whether built-in names are accepted or if IDs are necessary.
[ASSISTANT]: I’ve got the IDs and helper names are free. I’m pulling the nested schemas for **TimeSegment** and **Calculation** so I can create the constant assumption and self-referencing helper correctly on the first try.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get TimeSegment schema", object_type="TimeSegment", parameters={"format":"structured","help":true})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get Calculation schema", object_type="Calculation", parameters={"format":"structured","help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new TimeSegment. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","object_type":"TimeSegment","parameters":{"assumptionIds":{"type":"array[string]"},"duration":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='SegmentDuration'","type":"SegmentDuration"},"end":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='SegmentPeriod'","type":"SegmentPeriod"},"id":{"type":"string"},"modelFormulaType":{"type":"enum","values":["Auto","Assumptions","Calculation","Aggregation","Rearranged","NotApplicable"]},"start":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='SegmentPeriod'","type":"SegmentPeriod"}}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new Calculation. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","notes":["Calculation cannot be created/updated standalone - use Variable or Metric operations. This schema is for documentation purposes only."],"object_type":"Calculation","parameters":{"calculationParts":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='CalculationPart'","type":"array[CalculationPart]"},"formulaText":{"description":"Human-readable formula string (e.g., 'Revenue - Costs'). Alternative to calculationParts array. If both formulaText and calculationParts are provided, calculationParts takes precedence. Supports: variable names, constants, operators (+, -, *, /, ^), parentheses, functions (SUM, MAX, MIN, IF, etc.), period offsets (Revenue[-1] for previous period), period references (Periods returns end date of current period, useful for date comparisons like 'Periods \u003e Launch_Date'). Quote variable names containing special characters: \"Revenue (Net)\".","type":"string"},"id":{"type":"string"}}}
[THINKING]: **Considering forecast integration**

I’m wondering if we should incorporate this without a toggle, as it might disrupt the existing design. I need to inspect the root variable, since it seems there’s currently no formula related to the "end point" forecast. I should check if that variable is just for certain device types. The user asked for a formula to apply to the forecast period, likely involving linear interpolation. I’ll also consider whether a toggle is truly necessary here.**Evaluating forecast integration**

I'm thinking if users might eventually combine this with other forecast sources, it might be wise not to include it unless specifically requested. I should review the time segments since the forecast variable already shows "NotApplicable" for 2020 and "Auto" for 2021 onward. Perhaps just updating the default calculation will suffice. I might also need to validate the model afterward. Using tasks could be optional, and it’s possible that I don't need exact object schemas; I could infer the format instead.**Figuring out model assumptions**

I need to create a `ModelAssumption` and check the existing assumption variable's underlying assumptions, although that might not be necessary. I should definitely update the `TimeSegment` nested schema if `assumptionIds` are enough. For a constant assumption variable, I might set time segments to autofill using `assumptionIds` from `[modelAssumptionId]`. Now, I have to figure out how to define the start and end; I think it’s possibly just “auto” and “fill.” I’ll need to look into the `SegmentDuration` schema too.
[ASSISTANT]: I’m pulling the remaining schemas needed for a safe create: the ModelAssumption payload plus SegmentPeriod/SegmentDuration. Then I’ll create the constant start-year assumption, the two helper Variables, and update the forecast Variable.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get ModelAssumption schema", object_type="ModelAssumption", parameters={"format":"structured","help":true})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get SegmentPeriod schema", object_type="SegmentPeriod", parameters={"format":"structured","help":true})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Get SegmentDuration schema", object_type="SegmentDuration", parameters={"format":"structured","help":true})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new ModelAssumption. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","notes":["Updates support partial payloads - only include properties you want to change"],"object_type":"ModelAssumption","parameters":{"dataType":{"type":"enum","values":["Double","Integer","String","DateTime","Date","Boolean","Validation"]},"notes":{"type":"string"},"numberFormatId":{"type":"string"},"prefix":{"description":"The Assumption name before dimensional/time context is added","required":true,"type":"string"},"sensitivities":{"description":"Sensitivity overrides. Keys are Sensitivity IDs.. Map from string key to SensitivityValue. For value schema, query help with object_type='SensitivityValue'.","properties":{},"type":"object"},"sensitivityType":{"description":"Type for all sensitivity values. Individual SensitivityValue.sensitivityValueType must match.","type":"enum","values":["PercentageChange","Delta","Absolute"]},"unit":{"description":"For full schema, query help with object_type='Unit'","type":"Unit"},"validationDimensionId":{"relevant_when":{"dataType":"Validation"},"type":"string"},"values":{"description":"Values for different Scenarios. Keys are Scenario IDs.. Map from string key to ModelAssumptionValue. For value schema, query help with object_type='ModelAssumptionValue'.","properties":{},"type":"object"}}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new SegmentPeriod. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","object_type":"SegmentPeriod","parameters":{"fixedPeriodDateCode":{"required_when":{"segmentPeriodType":"FixedPeriod"},"type":"string"},"genericPeriodsFromEnd":{"description":"1-indexed period relative to end","required_when":{"segmentPeriodType":"PeriodsFromEndGeneric"},"type":"integer"},"genericPeriodsFromStart":{"description":"1-indexed period relative to start","required_when":{"segmentPeriodType":"PeriodsFromStartGeneric"},"type":"integer"},"id":{"type":"string"},"lastActualsOffset":{"description":"Offset from last actuals period (0 = last actuals, positive = forecast, negative = earlier actuals)","required_when":{"segmentPeriodType":"RelativeToActuals"},"type":"integer"},"segmentPeriodType":{"required":true,"type":"enum","values":["Auto","FixedPeriod","PeriodsFromStartGeneric","PeriodsFromStartSpecific","PeriodsFromEndGeneric","PeriodsFromEndSpecific","RelativeToActuals"]}}}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"action":"create","description":"Create/Update a new SegmentDuration. NOTE: same schema for Create/Update actions, don't retrieve both.","object_type":"SegmentDuration","parameters":{"genericPeriods":{"required_when":{"segmentDurationType":"PeriodsGeneric"},"type":"integer"},"id":{"type":"string"},"segmentDurationType":{"required":true,"type":"enum","values":["Auto","PeriodsGeneric","PeriodsSpecific"]}}}
[THINKING]: I think I should take a closer look at the existing assumption variable details. Maybe we need to incorporate properties like 'timeSegments.assumptionIds' to enhance how we manage or reference assumptions. It feels necessary to ensure we're correctly aligning these properties with our overall structure. Understanding these details better will help improve our approach moving forward. Let's really dig into this to get a clearer picture!
[ASSISTANT]: Before I write, I’m checking one existing assumption Variable in more detail so I can mirror the exact pattern the model is already using for a constant assumption. Then I’ll create the new assumption and helpers.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Expand end year assumptions links", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yW7J","properties":["defaultAssumptionId","timeSegments.assumptionIds","timeSegments.modelFormulaType"]})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="get-details", explanation="Expand historic assumption links", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","id":"-Pdi4CwvLwmjxARwEiHF","properties":["defaultAssumptionId","timeSegments.assumptionIds","timeSegments.modelFormulaType"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"timeSegments":[{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Auto...}","endPeriodDescription":"End","formula":"{Assumptions: 1 assumption...}","formulaDescription":"1 assumption","hasError":false,"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yX__","modelFormulaType":"Assumptions","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Start"}]},"warnings":["Unknown property: 'timeSegments'.'assumptionIds'. Use help to see available properties."]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"variable":{"timeSegments":[{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Last period of Actuals...}","endPeriodDescription":"Last period of Actuals (2020)","formula":"{Assumptions: 360 assumptions...}","formulaDescription":"360 assumptions","hasError":false,"id":"-PdjgP9oVsm2mHq67JOP","modelFormulaType":"Assumptions","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Start"},{"duration":"{Fill...}","durationDescription":"Fill","end":"{Auto...}","endPeriodDescription":"End","formula":"{NotApplicable: No values required for these periods...}","formulaDescription":"No values required for these periods","hasError":false,"id":"-PdjgP9oVsm2mHq67JH-","modelFormulaType":"NotApplicable","start":"{Auto...}","startPeriodDescription":"Auto (2021)"}]},"warnings":["Unknown property: 'timeSegments'.'assumptionIds'. Use help to see available properties."]}
[THINKING]: **Considering schema structure**

I’m weighing whether I need an exact nested schema, but it seems like properties could support a timeSegments array with elements like start, duration, end, and modelFormulaType. The assumptions object could help, even though the TimeSegment guidance is missing. It's risky since the schema doesn’t explicitly list assumptions. An alternative could be to create a constant formula for the start year as `2020`, because the user specifically asked for that constant assumption variable.**Evaluating formula options**

I’m thinking through an Excel formula using the IF function with a potential YEAR function. I assumed YEAR(Periods) exists, but I haven’t verified that yet. If Periods returns a date, comparing it to an integer might not work right. Perhaps I should compare it to DATE(2020,12,31) for clarity. I'll also need current year numbers for calculations, and a safer approach might involve creating a date-type helper. It seems important to handle variables correctly in JSON too.**Considering formula adjustments**

I'm exploring the equality operator in Excel functions, especially within IF statements. Although the syntax docs didn't clearly mention comparisons, they did show examples with greater-than operators. There's a potential issue with using scalar and dimensional variables with IF, MIN, and MAX functions. Another concern is the recursive self-reference for "Last actual % takeup of device," which might need time segments to prevent circular references. I believe using IF(YEAR(Periods)<=startyear, historic, self[-1]) could address this. It seems updating the default calculation for components might help too.**Examining forecast variables**

I think we should incorporate a toggle in the main forecast formula to ensure that only flagged device types use the endpoint forecast. Currently, the variable is set to the entire endpoint forecast, but maybe it should always calculate interpolation, regardless of the toggle. I see that the user asked for the formula to be applied to the forecast period of this variable. Since a toggle already exists, I should consider gating it to prevent values for non-endpoint devices. Inspecting the root variables might help clarify things further.**Considering time segments setup**

I’m thinking about whether timeSegments should include modelFormulaType. It seems like it might be auto-set if the assumptions object is present according to the documentation, so I could probably omit it. For defaultFormulaType, I’ll use "Assumptions" with unitOption defined as unitless and timeless. I’m also looking at isConstant being true, with dataType as Integer and a potential numberFormatId of General. The name could be "End point interpolation start year," and the timeSegments will just auto-fill with assumptions values like [["2020"]]. I hope this will work!**Clarifying formula formatting**

I'm thinking about how the formulaText parser might need the variable name formatted correctly. It seems like for a variable containing quotes, I might need to escape those quotes by doubling them up, similar to how strings work in Excel. So, for a variable name like `"End point" forecast end year`, I could try using `"\"End point\" forecast end year"` as a JSON string instead. It's a little tricky, but I think that might work!**Simplifying variables for formulas**

I need to focus on just the end year assumption and end year % takeup for the main formula. I think about creating a simpler helper variable that copies the end year assumption, but the end year integer is necessary for weight calculations. I could set up a calculation for “End point interpolation end year,” but I still need to refer to the quoted name. It seems safer to create helper variables referencing the quoted names separately to avoid potential parser errors, even though I can't do it interactively.**Considering model actions**

I should retrieve verify-model first since there's been significant work done. Maybe I’ll use GetInstructions for verify-model and look into get-model-health too. Although the instructions say to use get-model-health, I'm uncertain about the model action parameters. It's tricky since I've previously attempted help but got an invalid response. Maybe I can just validate the layout or check created variable details incrementally. I think I'll stick to a sequential approach due to dependencies instead of going parallel.**Creating assumptions**

I need to create an assumption variable, which might be easier as an inline assumption. However, there's also the option of creating ModelAssumption separately. I think it makes sense to create the modelAssumption first. But before I do that, I need to confirm if QueryObject supports creating an object_type for ModelAssumption. Since I already know the payload, I believe it’s time to proceed with creating the assumption. Just need to add a comment about it!
[ASSISTANT]: I’m creating the constant start-year assumption first, then the carry-forward helper, the interpolation weight, and finally I’ll wire the main forecast Variable to use them.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create interpolation start assumption", object_type="ModelAssumption", parameters={"dataType":"Integer","format":"structured","numberFormatId":"General","prefix":"End point interpolation start year","unit":{"unitParts":[{"timeType":"Timeless"}]},"values":{"Base":{"localInputValue":"2020","modelAssumptionValueType":"LocalInput"}}})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"data":{"modelAssumption":{"dataType":"Integer","date":"[no date/time]","defaultValue":"Local Input: 2020","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yldj","isInLayout":"No","isUsed":"No","numberFormat":"General","prefix":"End point interpolation start year","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"},"success":true},"warnings":["Unknown parameter 'format' ignored"]}
[ASSISTANT]: The assumption is in place. Now I’m creating the matching constant assumption Variable and the two calculation helpers in one go, using the same dimensions as the existing forecast/historic Variables.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create interpolation helper vars", object_type="Variable", parameters={"bulk":true,"items":[{"dataType":"Integer","defaultAssumptionId":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yldj","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","isConstant":true,"name":"End point interpolation start year","numberFormatId":"General","timeSegments":[{"duration":{"segmentDurationType":"Auto"},"modelFormulaType":"Assumptions","start":{"segmentPeriodType":"Auto"}}],"unit":{"unitParts":[{"timeType":"Timeless"}]}},{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"IF(YEAR(Periods) \u003c= \"End point interpolation start year\", \"% takeup of device (historic)\", \"Last actual % takeup of device\"[-1])"},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","isConstant":false,"name":"Last actual % takeup of device","numberFormatId":"Pct1Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PdiHAQz-DLqL0tEIrQv"},{"tagId":"-PdiHAQz-DLqL0tEIvrR"}]},"unit":{"unitParts":[{"timeType":"Timeless"}]},"unitOption":"Defined"},{"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"MIN(1, MAX(0, (YEAR(Periods) - \"End point interpolation start year\") / (\"End point\" forecast end year - \"End point interpolation start year\")))"},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","isConstant":false,"name":"End point interpolation weight","numberFormatId":"Pct1Dp","unit":{"unitParts":[{"timeType":"Timeless"}]},"unitOption":"Defined"}],"mode":"atomic"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"bulk":true,"failed":2,"message":"Bulk operation stopped at item 3 due to error (atomic mode)","mode":"atomic","processed":3,"results":[{"contentType":"application/json","data":{"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"value":"2020"},"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2ynEz","isConstant":"True","name":"End point interpolation start year","numberFormat":"General","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: 1 assumption","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}},"success":true},{"error":"Parameter preprocessing error: defaultCalculation.formulaText: Unexpected 'Last actual % takeup of device', expected valid variable name (Hint: Variable 'Last actual % takeup of device' not found in Model)","errorCode":"INVALID_PARAMETER","success":false},{"error":"Parameter preprocessing error: defaultCalculation.formulaText: Unexpected 'End point', expected valid variable name (Hint: Variable 'End point' not found in Model)","errorCode":"INVALID_PARAMETER","success":false}],"succeeded":1,"success":false}
[THINKING]: **Investigating variable creation**

I need to recover and possibly create helpers in sequence. There seems to be an error due to quoting the "End point" variable, which might be caused by incorrect string escaping. I can’t create a self-referenced variable because it doesn't exist yet. Should I create it with no default calculation, then update it? Maybe I can use double quotes inside the variable name or inspect the existing names to see if they include quotes. I have to understand the parser's escaping rules for this!**Clarifying formula syntax**

I think the formula text should be `"\"End point\" forecast end year"`, but it seems that through JSON conversion, it became `"End point" forecast end year`, causing a parsing issue. The error indicates that the parser couldn’t find the variable ‘End point.’ This means I need to use doubled internal quotes inside my quoted identifier, which should be `"""End point"" forecast end year"` to include the literal quotes. I might also create the last helper first using a temporary formula. It sounds like a plan!**Reviewing variable syntax**

I need to consider that the variable might be `"End point" forecast end year`, and I should use a formula syntax identifier with embedded quotes, which will likely look like `"""End point"" forecast end year"`. I might also need to apply the same syntax for variations like `"End point" forecast end year % takeup` and `"End point" forecast % takeup of device`. Updating the existing forecast variable syntax sounds necessary, and I should ensure I've got that exact syntax down for endpoint % takeup with doubled internal quotes. It seems that creating the assumption variable worked well!
[ASSISTANT]: The start-year assumption Variable created successfully. Two formula issues came up:
- the self-referencing helper can’t be created with a self-reference until it exists
- variable names that contain literal quotes need **doubled internal quotes** in `formulaText`

I’m fixing that by creating the helper first with a temporary formula, then updating it, and then wiring the main forecast Variable.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Check created start year variable", object_type="Variable", parameters={"format":"structured","limit":10,"name":"*End point interpolation start year*"})
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="filter", explanation="Check helper variable absence", object_type="Variable", parameters={"$or":[{"name":"*Last actual % takeup of device*"},{"name":"*End point interpolation weight*"}],"format":"structured","limit":10})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":1,"variables":[{"calculation":"-","defaultFormulaType":"Assumptions","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2ynEz","isConstant":"True","name":"End point interpolation start year","numberFormat":"General","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: 1 assumption","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}]}
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"count":0,"variables":[]}
[ASSISTANT]: I’ve confirmed only the start-year Variable exists so far. I’m now creating the carry-forward helper with a temporary base formula, then the interpolation weight, then updating the carry-forward and main forecast formulas with corrected quoting.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create carry-forward helper temp", object_type="Variable", parameters={"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"\"% takeup of device (historic)\""},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","isConstant":false,"name":"Last actual % takeup of device","numberFormatId":"Pct1Dp","tagParents":{"parents":[{"tagId":"-PdiHAQz-DLqL0tEIrQv"},{"tagId":"-PdiHAQz-DLqL0tEIvrR"}]},"unit":{"unitParts":[{"timeType":"Timeless"}]},"unitOption":"Defined"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"dimensions":{"15-24/Any TV":"N/A","15-24/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"N/A","15-24/Car: AM/FM radio":"N/A","15-24/Car: Connected car":"N/A","15-24/Car: DAB radio":"N/A","15-24/Desktop computer":"N/A","15-24/Digital music player":"N/A","15-24/Home: AM/FM radio":"N/A","15-24/Home: Any radio":"N/A","15-24/Home: DAB radio":"N/A","15-24/Home: Internet radio":"N/A","15-24/Laptop computer":"N/A","15-24/Smart TV":"N/A","15-24/Smartphone":"N/A","15-24/Standard mobile phone":"N/A","15-24/Tablet":"N/A","15-24/Voice activated speaker":"N/A","15-24/Wearable technology":"N/A","25-34/Any TV":"N/A","25-34/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"N/A","25-34/Car: AM/FM radio":"N/A","25-34/Car: Connected car":"N/A","25-34/Car: DAB radio":"N/A","25-34/Desktop computer":"N/A","25-34/Digital music player":"N/A","25-34/Home: AM/FM radio":"N/A","25-34/Home: Any radio":"N/A","25-34/Home: DAB radio":"N/A","25-34/Home: Internet radio":"N/A","25-34/Laptop computer":"N/A","25-34/Smart TV":"N/A","25-34/Smartphone":"N/A","25-34/Standard mobile phone":"N/A","25-34/Tablet":"N/A","25-34/Voice activated speaker":"N/A","25-34/Wearable technology":"N/A","35-54/Any TV":"N/A","35-54/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"N/A","35-54/Car: AM/FM radio":"N/A","35-54/Car: Connected car":"N/A","35-54/Car: DAB radio":"N/A","35-54/Desktop computer":"N/A","35-54/Digital music player":"N/A","35-54/Home: AM/FM radio":"N/A","35-54/Home: Any radio":"N/A","35-54/Home: DAB radio":"N/A","35-54/Home: Internet radio":"N/A","35-54/Laptop computer":"N/A","35-54/Smart TV":"N/A","35-54/Smartphone":"N/A","35-54/Standard mobile phone":"N/A","35-54/Tablet":"N/A","35-54/Voice activated speaker":"N/A","35-54/Wearable technology":"N/A","55+/Any TV":"N/A","55+/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"N/A","55+/Car: AM/FM radio":"N/A","55+/Car: Connected car":"N/A","55+/Car: DAB radio":"N/A","55+/Desktop computer":"N/A","55+/Digital music player":"N/A","55+/Home: AM/FM radio":"N/A","55+/Home: Any radio":"N/A","55+/Home: DAB radio":"N/A","55+/Home: Internet radio":"N/A","55+/Laptop computer":"N/A","55+/Smart TV":"N/A","55+/Smartphone":"N/A","55+/Standard mobile phone":"N/A","55+/Tablet":"N/A","55+/Voice activated speaker":"N/A","55+/Wearable technology":"N/A"},"growthRate":"-1.3% per period","note":"Variable has no summary line","sample":{"2016":"55.5%","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"},"trend":"stable"},"calculation":"% takeup of device (historic) [Auto]","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"\"% takeup of device (historic)\"","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yowA","isConstant":"False","name":"Last actual % takeup of device","numberFormat":"0.0%","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: Auto","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}}
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="create", explanation="Create interpolation weight", object_type="Variable", parameters={"dataType":"Double","defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"MIN(1, MAX(0, (YEAR(Periods) - \"End point interpolation start year\") / (\"\"\"End point\"\" forecast end year\" - \"End point interpolation start year\")))"},"defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","isConstant":false,"name":"End point interpolation weight","numberFormatId":"Pct1Dp","unit":{"unitParts":[{"timeType":"Timeless"}]},"unitOption":"Defined"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"growthRate":"+23.2% per period","sample":{"2016":"0.0%","2026":"40.0%","2035":"100.0%"},"trend":"growing"},"calculation":"MIN ( 1 , MAX ( 0 , ( YEAR ( Periods ) - End point interpolation start year ) / ( \"End point\" forecast end year - End point interpolation start year ) ) )","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"MIN(1, MAX(0, (YEAR(Periods) - End point interpolation start year) / (\"\"\"End point\"\" forecast end year\" - End point interpolation start year)))","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2ypr4","isConstant":"False","name":"End point interpolation weight","numberFormat":"0.0%","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: Auto","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}}
[ASSISTANT]: Both helper Variables now exist. I’m updating the carry-forward helper to the recursive formula, then updating the main forecast Variable to use the interpolation formula. After that I’ll spot-check values.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="update", explanation="Update carry-forward helper formula", object_type="Variable", parameters={"defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"IF(YEAR(Periods) \u003c= \"End point interpolation start year\", \"% takeup of device (historic)\", \"Last actual % takeup of device\"[-1])"},"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yowA"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"dimensions":{"15-24/Any TV":"97.0%","15-24/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"65.9%","15-24/Car: AM/FM radio":"35.0%","15-24/Car: Connected car":"50.0%","15-24/Car: DAB radio":"41.0%","15-24/Desktop computer":"52.4%","15-24/Digital music player":"22.7%","15-24/Home: AM/FM radio":"22.0%","15-24/Home: Any radio":"43.0%","15-24/Home: DAB radio":"27.0%","15-24/Home: Internet radio":"0.0%","15-24/Laptop computer":"91.0%","15-24/Smart TV":"73.8%","15-24/Smartphone":"96.4%","15-24/Standard mobile phone":"2.0%","15-24/Tablet":"60.3%","15-24/Voice activated speaker":"40.3%","15-24/Wearable technology":"33.8%","25-34/Any TV":"96.0%","25-34/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"52.9%","25-34/Car: AM/FM radio":"38.0%","25-34/Car: Connected car":"49.0%","25-34/Car: DAB radio":"40.0%","25-34/Desktop computer":"48.0%","25-34/Digital music player":"34.6%","25-34/Home: AM/FM radio":"15.0%","25-34/Home: Any radio":"42.0%","25-34/Home: DAB radio":"29.0%","25-34/Home: Internet radio":"0.0%","25-34/Laptop computer":"91.7%","25-34/Smart TV":"73.8%","25-34/Smartphone":"92.2%","25-34/Standard mobile phone":"1.0%","25-34/Tablet":"65.2%","25-34/Voice activated speaker":"41.5%","25-34/Wearable technology":"42.6%","35-54/Any TV":"98.0%","35-54/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"52.9%","35-54/Car: AM/FM radio":"38.0%","35-54/Car: Connected car":"45.0%","35-54/Car: DAB radio":"40.0%","35-54/Desktop computer":"50.3%","35-54/Digital music player":"38.6%","35-54/Home: AM/FM radio":"21.0%","35-54/Home: Any radio":"59.0%","35-54/Home: DAB radio":"44.0%","35-54/Home: Internet radio":"0.0%","35-54/Laptop computer":"85.6%","35-54/Smart TV":"75.0%","35-54/Smartphone":"92.2%","35-54/Standard mobile phone":"3.5%","35-54/Tablet":"75.4%","35-54/Voice activated speaker":"39.6%","35-54/Wearable technology":"37.6%","55+/Any TV":"98.0%","55+/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"27.5%","55+/Car: AM/FM radio":"42.0%","55+/Car: Connected car":"27.0%","55+/Car: DAB radio":"37.0%","55+/Desktop computer":"47.2%","55+/Digital music player":"27.0%","55+/Home: AM/FM radio":"54.0%","55+/Home: Any radio":"77.0%","55+/Home: DAB radio":"44.0%","55+/Home: Internet radio":"0.0%","55+/Laptop computer":"65.6%","55+/Smart TV":"53.7%","55+/Smartphone":"64.5%","55+/Standard mobile phone":"20.5%","55+/Tablet":"59.6%","55+/Voice activated speaker":"21.3%","55+/Wearable technology":"15.2%"},"growthRate":"-0.3% per period","note":"Variable has no summary line","sample":{"2016":"55.5%","2026":"52.4%","2035":"52.4%"},"trend":"stable"},"calculation":"IF ( YEAR ( Periods ) \u003c= End point interpolation start year , % takeup of device (historic) [Auto] , Last actual % takeup of device [Auto]  [-1] )","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"IF(YEAR(Periods) \u003c= End point interpolation start year, \"% takeup of device (historic)\", Last actual % takeup of device[-1])","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yowA","isConstant":"False","name":"Last actual % takeup of device","numberFormat":"0.0%","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2035`: Auto","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}}
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="update", explanation="Update forecast interpolation formula", object_type="Variable", parameters={"defaultCalculation":{"formulaText":"\"Last actual % takeup of device\" + \"End point interpolation weight\" * (\"\"\"End point\"\" forecast end year % takeup\" - \"Last actual % takeup of device\")"},"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yhph"})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"success":true,"variable":{"calculatedValues":{"dimensions":{"15-24/Any TV":"95.0%","15-24/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"20.0%","15-24/Car: AM/FM radio":"2.9%","15-24/Car: Connected car":"0.0%","15-24/Car: DAB radio":"77.3%","15-24/Desktop computer":"20.0%","15-24/Digital music player":"10.0%","15-24/Home: AM/FM radio":"0.0%","15-24/Home: Any radio":"0.0%","15-24/Home: DAB radio":"0.0%","15-24/Home: Internet radio":"0.0%","15-24/Laptop computer":"93.0%","15-24/Smart TV":"90.0%","15-24/Smartphone":"98.0%","15-24/Standard mobile phone":"1.0%","15-24/Tablet":"55.0%","15-24/Voice activated speaker":"0.0%","15-24/Wearable technology":"40.0%","25-34/Any TV":"94.0%","25-34/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"30.0%","25-34/Car: AM/FM radio":"2.9%","25-34/Car: Connected car":"0.0%","25-34/Car: DAB radio":"77.3%","25-34/Desktop computer":"25.0%","25-34/Digital music player":"20.0%","25-34/Home: AM/FM radio":"0.0%","25-34/Home: Any radio":"0.0%","25-34/Home: DAB radio":"0.0%","25-34/Home: Internet radio":"0.0%","25-34/Laptop computer":"85.0%","25-34/Smart TV":"93.0%","25-34/Smartphone":"95.0%","25-34/Standard mobile phone":"1.0%","25-34/Tablet":"65.0%","25-34/Voice activated speaker":"0.0%","25-34/Wearable technology":"45.0%","35-54/Any TV":"96.0%","35-54/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"25.0%","35-54/Car: AM/FM radio":"2.9%","35-54/Car: Connected car":"0.0%","35-54/Car: DAB radio":"77.3%","35-54/Desktop computer":"30.0%","35-54/Digital music player":"20.0%","35-54/Home: AM/FM radio":"0.0%","35-54/Home: Any radio":"0.0%","35-54/Home: DAB radio":"0.0%","35-54/Home: Internet radio":"0.0%","35-54/Laptop computer":"80.0%","35-54/Smart TV":"95.0%","35-54/Smartphone":"93.0%","35-54/Standard mobile phone":"2.0%","35-54/Tablet":"70.0%","35-54/Voice activated speaker":"0.0%","35-54/Wearable technology":"45.0%","55+/Any TV":"98.0%","55+/Bluetooth/wireless speaker":"35.0%","55+/Car: AM/FM radio":"2.9%","55+/Car: Connected car":"0.0%","55+/Car: DAB radio":"77.3%","55+/Desktop computer":"35.0%","55+/Digital music player":"15.0%","55+/Home: AM/FM radio":"0.0%","55+/Home: Any radio":"0.0%","55+/Home: DAB radio":"0.0%","55+/Home: Internet radio":"0.0%","55+/Laptop computer":"55.0%","55+/Smart TV":"85.0%","55+/Smartphone":"80.0%","55+/Standard mobile phone":"10.0%","55+/Tablet":"60.0%","55+/Voice activated speaker":"0.0%","55+/Wearable technology":"35.0%"},"growthRate":"-6.4% per period","note":"Variable has no summary line","sample":{"2016":"N/A","2026":"39.4%","2035":"20.0%"},"trend":"declining"},"calculation":"Last actual % takeup of device [Auto] + End point interpolation weight * ( \"End point\" forecast end year % takeup [Auto] - Last actual % takeup of device [Auto] )","defaultFormulaType":"Calculation","formulaText":"Last actual % takeup of device + End point interpolation weight * (\"\"\"End point\"\" forecast end year % takeup\" - Last actual % takeup of device)","id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yhph","isConstant":"False","name":"\"End point\" forecast % takeup of device","numberFormat":"0.0%","timeSegments":"`2016 - 2020`: No values required for these periods; `2021 - 2035`: Auto","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"}}
[ASSISTANT]: The formulas are now in place. I’m doing a quick value check around the key years to confirm the interpolation starts from the last actual and lands on the endpoint in 2035.
[TOOL]: QueryObject(action="other", explanation="Check interpolation years", object_type="Variable", otherAction="get-values", parameters={"case":"Base/Base","dimensions":["15-24/Desktop computer","55+/Smartphone","15-24/Voice activated speaker"],"format":"structured","ids":["-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yhph","-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yowA","-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2ypr4"],"includeAnalysis":false,"periods":["2020","2021","2026","2035"]})
[TOOL_RESULT]: {"case":"Base/Base","periodsReturned":["2020","2021","2026","2035"],"variables":[{"dimensions":[{"path":"15-24/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"50.2%","2026":"39.4%","2035":"20.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"91.1%","2026":"91.8%","2035":"93.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Tablet","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"59.9%","2026":"58.2%","2035":"55.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"21.9%","2026":"17.6%","2035":"10.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"96.5%","2026":"97.0%","2035":"98.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"1.9%","2026":"1.6%","2035":"1.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Any TV","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"96.9%","2026":"96.2%","2035":"95.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"74.9%","2026":"80.3%","2035":"90.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"34.2%","2026":"36.3%","2035":"40.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"37.6%","2026":"24.2%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"43.4%","2026":"55.5%","2035":"77.3%"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"46.7%","2026":"30.0%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"40.1%","2026":"25.8%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"25.2%","2026":"16.2%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"0.0%","2026":"0.0%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"46.5%","2026":"38.8%","2035":"25.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"91.3%","2026":"89.0%","2035":"85.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Tablet","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"65.2%","2026":"65.1%","2035":"65.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"33.6%","2026":"28.8%","2035":"20.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"92.4%","2026":"93.3%","2035":"95.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"1.0%","2026":"1.0%","2035":"1.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Any TV","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"95.9%","2026":"95.2%","2035":"94.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"75.1%","2026":"81.5%","2035":"93.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"42.8%","2026":"43.6%","2035":"45.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"38.7%","2026":"24.9%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"42.5%","2026":"54.9%","2035":"77.3%"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"45.7%","2026":"29.4%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"39.2%","2026":"25.2%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"27.1%","2026":"17.4%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"0.0%","2026":"0.0%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"48.9%","2026":"42.2%","2035":"30.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"85.2%","2026":"83.4%","2035":"80.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Tablet","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"75.0%","2026":"73.2%","2035":"70.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"37.4%","2026":"31.2%","2035":"20.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"92.3%","2026":"92.5%","2035":"93.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"3.4%","2026":"2.9%","2035":"2.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Any TV","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"97.9%","2026":"97.2%","2035":"96.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"76.3%","2026":"83.0%","2035":"95.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"38.1%","2026":"40.6%","2035":"45.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"37.0%","2026":"23.8%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"42.5%","2026":"54.9%","2035":"77.3%"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"42.0%","2026":"27.0%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"55.1%","2026":"35.4%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"41.1%","2026":"26.4%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"0.0%","2026":"0.0%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"46.4%","2026":"42.3%","2035":"35.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"64.9%","2026":"61.4%","2035":"55.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Tablet","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"59.6%","2026":"59.8%","2035":"60.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"26.2%","2026":"22.2%","2035":"15.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"65.5%","2026":"70.7%","2035":"80.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"19.8%","2026":"16.3%","2035":"10.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Any TV","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"98.0%","2026":"98.0%","2035":"98.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"55.8%","2026":"66.2%","2035":"85.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"16.5%","2026":"23.1%","2035":"35.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"19.9%","2026":"12.8%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"39.7%","2026":"53.1%","2035":"77.3%"}},{"path":"55+/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"25.2%","2026":"16.2%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"71.9%","2026":"46.2%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"41.1%","2026":"26.4%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"0.0%","2026":"0.0%","2035":"0.0%"}}],"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yhph","name":"\"End point\" forecast % takeup of device","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"},{"dimensions":[{"path":"15-24/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"52.4%","2021":"52.4%","2026":"52.4%","2035":"52.4%"}},{"path":"15-24/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"91.0%","2021":"91.0%","2026":"91.0%","2035":"91.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Tablet","values":{"2020":"60.3%","2021":"60.3%","2026":"60.3%","2035":"60.3%"}},{"path":"15-24/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"22.7%","2021":"22.7%","2026":"22.7%","2035":"22.7%"}},{"path":"15-24/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"96.4%","2021":"96.4%","2026":"96.4%","2035":"96.4%"}},{"path":"15-24/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"2.0%","2021":"2.0%","2026":"2.0%","2035":"2.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Any TV","values":{"2020":"97.0%","2021":"97.0%","2026":"97.0%","2035":"97.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"73.8%","2021":"73.8%","2026":"73.8%","2035":"73.8%"}},{"path":"15-24/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"33.8%","2021":"33.8%","2026":"33.8%","2035":"33.8%"}},{"path":"15-24/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"40.3%","2021":"40.3%","2026":"40.3%","2035":"40.3%"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"41.0%","2021":"41.0%","2026":"41.0%","2035":"41.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"50.0%","2021":"50.0%","2026":"50.0%","2035":"50.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"43.0%","2021":"43.0%","2026":"43.0%","2035":"43.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"27.0%","2021":"27.0%","2026":"27.0%","2035":"27.0%"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"15-24/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"0.0%","2021":"0.0%","2026":"0.0%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"48.0%","2021":"48.0%","2026":"48.0%","2035":"48.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"91.7%","2021":"91.7%","2026":"91.7%","2035":"91.7%"}},{"path":"25-34/Tablet","values":{"2020":"65.2%","2021":"65.2%","2026":"65.2%","2035":"65.2%"}},{"path":"25-34/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"34.6%","2021":"34.6%","2026":"34.6%","2035":"34.6%"}},{"path":"25-34/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"92.2%","2021":"92.2%","2026":"92.2%","2035":"92.2%"}},{"path":"25-34/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"1.0%","2021":"1.0%","2026":"1.0%","2035":"1.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Any TV","values":{"2020":"96.0%","2021":"96.0%","2026":"96.0%","2035":"96.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"73.8%","2021":"73.8%","2026":"73.8%","2035":"73.8%"}},{"path":"25-34/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"42.6%","2021":"42.6%","2026":"42.6%","2035":"42.6%"}},{"path":"25-34/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"41.5%","2021":"41.5%","2026":"41.5%","2035":"41.5%"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"40.0%","2021":"40.0%","2026":"40.0%","2035":"40.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"49.0%","2021":"49.0%","2026":"49.0%","2035":"49.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"42.0%","2021":"42.0%","2026":"42.0%","2035":"42.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"29.0%","2021":"29.0%","2026":"29.0%","2035":"29.0%"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"25-34/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"0.0%","2021":"0.0%","2026":"0.0%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"50.3%","2021":"50.3%","2026":"50.3%","2035":"50.3%"}},{"path":"35-54/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"85.6%","2021":"85.6%","2026":"85.6%","2035":"85.6%"}},{"path":"35-54/Tablet","values":{"2020":"75.4%","2021":"75.4%","2026":"75.4%","2035":"75.4%"}},{"path":"35-54/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"38.6%","2021":"38.6%","2026":"38.6%","2035":"38.6%"}},{"path":"35-54/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"92.2%","2021":"92.2%","2026":"92.2%","2035":"92.2%"}},{"path":"35-54/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"3.5%","2021":"3.5%","2026":"3.5%","2035":"3.5%"}},{"path":"35-54/Any TV","values":{"2020":"98.0%","2021":"98.0%","2026":"98.0%","2035":"98.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"75.0%","2021":"75.0%","2026":"75.0%","2035":"75.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"37.6%","2021":"37.6%","2026":"37.6%","2035":"37.6%"}},{"path":"35-54/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"39.6%","2021":"39.6%","2026":"39.6%","2035":"39.6%"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"40.0%","2021":"40.0%","2026":"40.0%","2035":"40.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"45.0%","2021":"45.0%","2026":"45.0%","2035":"45.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"59.0%","2021":"59.0%","2026":"59.0%","2035":"59.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"44.0%","2021":"44.0%","2026":"44.0%","2035":"44.0%"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"35-54/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"0.0%","2021":"0.0%","2026":"0.0%","2035":"0.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Desktop computer","values":{"2020":"47.2%","2021":"47.2%","2026":"47.2%","2035":"47.2%"}},{"path":"55+/Laptop computer","values":{"2020":"65.6%","2021":"65.6%","2026":"65.6%","2035":"65.6%"}},{"path":"55+/Tablet","values":{"2020":"59.6%","2021":"59.6%","2026":"59.6%","2035":"59.6%"}},{"path":"55+/Digital music player","values":{"2020":"27.0%","2021":"27.0%","2026":"27.0%","2035":"27.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Smartphone","values":{"2020":"64.5%","2021":"64.5%","2026":"64.5%","2035":"64.5%"}},{"path":"55+/Standard mobile phone","values":{"2020":"20.5%","2021":"20.5%","2026":"20.5%","2035":"20.5%"}},{"path":"55+/Any TV","values":{"2020":"98.0%","2021":"98.0%","2026":"98.0%","2035":"98.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Smart TV","values":{"2020":"53.7%","2021":"53.7%","2026":"53.7%","2035":"53.7%"}},{"path":"55+/Bluetooth/wireless speaker","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Wearable technology","values":{"2020":"15.2%","2021":"15.2%","2026":"15.2%","2035":"15.2%"}},{"path":"55+/Voice activated speaker","values":{"2020":"21.3%","2021":"21.3%","2026":"21.3%","2035":"21.3%"}},{"path":"55+/Car: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"37.0%","2021":"37.0%","2026":"37.0%","2035":"37.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Car: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Car: Connected car","values":{"2020":"27.0%","2021":"27.0%","2026":"27.0%","2035":"27.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Any radio","values":{"2020":"77.0%","2021":"77.0%","2026":"77.0%","2035":"77.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: DAB radio","values":{"2020":"44.0%","2021":"44.0%","2026":"44.0%","2035":"44.0%"}},{"path":"55+/Home: AM/FM radio","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}},{"path":"55+/Home: Internet radio","values":{"2020":"0.0%","2021":"0.0%","2026":"0.0%","2035":"0.0%"}}],"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2yowA","name":"Last actual % takeup of device","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]"},{"id":"-Pdo6HWuVo_at8Z2ypr4","name":"End point interpolation weight","unit":"Unitless [Timeless]","values":{"2020":"N/A","2021":"N/A","2026":"N/A","2035":"N/A"}}]}
[THINKING]: **Explaining results clearly**

I need to respond concisely and explain the results. I see there's a problem with the weight variable returning N/A in get-values, likely due to an incompatible dimension filter parameter. Even though the main forecast works, the weight variable seems to have issues. I should mention that the earlier endpoint weight sample was fine. It's also good to note that some historical variable combinations remain N/A and that we didn’t include "end point" forecasts since they weren't requested.**Validating model health**

I could mention that the actual formula logic works with examples. It might be a good idea to validate the model's health after all the significant work done. I should retrieve the instructions for the verify-model and maybe check the model's health using the appropriate tools: GetInstructions for verify-model and ModelAction for get-model-health. Since we've done substantial work, it feels crucial to ensure everything is functioning correctly. Let's proceed with that.
[ASSISTANT]: I’ve built the interpolation structure and the core values are behaving as expected. I’m doing one final model health check now so I can confirm there aren’t any unintended formula or unit issues.
[TOOL]: GetInstructions(action="get", explanation="Verify model workflow", parameters={"category":"verify-model","format":"compact"})
[TOOL]: ModelAction(action="get-model-health", explanation="Run model health check", parameters={"format":"structured","help":false,"model_id":""})
</conversation>
